<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematyps="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 34 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 34 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-14">May 14, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-14" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="151-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-Hd1e97">Chapter 34</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e99">
          Chapter 34
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e104">
          The same ought to be concluded about the crime of sacrificing human beings,
          which is said to be in use among them.
          For war is not just on these grounds,
          both from what was said above (namely) 
          that the truth can hardly be signified to them briefly through envoys announced,
          and also because the Indians are not bound to put faith in the Spaniards,
          even if they repeat the truth to them a thousand times.
          Why should they believe a people proud,
          greedy,
          fierce,
          rapacious?
          Or why should they depart from the religion of their ancestors,
          confirmed by the consensus of so many centuries,
          strengthened by the authority of so many wise men,
          at the warning of a people whose miracles do not confirm their faith,
          nor do their vices commend it?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e153">
          For the Indians worshiping idols,
          although they cannot be excused before God,
          are nevertheless entirely excused before men for a double reason.
          First,
          because they follow a probable error,
          for according to the Philosopher in Topics 1,
          that is called probable which all men approve,
          or the greater part of the wise,
          or those whose wisdom is more approved.
          Again in Rhetoric 1 chapter 20 he says:
          That ought necessarily to be considered good or better which all or the greater part of the prudent judge to be good,
          or those who are considered more prudent,
          even if there is one who judges it good.
          And such decrees approved by these opinions are said to be morally certain according to the same Philosopher 
          in Ethics 1 chapter 2,
          whom all philosophers as well as theologians follow.
          But when the opinion about the gods and the sacrifices to be offered to them,
          and from which things sacrifice ought to be made,
          is approved by the consensus of all nations known to the Indians,
          and these are worshiped by those whom they believe to be sacred and divine men (namely) by the priests,
          and the cult of idols is confirmed by the decrees of laws and the sanctions of princes,
          with threats and penalties added against transgressors,
          finally when idols are worshiped not secretly but publicly and religiously 
          in temples from most ancient centuries,
          certainly it is most manifest that they err probably.
          Nor is it to be wondered at if they do not immediately awaken at the first voice of our people.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e229">
          And especially they err probably concerning the custom of sacrificing human victims,
          since ancient histories both of pagans and also of Catholics testify 
          that almost all peoples were accustomed to do the same.
          For thus Eusebius says in On the Preparation for the Gospel book 4 chapter 7:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-Qd1e246">
            All men commonly,
            when the appointed day comes on which they were accustomed to sacrifice a man,
            sprinkle the altar with human blood;
            it was the custom of the ancients in great calamities and dangers 
            that the prince of the city or nation would hand over the most beloved of his children 
            to the avenging demon as if a price of redemption,
            and thus the one handed over was mystically slaughtered
          </quote>.
          And below: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-Qd1e266">
            the sacrifices of men are demanded,
            namely by demons,
            who falling upon many cities and peoples not infrequently 
            like common plagues and lightning bolts,
            did not cease to harass men atrociously until they were placated with their blood
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e283">
          Again Clement in book 9 of the Recognitions to James the brother of the Lord 
          reports that certain peoples in the western Indies,
          which perhaps are these of ours,
          are accustomed to sacrifice arriving guests to their gods and afterwards to eat them,
          which Eusebius also writes in the place cited above.
          Moreover Lactantius in book 1 chapter 21 of the Divine Institutes says:
          There was (he says) a law among the Tauri,
          an inhuman and savage people,
          that a guest should be sacrificed to Diana,
          and this sacrifice was celebrated for many times.
          The Gauls placated Esus and Teutates with human blood.
          Nor indeed were the Latins free from this savagery.
          For the Latian Jupiter is worshiped with human blood even now.
          But it is not to be wondered at concerning barbarians whose religion agrees with their customs;
          but our people who always claimed for themselves the glory of gentleness and humanity,
          are they not found more savage in these sacrilegious rites?
          And a little below:
          Nevertheless it appears that this rite of sacrificing men is ancient.
          They threw these in honor of Saturn from the Milvian bridge into the Tiber.
          But concerning innocent children he says:
          For what shall I say about the infants who were sacrificed to that same Saturn 
          because of hatred of Jupiter,
          I do not find.
          That men were so barbarous,
          so savage,
          that they should call parricide,
          that is,
          a crime foul and execrable to the human race,
          a sacrifice,
          when they extinguished tender and innocent souls,
          which is especially the age most sweet to parents,
          without any respect for piety,
          etc.
          And below:
          The Carthaginians were accustomed to sacrifice human victims to Saturn,
          and when they had been conquered by Agathocles king of Sicily,
          they sought to appease the god angry with them,
          and so that they might more diligently pay the expiation,
          they sacrificed two hundred sons of nobles,
          etc.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e396">
          Again 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-Rd1e398">
            Plutarch in the Problems page 465
          </ref>
          writes that the Romans did not punish certain barbarians who sacrificed men to the gods,
          because they learned they had done it by custom and law.
          Nevertheless Plutarch reports that the Romans did the same at some time.
          I will subjoin his words here:
          What is it that when the Romans had heard that certain barbarians had sacrificed a man to the immortal gods,
          their magistrates thought they should be summoned and punished,
          whom afterwards when they had learned that they had done this by a certain custom and law,
          they dismissed them and forbade them to do it otherwise,
          when they themselves not many years before had buried alive 
          two men and two women in the cattle market?
          For it does not seem fitting that they themselves should do these things 
          and reprove barbarians who had committed such things.
          Was sacrificing a man to the immortal gods considered impious,
          but to demons necessary?
          Or did they think those who did it by custom and law were sinning,
          but they themselves,
          commanded by the Sibylline books,
          did not think they were held by the same crime,
          etc.
          These are Plutarch's words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e450">
          Then Herodotus the Greek historiographer in book 4 page 299 
          narrates that the Scythians were accustomed to sacrifice to their gods 
          one out of every hundred captives in war.
          And then he writes that the Scytho-Taurian peoples who are in Germany 
          offer to Iphigenia daughter of Agamemnon 
          all who have suffered shipwreck and have been cast on shore,
          and likewise guests.
          The same Solinus writes in the Polyhistory chapter 20 and Pomponius Mela in book 2 chapter 1.
          Then Diodorus Siculus in book 6 folio 190 writes that the Galatians sacrifice to the gods 
          captives or those condemned for crimes.
          Our Spaniards who reproach the miserable Indian people for the sacrifices of men 
          were sacrificing captives and horses to Mars,
          which Strabo records in book 3 On the Geography of the World.
          He says some neighbors of the Durius river live according to the Spartan rite.
          And a little below:
          Devoted to sacrifices,
          they also seek divination especially from the intestines of these captives.
          They offer to the gods the severed right hands of captives.
          They use especially the he-goat which they also sacrifice to Mars,
          just as captives and horses,
          etc.
          These are Strabo's words.
          And concerning many other peoples he narrates similar things in the following books.
          And Polydore Vergil recorded very many things in book 5 chapter 8 
          On the Inventors of Things.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e512">
          Therefore since among so many peoples it was customary to sacrifice men to the gods,
          certainly the Indians sacrificing men for so many centuries err probably.
          We know indeed that in many regions of the world very famous philosophers lived.
          These nevertheless,
          although they knew that the stories about the gods were mere fables 
          and judged that divine honors should not be attributed to them 
          (of whose number were Seneca and Cicero),
          nevertheless did not wish to call the people away from the ancient custom 
          received for so many centuries,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-Rd1e545" target="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l6-Dd1e243">
            according to Augustine in the City of God book 6 chapter 10
          </ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e487-d1e547">
          Why therefore should it be thought that the Indians ought to depart 
          from a religion received for so many centuries,
          sanctioned by the laws of so many princes,
          confirmed by the example of so many wise men,
          at the exhortation of Christian soldiers,
          when they are barbarous peoples surpassing every impiety?
          Indeed they would be most fickle and worthy of reproof and punishment 
          in so arduous a matter and of such great moment 
          and most difficult desertion,
          as Chrysostom says in Homily 7 on 1 Corinthians,
          if they should put faith in them concerning this,
          with so many and such great testimonies of such authority among them set aside,
          until they are taught by more probable reasons,
          which cannot be done in a short time,
          that the Christian religion is more probable.
          Let those therefore be ashamed who are pleased that the gospel be preached with armed hand;
          they want men to be taught,
          they do not want them to be compelled.
          But they can in no way be taught briefly,
          obviously ignorant of our language and we of theirs,
          and prudently tenacious of their religion until they are convinced by reason.
          For no business is greater for man or more arduous 
          than to depart from a religion which he once put on,
          as we have said.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>