<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 19 [Bnf 12926 English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 19 [Bnf 12926 English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-02-05">Feb 05, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines 
          for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-02-05" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="89-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Hd1e97">Chapter 19 [Bnf 12926 English Translation]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e99">
          Chapter 19.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e104">
          From these things it is shown clearly enough in what manner a life adorned with virtues 
          in the preachers of the faith supplies the place of miracles,
          so that the unbelievers willingly hear the words of life 
          and see reasonably that those things are to be believed,
          and thus at last they may gain them for Christ.
          On the contrary, however, if it should be infected with crimes,
          especially with devastations of lands, 
          rapines,
          invasions, 
          and unjust occupations of the dominions 
          and possessions of those very unbelievers,
          and on account of this with innumerable of them killed 
          and slaughtered,
          just as in the western Indian regions we have always and continuously done,
          that we have been an impediment to their efficacious conversion 
          nothing can seem clearer.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e141">
          ¶ Wherefore we can gather that very many of the unbelievers are excused from the reception of the faith 
          for a long time 
          and perhaps for their whole life however long it may have lasted,
          as long as they see the most corrupt 
          <pb ed="#P" n="89-v"/>
          and detestable morals of the Christians,
          even if with such men religious men go for the sake of preaching 
          and preach in act.
          For they have sufficient impediments to believing,
          indeed to hearing and conversing with men of this kind,
          nay rather they have very many motives to the contrary,
          as appears 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e170">from the sayings of Chrysostom</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e173">
          For it is written 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e177">Ecclesiasticus 34</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Qd1e179" source="http://scta.info/resource/sir34_28">
            One builds up and another tears down,
            what does it profit them except labor?
          </quote>
          And the labor will be far greater if one preaches 
          and a thousand do the contrary.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e198">Scotus agrees in 4 Sententiarum distinction 3, question 4</ref>,
          where he says that no one is bound to any divine precept 
          unless it is promulgated to him by someone suitable and authentic,
          or by truthful report and the testimony of good men,
          which anyone ought reasonably to believe.
          Which Scotus understands concerning a divine positive precept or law,
          or human, 
          which is not known interiorly in the heart.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e224">
          ¶ But returning to the proposition, 
          such unbelievers have no one suitable or authentic 
          whom they ought reasonably to trust,
          nor is there among them truthful report,
          since they have not yet seen the preachers of the faith, 
          as we suppose, 
          nor the testimony of good men,
          since all of that kind are held by ignorance of unbelief.
          Therefore negative unbelievers will not always sin by worshiping idols.
          And consequently they will be punished illicitly on account of this,
          <pb ed="#P" n="90-r"/>
          that they worship idols, 
          by human judgment.
          Concerning which in my judgment there ought to be no ambiguity to anyone 
          through those things which have been alleged above.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e257">
          <add place="margin-right" hand="F">objection</add>
          ¶ There can also be adduced against the aforesaid the common opinion of all the holy doctors,
          namely that concerning those things which are of the faith 
          and of divine law and necessary for salvation,
          invincible ignorance cannot fall.
          Because if they did what is in them, 
          God is ready to illuminate them by His grace.
          Therefore if they are not illuminated, 
          it is on account of their fault,
          because they do not do what is in them, 
          and thus they sin.
          Therefore justly on account of that sin they can be punished even by human judgment.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e284">
          The assumption is clear through 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e288">
            Saint Thomas especially in De Veritate, question 14, article 11, ad 1
          </ref>,
          where speaking of a man raised among groves, 
          forests, 
          or wild beasts, 
          he says thus: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Qd1e297">
            For this pertains to divine providence,
            that it provide for each one concerning things necessary for salvation,
            provided he is not impeded on his part.
            For if someone should be nourished in the forests or among wolves,
            and followed the guidance of natural reason with the appetite for good and flight from evil,
            most certainly it is to be held that God would reveal through internal inspiration 
            those things which are necessary to be believed,
            or would direct some preacher of the faith,
            just as he sent 
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Nd1e320">Peter</name> 
            to 
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Nd1e323">Cornelius</name>, 
            Acts 10.
          </quote>
          These words of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Nd1e329">Saint Thomas</name>; 
          he teaches the same in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e331">Romans 10, lecture 3</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e337">
          <add place="margin-right" hand="F">objection</add>
          ¶ To this we respond first that not always to one doing what is in him 
          is God ready to illuminate through His grace,
          <pb ed="#P" n="90-v"/>
          unless it is from the intention of God that he be illuminated 
          and receive grace, 
          and then someone is infallibly illuminated and receives grace.
          Thus teaches 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e355" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1251-d1e651@8-137">
            Saint Thomas Prima Secundae, question 112, article 3 in the body
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e359" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1251-d1e699@6-59">ad 1</ref>,
          where he asks whether by necessity grace is given to one preparing himself for grace 
          or doing what is in him.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e367">
          And he responded that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Qd1e369" source="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1251-d1e651@24-122">
            preparation for grace can be considered in two ways:
            either according as it is from free will,
            and according to this it has no necessity to the obtaining of grace;
            or according as it is from God moving,
            and then it has necessity to that to which it is ordained by God,
            not indeed of coercion but of infallibility,
            because the intention of God cannot fail.
            Whence if it is from the intention of God moving that the man whose heart He moves 
            should obtain grace, 
            he infallibly obtains it,
          </quote>
          and so forth. 
          These words of Saint Thomas.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e396">
          Therefore since for those who are foreknown 
          and at last to be damned with the reprobate,
          it is not from the intention of God to impart grace or to illuminate them,
          however much they prepare themselves through free will or do what is in them,
          they will not obtain grace,
          and therefore then they do not sin by not receiving grace.
          Because not on account of a fault which is in them,
          since rather in them there is punishment than fault on account of original sin 
          according to Augustine, 
          where he will be alleged below,
          but because God does not will to illuminate them by His mere will,
          not on account of sins but because He does not will,
          from the fact that just as no cause of reprobation 
          <pb ed="#P" n="91-r"/>
          or predestination is given on our part,
          so sometimes no cause of the effect itself of reprobation is given;
          but the effect of reprobation is to deny grace 
          and the means necessary for the obtaining of grace.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e441">
          But a means necessary for the obtaining of faith and grace is the exterior vocation itself 
          through preachers,
          in which the predestination itself begins to be fulfilled 
          according to 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Nd1e451">Augustine</name>,
          and similarly the interior vocation by which God calls by inspiring.
          Whence 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e458">Saint Thomas in Quodlibet 2, article 6</ref> 
          says that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Qd1e462">
            a man is bound to believe according to how he is aided to believe.
            But someone is aided to believe in three ways:
            first indeed through interior vocation,
            second through exterior teaching and preaching,
            third through exterior miracles.
          </quote>
          These are his words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e476">
          Therefore if they are not aided by God through any of the aforesaid modes,
          as in the foreknown, 
          they do not sin by not believing or not receiving grace.
          This 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e485">Augustine intimates in the book On the Predestination of the Saints, chapters 9 and 10</ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e490">On the Gift of Perseverance, chapters 13 and 14</ref>,
          where among other profound and most beautiful things he says,
          speaking of the Tyrians and Sidonians, 
          thus: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Qd1e503">
            But the rest, 
            where if not in the mass of perdition are they left by just divine judgment?
            Where the Tyrians were left and the Sidonians,
            who even could have believed if they had seen those miracles of Christ.
            But because it was not given to them to believe,
            even that from which they might believe was denied,
            namely preaching.
          </quote>
          And below: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Qd1e521">
            Therefore the eyes of the Tyrians and Sidonians were not so blinded,
            <pb ed="#P" n="91-v"/>
            nor was the heart so hardened,
            since they would have believed if they had seen such signs as these saw,
            namely the Jews of whom he also speaks there,
            but it did not profit even them that they could believe,
            because they were not predestined.
          </quote>
          These words of Augustine.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e540">
          ¶ Therefore that common opinion of the doctors is understood,
          namely that concerning things necessary for salvation no one has invincible ignorance,
          because if he did what is in him, et cetera,
          concerning those who to eternal life through the mercy of God are preordained.
          For such persons, 
          if they did what is in them,
          most certainly it is to be held that God would provide the remedy;
          but as often as they do not do it, 
          they sin, 
          as the saints say.
          And therefore these things do not obstruct what has been determined above.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e570">
          <add rend="margin-left" hand="F">solution</add>
          ¶ Second, 
          we respond that whatever it may be concerning sin,
          namely if we suppose that they sin,
          nevertheless the punishment of that sin is reserved to divine judgment alone,
          and therefore human judgment is excluded from care of this kind.
          Both because,
          as appears from what has been said,
          it is uncertain,
          indeed it would be impossible to find or discern those whom invincible ignorance cannot excuse 
          from those who are rendered culpable by it.
          And therefore this distinction is not of human judgment but of divine,
          because God is the knower and judge of secrets. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e601" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d32-d1e300">
            32 distinctio, c. erubescant
          </ref>; 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e606" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c2q5-d1e376">
            and 2, q. 4, c. consuluisti
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e609">
          ¶ And he usurps divine judgment who judges uncertain 
          and doubtful things. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e615" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c2q1-d1e301">
            2, q. 1, nomen presbyteria
          </ref>;
          nor can that be condemned by human examination which God has reserved to His
          <pb ed="#P" n="92-r"/>
          judgment. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e626" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c15q6-d1e120">
            15, q. 6, c. si a sacerdotibus
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e629">
          ¶ Both because, 
          as is taught more fully below,
          sins which are committed only between God and the sinner himself are reserved to divine judgment alone,
          as is clear in many things,
          especially in sins of thoughts,
          even if they were known to the otherwise competent judge to be most grave.
          And therefore no judge has the power of judging concerning hidden things. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e648">
            The said c. erubescant, and 6, q. 1, c. si omnia
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e654">the said c. consuluisti</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e658">
          ¶ Likewise it is clear in this,
          that the sin of the Jews and Saracens,
          even those subject to Christian princes,
          is not punished by human judgment but is reserved to divine judgment.
          Whence the canonists say in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e671">c. quod super his. de voto</ref>,
          that to be a Jew,
          and by the same reason a pagan or Saracen,
          is in itself a delict with respect to God and to eternal punishment,
          but not with respect to the judge and contentious forum,
          and thus it is not punishable by men.
          The same says Bartholus and others in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e688">l. apud Iulianum, § 1</ref>,
          and there 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e693">Iasso § constat 5 columine</ref>.
          See 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-Rd1e698">the gloss in c. post miserabilem: de vsuris</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e704">
          Since therefore the sin of those worshiping idols,
          even supposing that they are not excused from the sin of idolatry,
          is done only between God and the sinners themselves,
          and since it is very difficult,
          indeed impossible,
          to discern whom invincible ignorance does not excuse,
          and through this they are committed by most hidden cogitation,
          it follows that human judgment is excluded from the care of punishing
          <pb ed="#P" n="92-v"/>
          such sins,
          unless it wishes rashly to usurp divine judgment.
          Therefore the truth of the conclusion is clear,
          that namely the negative unbelievers would be punished illicitly on account of this alone,
          that they worship idols,
          at least by human judgment.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e289-d1e747">
          <add place="margin-left" hand="F">
            Against Innocent who said the pope can punish a people because they worship idols
          </add>
          And thus at last it appears sufficiently that Innocent in this matter errs enormously,
          when he says it pertains to the pope to punish a gentile having only the natural law 
          if he worships idols.
          To his argument,
          namely because it is natural to worship one and only God the creator,
          we concede that it is natural,
          but after it shall have been known that there is a true and unique God.
          For then any rational creature will naturally understand that He is to be worshiped,
          and to Him every act of worship,
          reverence, 
          and sacrifice is to be exhibited, 
          et cetera.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>