<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 35 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 35 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-13">May 13, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-13" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="154-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Hd1e97">Chapter 35</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e99">
          Chapter 35
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/>
          Secondly, it is proved as a principal point that the Indians ought not immediately believe 
          it is wrong to sacrifice human beings to their gods:
          because it cannot be made evident to them in few words nor in many that it is prohibited 
          by natural reason to sacrifice human beings to the true God or to a putative god,
          if it is worshiped as the true one.
          Rather,
          by the same natural reason they themselves can demonstrate:
          not only that human beings ought to be offered to God in sacrifice,
          but also that even the angels themselves would be insufficient if they were able 
          to be sacrificed.
          We persuade this as follows,
          supposing first four principles.
          First,
          that there is no nation so barbarous that it does not have some,
          even if confused,
          knowledge of God.
          But all understand God to be one than whom nothing is or can be greater or better.
          Thus teaches Damascene 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e153">
            at the beginning of his book On the Orthodox Faith and chapter 3
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e158">
            By no means (he says) does God wholly desert us who are surrounded by ignorance of him;
            rather,
            the knowledge that God exists has been naturally implanted and innate in all from him himself
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e170">
          Likewise 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e172">
            Gregory of Nazianzus in his book On Theology,
            column 11
          </ref>.
          Likewise 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e179">
            Lactantius book 3,
            chapter 11 of the Divine Institutes
          </ref>.
          Again 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e184">
            Cicero in the book of Tusculan Questions
          </ref>
          says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e189" source="http://scta.info/resource/ctd99a-asdvss-d1e219@16-26">
            There is no one among human beings so savage whose mind has not been imbued 
            with the opinion of divinity
          </quote>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e197">
            in the book On the Laws
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e200">
            There is no nation so savage,
            so wild,
            which,
            even if it does not know what kind of God it ought to have,
            nevertheless does not know that it ought to have one
          </quote>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e209">
            Aristotle in the first and second books On the Heavens and the World
          </ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e214">
            in the third book of the Physics
          </ref>
          says that all people have agreed on this:
          that this glorious body,
          the first (namely) heaven,
          is the place of the supreme God,
          namely the Greeks and others of the first nations who knew God and things divine.
          Both points are taught by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e231">
            Boethius in book 3 of the Consolation of Philosophy,
            prose 10
          </ref>
          in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e236" source="http://scta.info/resource/hy7y6y-d1e67-d1e561@156-182">
            That the true God is the principle or beginning of all things and is good is proved 
            by the common conception of human minds.
            For since nothing better than God can be conceived,
            who would doubt that that than which nothing is better is good
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e250">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/>
          Secondly,
          it must be supposed that humans are led by natural instinct to worship God with their powers 
          and according to their manner,
          the reason for which is that they naturally estimate and believe their life and whatever 
          they have to flow from him.
          Thus writes 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e271">
            Saint Thomas in book 3,
            chapter 119 of the Summa Contra Gentiles
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e276" source="http://scta.info/resource/v8naTA-d1e2680-d1e294@1-27" type="paraphrase">
            since they believe all things to be given by and proceed from him,
            our intellect judges that all things are owed to God
          </quote>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e283">
            the Philosopher in book 7 of the Politics,
            chapter 9
          </ref>
          writes:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e289">
            to God,
            on account of his excellence,
            all the highest and best things ought to be offered,
            which natural reason itself also dictates
          </quote>.
          And again 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e298">
            in book 8 of the Ethics,
            chapter 10
          </ref>
          he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e303">
            but there is for humans a friendship toward the gods as toward a super-excellent good,
            and to friends according to excellence more ought to be given
          </quote>.
          And again he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e314">
            To the gods no one can ever give back worthily,
            but whoever does this according to his ability seems to be good
          </quote>.
          The same is taught by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e325">
            Saint Thomas in book 4 of the Sentences,
            distinction 19,
            question 1,
            article 2 in the body
          </ref>
          where he says that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e330" source="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d15q1-d1e335@8-88" type="paraphrase">
            man owes God in two ways:
            first on account of benefits received from him,
            second on account of sins committed against him.
            By these two obligations man can never make equal satisfaction to God,
            because (he says) in those honors which are owed to parents and to the gods,
            even according to the Philosopher,
            it is impossible to render an equivalent according to quantity,
            but it suffices that man render what he can according to proportionality
          </quote>
          etc.
          These are the words of Saint Thomas.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e356">
          From these things it is clear that humans are bound by natural law to honor God 
          through the most excellent and best things and to offer sacrifice from better things.
          Hence it follows that neither a particular person nor an entire community together,
          or a whole kingdom,
          is able to make recompense to God for benefits received,
          even if it renders to him wealth,
          labors,
          vigilance,
          and finally life and death itself for the glory of God and endures these,
          however much God may not wish to reward such things in the other life,
          because God owes nothing,
          who has heaped upon us so many and such admirable benefits with ineffable generosity,
          on account of which that verse 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e390">
            of Psalm 114
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e392" source="http://scta.info/resource/ps115_3@1-7">
            What shall I render to the Lord for all that he has rendered to me
          </quote>?
          As if to say:
          there is nothing in me or that I can do by which I can render back to God 
          for those things by which I perceive myself to be his debtor.
          But the reason is that,
          just as a man does not commit injustice against his own possession even if he uses it 
          and renders it no payment,
          because there is no just political or civil right of a man toward his own possession 
          according to the Philosopher in book 5 of the Ethics,
          but all creatures are possessions of God,
          therefore in no way is it possible for God to do us injustice if he does not repay 
          the services which we have rendered for his honor,
          because between God and us there cannot be given a political justice which is 
          justice simply speaking.
          For although God gives eternal happiness to those having charity,
          he is not bound to do this from justice insofar as it is justice simply speaking,
          which signifies quantitative equality from one part to another.
          For according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e445">
            the Apostle to the Romans,
            chapter 8
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e450" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom8_18@4-16">
            The sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory 
            to come which shall be revealed in us
          </quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e458">
          Yet it is said that between man and God there is a certain condescending justice (namely),
          that the Lord,
          using the magnitude of his mercy,
          deigns that there be a certain proportional equality between himself and humans,
          willing (namely) to obligate himself to humans and humans to himself,
          so that for those persisting unto death in faith and charity,
          he is bound to give eternal life,
          not from our equal merits but from a disposition established by himself,
          which he willed to be between himself and us a certain condescending justice and 
          a kind of pact,
          so that in works of charity God is bound to give us eternal life.
          And this is called justice not simply but in a qualified sense.
          And according to this sense God would be said to do injustice if he did not provide 
          eternal life to those dying in charity,
          and thus is understood the Apostle in 2 Timothy,
          chapter 4:
          henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of justice,
          that is,
          by the justice of an agreement or supposed pact already mentioned.
          Therefore God owes us nothing except from condescending justice;
          we owe him all things whatsoever we have and are:
          wealth,
          strength,
          life,
          and the soul itself we ought to offer in his service,
          to which by a greater bond we are bound after he gave his soul for us.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e528">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/>
          Thirdly,
          it must be supposed that God is worshiped by nothing more than by sacrifice,
          which is the principal act of latria owed to God alone,
          nor do humans show themselves more grateful and subject to God by external acts.
          For sacrifice is a sign that he to whom it is offered is God,
          and it is most certain that there has been no nation so barbarous,
          brutish,
          and stupid that it would offer sacrifice to anyone other than him whom it thought 
          to be God,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e554">
            Saint Augustine in book 10,
            chapter 4 of the City of God
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e559" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l10-d1e1382@62-98">
            For who ever thought sacrifice should be made except to him whom he knew or thought 
            or feigned to be God?
            Moreover,
            how ancient is the worship of God in sacrificing,
            those two brothers Cain and Abel sufficiently indicate,
            whose sacrifice God rejected in the elder but looked upon in the younger
          </quote>.
          These are the words of Augustine.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e586">
          The same is taught by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e590">
            Saint Thomas in book 3,
            chapter 120 of the Summa Contra Gentiles
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e595" source="http://scta.info/resource/v8naTA-d1e2688-d1e365@29-43">
            But no one ever thought sacrifice should be offered to anyone unless because he estimated 
            him to be God,
            or pretended to estimate him so
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e605">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/>
          Fourth,
          it must be supposed that to offer sacrifice to the true God or to him who is estimated 
          to be God is from natural law.
          But what things ought to be offered to God is human law and positive constitution.
          Hence either this is left to the whole community or to one acting in its stead,
          such as a prince,
          or if this is lacking,
          it is committed to any particular person from which or from what things he may construct 
          his sacrifice.
          The first is evident from the three preceding principles,
          because since all nations know by nature itself that God exceeds all things which 
          they can conceive,
          and that from him they have life and whatever they possess,
          and since they understand by nature that they owe to God the highest reverence and worship 
          on account of his incomparable excellence and majesty,
          and it is received among all that the principal act of latria owed to God alone is sacrifice,
          it follows that they are bound by natural law to offer sacrifice by which humans above 
          all other external things show themselves more grateful and subject to God.
          Hence there has been no nation so barbarous which,
          impelled by nature,
          did not judge that sacrifice was owed to the true God or to him whom erring 
          they considered to be true.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e671">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/>
          Secondly,
          it is proved from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e677">
            Saint Thomas in the Secunda Secundae,
            question 85,
            article 1
          </ref>,
          where he says that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e681" source="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1711-d1e242@5-17">
            in every age and among any nations of humans there has always been some offering of sacrifices
          </quote>,
          and the reason is because 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e691" source="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1711-d1e255@4-37">
            natural reason dictates to man that he is subject to some superior on account of the defects 
            which he feels in himself,
            in which he needs to be helped and directed by some superior,
            and whatever that may be,
            this is what is called God among all
          </quote>.
          And therefore the offering of sacrifices pertains to natural law according to Saint Thomas.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e710">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/>
          Thirdly,
          it is proved from the jurists who teach that religion is from the law of nations in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e718" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e59-d1e131">
            the law Veluti,
            Digest,
            On Justice and Law
          </ref>.
          But they call natural law the law of nations because only humans use it,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e728" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e59-d1e123">
            law 1,
            Digest,
            same title
          </ref>,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e732">
            paragraph Singulorum,
            Institutes,
            On the Division of Things
          </ref>.
          But humans,
          as soon as they multiplied,
          immediately exercised the law of nations.
          For the nations which lived in the first ages taught very many things by the instinct 
          of nature.
          Therefore from that beginning the custom of sacrificing was initiated,
          produced by the instinct of nature.
          Therefore to offer sacrifices is a most ancient thing introduced by natural law.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e750">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/>
          But the second point (namely),
          that to offer this or that in sacrifice is from human law,
          but the law of nature does not prescribe a certain thing,
          is also proved first because even if something is generally from natural law,
          nevertheless the disposition and ordering when and how that ought to be done is positive,
          which is nothing other than a certain determination of natural law which either 
          the prince or the republic establishes.
          For example:
          humans are bound to devote themselves sometimes to divine things and to worship God 
          by certain external acts which theologians call acts of latria,
          which natural reason dictates,
          but that the seventh day ought to be given to divine worship is a human constitution 
          promulgated by the Church,
          to whom Christ gave the right of making laws concerning divine worship.
          Although I know that the seventh day (namely) Sunday succeeded in place of the Sabbath,
          which God commanded in the positive law to be given to divine things.
          So also the law of nature teaches that offenders ought to be punished,
          but what the punishment ought to be is taught by human law.
          In the same way,
          although nature itself teaches and leads man to sacrifice to God,
          nevertheless what thing ought to be offered in sacrifice,
          whether oxen,
          or sheep,
          or similar things,
          the law of nature does not teach,
          but humans have established this,
          as is evident from the sacrifices of diverse nations related above.
          Likewise,
          because others sacrificed pigs to Ceres,
          horses to Phoebus,
          geese to Diana,
          asses to Priapus,
          and again others offered other things,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e830">
            Ovid relates in Fasti,
            book 1
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e835">
            Lucan in On the Civil War,
            book 6
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e840">
            Juvenal in the penultimate satire
          </ref>.
          I have taken the above-written reason from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e844" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1711-d1e303@10-58">
            Saint Thomas in the Secunda Secundae,
            question 85,
            article 1,
            reply to objection 1
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e849" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d26q2-d1e201@5-45">
            book 4 of the Sentences,
            distinction 26,
            question 2,
            article 2,
            reply to objection 1
          </ref>
          and Quodlibet 2,
          article 8 in the body.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e858">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/>
          Secondly,
          this is proved from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e864">
            the Philosopher in book 5 of the Ethics
          </ref>,
          where speaking of natural law and of positive law he writes that all humans feel 
          the same way about those things which are natural but differ in laws and institutions.
          For speaking about sacrifices he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Qd1e876">
            One law is natural,
            another is legitimate,
            that is legal or positive.
            Natural indeed is that which has the same force everywhere,
            as fire burns both here and in Persia,
            not because it seems so or does not seem so.
            But legitimate,
            that is legal,
            is that which makes no difference in principle whether done this way or that,
            but when it is established it makes a difference,
            for instance,
            that the redemption of captives be made at a certain price,
            or to sacrifice a goat but not two sheep,
            and those things which are stipulated by laws concerning individual things,
            such as to perform sacred rites for Brasidas
          </quote>
          etc.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e909">
          Behold,
          he teaches that the law of nature does not change because one person wills and another 
          does not will to fulfill it.
          For neither can what is good be made impious by the will of humans,
          such as redeeming a captive suffering injustice,
          which the law of nature teaches,
          and likewise to offer sacrifice to God;
          all humans are bound to do this,
          whether they will it or not.
          But how much the price of captives ought to be and what thing ought to be sacrificed,
          human constitution teaches,
          which,
          after it has been established,
          it is proper to observe and not permitted to transgress.
          Let the example be what we read:
          that the Athenians and Spartans,
          waging war among themselves,
          established by common consent that captives of either side should redeem their freedom 
          for a certain fixed price.
          Likewise,
          if it were established that not one but two sheep should be offered in sacrifice,
          or that sacrifices should be made and festivals celebrated for someone who has merited 
          well of the republic,
          just as the Amphipolitans established that sacrifices should be offered by Brasidas,
          whom some think was a king of the Spartans,
          others a queen woman,
          on account of benefits conferred upon their nation—these sacrifices and the form sanctioned 
          by law it is not at all permitted to transgress.
          But if the law had sanctioned nothing,
          each private person could sacrifice what he wished and sell a captive for whatever price 
          he wished,
          for the natural law does not teach these things.
          And each person in those things which are indifferent can use his own judgment and can prescribe 
          to his own (namely) children and wife what he wishes,
          according to the Philosopher in book 1 of the Politics,
          where speaking of households and the city he says:
          but every house is ruled by the eldest,
          and thus also families propagated from it on account of blood relationship.
          And this is what Homer says:
          let individuals give laws to their children and wives.
          For they also dwelt separately in this manner in ancient times.
          These are his words.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e1003" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1566-d1e599@5-80">
            Saint Thomas speaks of these things in the Secunda Secundae,
            question 57,
            article 2,
            reply to objection 2
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e1008" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1582-d1e1226@6-67">
            question 60,
            article 5,
            reply to objection 1
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e1017" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1582-d1e1255@4-54">
            2
          </ref>,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-Rd1e1020" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1613-d1e1444@4-16">
            question 66,
            article 7 in the body
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e500-d1e1024">
          But that,
          unless a certain manner or thing to be sacrificed had been prescribed by law,
          it would be permitted to each one to sacrifice what he wished,
          is proved in Genesis,
          chapter 4,
          where Cain offered ears of grain and fruits of the earth,
          but Abel,
          who was a shepherd,
          sacrificed the firstborn of his flock to the Lord.
          But after the Lord made a pact with Abraham and his posterity,
          he prescribed through Moses the sacrifices to be offered to him,
          namely from quadrupeds:
          oxen and sheep,
          and from birds:
          turtledoves and doves,
          as is evident in Genesis 8:14,
          chapter 19,
          and Leviticus,
          chapter 1.
          Abulensis treats these matters learnedly in question 11 and 12 on Leviticus,
          and question 9,
          column 7,
          chapter 25 on Exodus,
          and something in Genesis,
          chapter 15.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>