<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Argumentum [English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Argumentum [English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-02-06">February 6, 2026</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-02-06" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>English translation created.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="1-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05-Hd1e97">Argumentum</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#P" n="1-r"/>
          Argumentum of the Apology of the Most Reverend Lord Brother Bartholomew de Las Casas,
          former Bishop of Chiapas,
          against Genesius Sepulveda,
          theologian of Cordoba
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05-d1e121">
          In the year from the Virgin's birth one thousand five hundred and forty-two,
          Charles Caesar,
          King of Spain,
          worthy of eternal human memory,
          having been informed that the Spanish were raging far and wide with violence and tyranny,
          oppressing with servitude and afflicting with the greatest burdens the Indians,
          inhabitants of the ocean sea,
          who by decree of the Roman Pontiff pertain to the supreme empire of Castile and Leon,
          convened a solemn council at Pintia or Valladolid,
          summoning certain men selected from the entire senate,
          most distinguished and most learned;
          he ordered them to determine whether those atrocious things which had been reported to him were true,
          and to devise an appropriate remedy by which such great evils might be opposed,
          so that the Indians might be restored to their former liberty,
          and at the same time that new world might be organized with salutary laws and prudent institutions,
          to be governed in the future.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05-d1e183">
          Concerning this matter there was debate for many days with great disputations,
          and finally certain laws were enacted
          <pb ed="#P" n="1-v"/>
          by which the military expeditions of the Spanish against the Indians,
          which they commonly called conquests,
          were prohibited;
          and at the same time it was provided that all the Indians oppressed by servitude,
          who by division,
          that is repartimiento or encomienda (indeed a satanic invention never heard of before),
          had been wrongly assigned to those to whom they had been adjudicated,
          should be restored to liberty,
          and all the Indians should be reduced to the universal dominion of the kings of Spain,
          with their natural kings and lords remaining in their power and jurisdiction.
          This matter greatly stung the spirits of the Spanish,
          for whom the Indians were rich plunder and whose fortunes grew by violence,
          rapine,
          and the despoiling of the Indians;
          and being indignant and raging with angry spirit,
          they lamented that they were being despoiled of their own property by the Caesar,
          as if he were not removing sacrilegious plunder from robbers,
          but dethroning legitimate owners of things from just possession of property.
          So that some,
          leaving no stone unturned to protect their interests,
          shamelessly defected from the Caesar and rebelled against the Caesar.
          Others fled to men renowned for their opinion of learning,
          so that they might attack the imperial constitutions with solid legal arguments,
          so that finally the Caesar,
          moved by the iniquity of the laws,
          might either abolish them or at least suspend their observance,
          as was done with some of them—not because they were not most equitable and most just,
          but because,
          knowing the rebellion of those traitors,
          some greater evil
          <pb ed="#P" n="2-r"/>
          or more atrocious sedition was feared.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05-d1e279">
          They found a learned defender of their opinion,
          who here indeed shows himself little erudite.
          This was a certain Genesius Sepulveda,
          royal historiographer,
          who composed a little work adorned with flowers of eloquence,
          to which he gave the title "On the Just Causes of War,"
          in which with all his might he attacks these new laws,
          making no express mention of them at all,
          but defending the past and future wars and expeditions of the Spanish against the Indians,
          and approving the servitude,
          that is,
          the division or encomienda by which the Indians,
          oppressed by the Spanish,
          either die or live a life harder than death,
          divided into parts as if they were herds or cattle—namely,
          divided among the Spanish and assigned to each up to a certain number,
          so that they might serve them.
          For these first conquests or invasions,
          second,
          divisions and assignments,
          which are made region by region from a certain number of Indians throughout that whole world,
          the Spanish have always seen to it that they be done from that day when that new world was first opened to us.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05-d1e332">
          Sepulveda brings forward certain fabricated arguments by which he favors the most avaricious greed of tyrants,
          distorting the authorities of the sacred volumes,
          the decrees of most holy fathers,
          and the wise and philosophers,
          recounting the crimes
          <pb ed="#P" n="2-v"/>
          and natural vices of the Indians,
          instructed (of course) by those Spanish,
          most hostile enemies of the Indians,
          and relying on those false denunciations;
          he falsely traduces the greater part of the human race,
          which divine providence has dispersed into those vast expanses of the Indies.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05-d1e364">
          The Bishop of Chiapas,
          when he learned that that little work had been written by Genesius and a summary of his work,
          written in Spanish,
          had come into his hands (for at that time he could not have a copy of the Latin codex),
          understanding what was the opinion of Genesius,
          composed the following apology against those invaders and oppressors of the Indians,
          who were living peacefully without injury to another nation,
          and who hold the Indians oppressed and drive them to death,
          wishing to protect and defend them from all injury.
          Moreover,
          he dedicated the Apology to our Most Serene Prince Philip,
          at that time placed in charge of the government of this realm with imperial authority by the most invincible Caesar Charles,
          his father.
          The apology contained a response to the four causes by which Sepulveda defended those expeditions and assignments of the Spanish,
          under whose title they oppressed the Indians with servitude.
          When,
          however,
          the Bishop had refuted Sepulveda at Complutum,
          and that whole celebrated academy had condemned Sepulveda's
          <pb ed="#P" n="3-r"/>
          opinion as not very sound,
          forbidding for this very express reason that the work be printed,
          this disputation of the Bishop and Sepulveda reached the ears of the Caesar,
          then acting in Germany,
          who in the year of human salvation one thousand five hundred and fifty-one ordered that distinguished theologians and jurists should meet together along with the senators of the Indian tribunal,
          and that they should hear both the Bishop and Sepulveda and determine what would be most advantageous for the republic.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e05-d1e445">
          First,
          the opportunity of speaking was given to Sepulveda for one day.
          But they listened to the Bishop speaking for five days,
          who recited this entire Apology in order,
          and finally,
          after many disputations held on both sides,
          they judged that the expeditions which we commonly call conquests are iniquitous,
          illicit,
          and unjust,
          and therefore to be altogether prohibited in the future.
          Concerning the assignments,
          however,
          which we commonly call repartimientos,
          they decreed nothing,
          for the rebellion of certain tyrants in the Peruvian kingdoms endured,
          and other provinces were in turmoil.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>