<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 3 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 3 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-27">July 27, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-27" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="19-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Hd1e97">Chapter 3 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-d1e99">
          Chapter 3
        </p>
        <p>
          ¶ It is no objection that we see men for the most part to be of corrupt morals and that according to 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e109">Solomon's</name> 
          sentence, 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e112">
            The number of fools is infinite
          </quote> 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e117">Ecclesiastes 2</ref>.
          For this comes about because men, 
          educated from a young age among bodily and sensible goods from which corruption of morals proceeds, 
          and always handling these things, 
          know them more fully. 
          But spiritual things and goods of reason and intellectual things, 
          they do not know so fully, 
          since these are removed from the senses. 
          And since they understand bodily things and always handle them, 
          but spiritual things not so easily, 
          it happens that they are immersed for the most part in depraved morals. 
          This, however, has no place in angels, 
          since they are all totally intellectual, 
          to whom sensible goods can bring no impediment or disturbance. 
          Since, therefore, 
          rational nature after the angelic is nobler and more perfect than all created things, 
          and thus is the most powerful and noblest part of the whole universe, 
          the more it approaches divine likeness, 
          if monstrosity were found in men for the most part, 
          such as having eyes in the forehead or being mute and deaf, 
          it would follow that the perfection of the universe which God especially intended in creation (as was said) 
          would be deficient in its nobler part, 
          suffering natural evil or sin or monstrosity in most cases, 
          which does not happen in other things. 
          Whence the plan of God willing the universe to be as beautiful and perfect as possible would be greatly frustrated. 
          But this is a great inconvenience and very false. 
          Therefore, dullness of intellect and of the higher powers, 
          and also of the interior sensitive powers which serve the higher powers for understanding well, 
          is impossible to be found in men for the most part; 
          <pb ed="#P" n="20-r"/>
          but rather it is necessary that for the most part men are found to be clever, 
          sagacious, 
          industrious, 
          and endowed with talent; 
          so that an entire region or province should be stupid and foolish or suffering similar natural defects or monstrosities is impossible. 
          We have discussed this matter at greater length in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e245">
            book 1, chapter 5 of our work, 
            <title>On the Only Way of Calling All Peoples to the True Religion</title>
          </ref>.
          where we made this conclusion plain with reasons and authorities, 
          namely that it would be impossible for an entire people, 
          nation, 
          or region or province to be found in all parts of the world that is foolish or stupid, 
          so that it does not have for the most part sufficient natural knowledge and industry to rule and govern itself. 
          To these barbarians, 
          barbarians simply, 
          strictly, 
          and properly speaking, 
          must be applied what 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e285">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e286">the Philosopher</name> 
            says in Politics 1
          </ref>,
          namely that they ought to be governed by the Greeks, 
          that is, by the wiser, 
          because nature, 
          on account of dullness of intellect and savagery, 
          makes them slaves. 
          And since they are far removed from the excellence of human nature, 
          it is necessary that they be governed by others, 
          that they may be taught to live politically and humanely, 
          and that they in turn, 
          who are generally robust, 
          may render service to their master, 
          and thus the same benefits both master and slave. 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e306">The Philosopher</name> 
          adds that it is lawful to hunt or chase such barbarians like wild beasts, 
          so that they may be brought to a right manner of life. 
          Here two things are to be noted: 
          <pb ed="#P" n="20-v"/>
          first, that to compel barbarians to live politically and humanely is not permitted to just anyone, 
          but only to princes and governors of the republic. 
          Then it must be observed that barbarians are not to be compelled as 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e326">the Philosopher</name> 
          strictly says, 
          but are to be gently led and allured by charity to undertake the best morals. 
          For we are commanded by divine institution to love our neighbor as ourselves, 
          and since we wish our own vices to be gently cured and uprooted, 
          we ought to render the same to our brothers, 
          even if they are barbarians; 
          which we are taught by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e343">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e344">Paul</name> 
            in Romans 15
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e347">
            We who are strong ought to bear the weaknesses of the weak and not please ourselves; 
            let each of us please his neighbor for good, 
            to edification
          </quote>.
          And below: 
          Therefore receive one another as Christ also received you to the honor of God. 
          Again, if we wish to be children of Christ and followers of Evangelical truth, 
          we ought to consider that even if they are exceedingly barbarous, 
          nevertheless they are created in the image of God, 
          nor are they so entirely destitute of divine providence that they are not capable of the kingdom of Christ: 
          brothers and redeemed by the most precious blood of Christ, 
          no less than the most prudent and wisest of the whole world. 
          Finally, it must be considered that some among them are predestined, 
          perhaps to become noble and illustrious in the kingdom of Christ. 
          For which reason, to any men, 
          however savage and extremely barbarous and stupid, 
          we are bound to render fraternal duty and Christian charity, 
          by the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e396">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e397">Paul</name> 
            in Romans 1
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e402">
            To Greeks and barbarians, to the wise and foolish, I am a debtor; 
            so that as far as is in me, I am ready to preach the gospel to you also
          </quote>.
          <pb ed="#P" n="21-r"/>
          Christ wished charity to be called His unique precept; 
          we owe this to all, 
          no one is excepted. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e416">
            There is neither male nor female, Gentile nor Jew, circumcision nor uncircumcision, Barbarian nor Scythian, 
            slave nor free; 
            but Christ is all and in all
          </quote>.
          Therefore, although 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e425">the Philosopher</name>, 
          ignorant of Christian truth and charity, 
          writes that the wise can hunt barbarians no less than wild beasts, 
          let no one understand that barbarians are either to be killed or oppressed with unjust works, 
          cruel, harsh, and severe, 
          like beasts of burden, 
          and can be sought and seized for this use by the wiser. 
          Farewell, Aristotle. 
          For from Christ, who is eternal truth, 
          we have: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e445">
            You shall love your neighbor as yourself
          </quote> 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e450">Matthew 22</ref>.
          And again 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e452">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e453">Paul</name> 
            in Corinthians 13
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e459">
            Charity (he says) does not seek its own
          </quote>,
          but those things which are of Jesus Christ. 
          Christ does not seek possessions but souls; 
          He who alone is king of kings immortal does not covet riches; 
          not leisure and pleasures but the salvation of the human race for which He offered His life, 
          fixed upon the tree of the cross. 
          Whoever wishes many to exist so that (following 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e477">Aristotle's</name> 
          teachings) he may act the savage butcher toward them, 
          that he may oppress them with servitude and grow rich from them, 
          is a tyrant, not a Christian; 
          a son of Satan, not of God; 
          he is a robber, not a shepherd; 
          he is led by a diabolical spirit, not a heavenly one. 
          If you seek the Indians so that you may gently, 
          modestly, 
          mildly, 
          humanely, 
          and finally in a Christian manner instruct them, 
          lead them by the word of God and by works
          <pb ed="#P" n="21-v"/>
          to the fold of Christ, 
          impressing upon their minds that most gentle Christ, 
          you perform an apostolic work and will have from our Supreme Lamb 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e506">
            an unfading crown of glory
          </quote>.
          But if you consume and plunder the most innocent peoples with iron, 
          flames, 
          slaughter, 
          impostures, 
          violence, 
          tyranny, 
          cruelty, 
          and more than barbarous inhumanity, 
          peoples prepared to abstain from evil and to receive the word of God, 
          you are sons of the devil and the most inhuman of all robbers. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e536">
            My yoke (says Christ) is sweet and my burden light
          </quote>.
          You impose unbearable burdens, 
          and you who ought to be light in life to the blind and ignorant, 
          consume the creatures of God. 
          Hear 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e550">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e551">Dionysius</name> 
            in the 
            <title>Letter to Demophilus the Monk</title>
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e555">
            For it is fitting that the ignorant be taught, not tortured; 
            just as we do not torment the blind but lead them by the hand
          </quote>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e564">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e565">a little</name> 
            below
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e568">
            It is therefore of great horror that he whom Christ the supremely good seeks wandering in the mountains, 
            calls back fleeing, 
            and scarcely found, bears back upon sacred shoulders, 
            is afflicted by you, 
            repudiated, 
            cast out
          </quote>.
          Thus far he. 
          In this way the apostles spread the Gospel and subjected the whole world to Christ, 
          as is evident from the Acts of the Apostles. 
          And concerning blessed 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e597">Jude Thaddeus</name>, 
          these words are read in the 
          <title>Roman Lectionary</title>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Qd1e609">
            The blessed apostle, sent by divine impulse to the city of Edessa as evangelist and preacher of the word of God, 
            coming to Mesopotamia and to the lower parts of Pontus and evangelizing, 
            <pb ed="#P" n="22-r"/>
            was softening savage and untamed peoples, 
            almost beast-like natures, 
            with holy doctrine, 
            and subjugating them to the faith of the Lord
          </quote>.
          Different was this hunting from that which Aristotle taught, 
          who, although endowed with great philosophy, 
          was nevertheless not worthy to be captured by it, 
          so as to come to God through knowledge of the true faith.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-d1e634">
          ¶ These three kinds of barbarians about which we have discussed are gathered from Saint 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e640">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Nd1e641">Thomas</name> 
            on books 1 and 3 of the 
            <title>Politics</title>
          </ref> 
          and from the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e645">
            first reading on Paul's Epistle to the Romans
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e650">
            1 Corinthians 14, reading 2
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e78-Rd1e655">
            Colossians 3, reading 2
          </ref>.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>