<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 56 [English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 56 [English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2026-01-06">January 06, 2026</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2026-01-06" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="234-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Hd1e107">Chapter 56 [English Translation]</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e109">
          Chapter 56
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e114">
          ¶ Third,
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e118">John Major</name> 
          teaches that a people who have received the faith of Christ ought,
          if they have received it sincerely,
          to want their prince,
          who perseveres in paganism,
          to be deposed.
          Indeed a people by nature or quasi-nature loves its ancient prince according to the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e133" target="http://scta.info/resource/ArNeTH-d1e250-d1e674@1-29">
            Philosopher in Ethics book 8, chapter 7
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e135">Politics book 3 chapter 10</ref>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e140" target="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l19-d1e3137@40-81">
            Augustine in the City of God book 19, chapter 16
          </ref>.
          Therefore a people would no less difficulty admit this than a new religion.
          Especially if for the deposed old lord an outsider is substituted,
          which tends to be unwelcome and hateful to the people.
          Therefore God almighty in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e154" target="http://scta.info/resource/deut17_14 http://scta.info/resource/deut17_15">
            Deuteronomy 17
          </ref>
          commanded the Jews that if they were to elect a king,
          they should elect one from among themselves.
          The reason for which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e166" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1214-d1e486@1-47">
            Saint Thomas assigns in 1a 2ae, question 105 article 1 ad 2
          </ref>.
          Therefore one should not suspect sinisterly of a newly converted people because they do not want their old prince deposed,
          even if he is pagan.
          For they can hope that he may sometime receive the faith.
          Moreover a recently converted people is not to be wondered at if they do not have so much evangelical vigor that,
          immediately having cast off all affections,
          they would hold hateful their old prince known through many years of custom.
          Therefore something must be permitted and given to their affections,
          even if they are not purely Christian,
          on the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e201">Gregory book 12 epistle 31</ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e207">To the Questions of Augustine chapter 7</ref>,
          fragments of which are read in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e214">35 question 2 and 3, chapter 'quaedam lex'</ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Qd1e219">
            Lest (he says) the good which has been planted with still weak root be uprooted,
            but let what has been begun be strengthened and guarded unto perfection.
          </quote>
          Thus he.
          Consequently 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e230">John Major</name> 
          exceeded in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e233">
            saying fourth that,
            in that case,
            such a King ought to be deposed.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e239">
          ¶ Next 
          <name>John Major</name> 
          adds that if the Indian nations of that island 
          (where it appears how poorly informed about Indian affairs 
          <name>John Major</name> 
          was speaking) 
          were not governed by kings,
          but jurisdiction and authority are with the republic,
          the republic ought to be despoiled of authority for the planting of the faith.
          Here John seems ridiculous to me.
          For he was proceeding very hastily through this matter.
          For if he leaves a kingdom to a king if he repairs expenses,
          why would he not also want it left to a republic under the same condition?
          For a king has whatever right he has from the consent of the people,
          whence if a king dies without offspring,
          the right of electing a king pertains to the people.
          Why therefore did he wish to despoil the republic of election more than the king,
          when the jurisdiction and power of the republic is more natural than the authority of a king,
          which takes its origin from the consent of the republic?
          For it is clear that a greater injustice is committed in despoiling a community or people of the right of electing without legitimate cause than in despoiling the prince himself of a kingdom,
          since it is contrary to greater justice.
          Hence 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e301">Peter of Palude</name> 
          writes in the treatise 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e306">On the Power of the Pope article 4</ref>,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e308">
            concerning the immediate cause of papal power in the first question
          </ref>,
          in the solution of a certain argument,
          that if the pope deposes a king from just cause,
          he cannot substitute another in his place,
          nor can he take away from the people the right belonging to them by natural law to elect a king.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e330">
          ¶ 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e332">John Major</name> 
          proceeds to speak untruthfully about the Indians in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Qd1e340" source="http://scta.info/resource/jb2v19-d111866-d1e326@307-334">
            Also there is another thing;
            that people lives bestially on both sides of the equator and beneath the poles live wild men as 
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e346">Ptolemy</name> 
            says in the Quadripartite.
            And now this has been confirmed by experience
          </quote>,
          et cetera.
          He also adduces that from the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e355">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e356">Philosopher</name> 
            in the first book of the <title>Politics</title>
          </ref>:
          that Greeks ought to rule over barbarians.
          From this (unless I am mistaken) 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e365">Sepúlveda</name> 
          gathers his poisons,
          but I am amazed that 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e367">John Major</name> 
          so easily gave credence to those who slander the Indians,
          a docile,
          sincere and ingenious people,
          with the most shameless lies as if they were stupid and wild,
          so that the most savage plunderers might act against them more freely.
          It did not befit a Theologian to rush to judgment in a matter of such importance,
          especially since the bull of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e387">Alexander VI</name>,
          from the report of the kings of Castile,
          narrates that 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e395">Christopher Columbus</name> 
          discovered certain gentle peoples living peacefully without any injury,
          not entirely ignorant of the divine power.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e405">
          Who ever,
          being a serious man,
          took up the pen without exact knowledge of fact and law?
          But here he demonstrates himself most ignorant of the law,
          and when he directs his speech to the fact,
          he errs completely.
          What he cites from 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e418">Ptolemy</name> 
          in the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e421">Quadripartite</ref> 
          is false,
          for 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e424">Ptolemy</name> 
          wrote no such thing.
          He describes the world known in his age in the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e428">
            second treatise of the Tripartite, chapter 3
          </ref>.
          But concerning this to which 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e436">John Major</name> 
          cites him,
          he made no word.
          For he did not describe the provinces of the Equator which he himself thought uncultivated and uninhabitable.
          Those whom 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e449">Ptolemy</name> 
          calls wild inhabit Mauretania in Africa at the promontory which we now commonly call Cabo de Aguer,
          where Arabs commonly called Alarabes dwell.
          And since 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e460">Ptolemy</name> 
          never knew our Indians,
          how could he have mentioned them?
          What he writes,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Qd1e466">
            that wild and forest men live on both sides of the equinoctial,
            is false,
            unless they recede very far from the equator so that by the harshness of cold and intemperance of the region men would quasi lack reason.
          </quote>
          Thus writes the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e481">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e482">Philosopher</name> 
            in the 7th book of the <title>Politics</title>
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e487">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e488">Vegetius</name> 
            on military matters, book 1, chapter 2
          </ref>.
          For the closer a region is to the zones and the arctic and antarctic circle,
          and the nearer it is to the poles,
          the colder it is,
          because of the distance of the sun.
          Whence the inhabitants are less able by reason.
          But since such men are judged monsters of nature,
          they will necessarily be very rare,
          as we proved above.
          Therefore those zones rigid with excessive cold are considered uninhabitable,
          not because they are inhabited by no one,
          but because the inhabitants are rare.
          Moreover the Indians of the new world inhabit provinces nearest to the equinoctial line,
          for all their provinces are distant twenty or twenty-five or thirty degrees from the arctic and a little more from the antarctic North and South.
          But the equinoctial line,
          since it provides days equal to nights,
          is most temperate.
          Whence it is inferred that the Indians inhabit the most fortunate regions of the whole world,
          which we know not only theoretically but practically and have experienced.
          And consequently that they are ingenious and greatly able by reason according to the opinion of Aristotle,
          Vegetius and Ptolemy.
          Of which matter we ourselves are witnesses,
          who for very many years have traversed those regions and most thoroughly examined those peoples,
          and have known their customs and characters,
          and know them to be far different from what 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e557">John Major</name> 
          most vainly writes,
          being ignorant of the people and the happy nature of the equinoctial line,
          which if he had known alone,
          it would have been enough to reject the calumnies and lies of those who,
          penetrating into those provinces,
          most savagely devastated a most gentle,
          sincere and modest people,
          which can scarcely be related without tears,
          et cetera.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e577">
          ¶ From these things it is elicited that by no means does what 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e581">John Major</name> 
          brings forth from the Philosopher fit here,
          that a Greek ought to rule over a barbarian.
          For the Indians are by no means barbarians,
          as he thought,
          as we taught above in chapter 2.
          Perhaps a certain disciple of his named Charles followed this absurd error of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e593">John Major</name>.
          He was sent as vicar of the Bishopric of Concepción which is on the island of Hispaniola in the year 1513,
          and he pronounced a sentence by which he dissolved the marriage between an Indian woman and a Spanish man,
          namely for that reason that he judged her stupid and devoid of reason because she was an Indian.
          He,
          a little later,
          having returned to Spain by the just judgment of God,
          was permitted to fall into many errors,
          concerning which he was accused before the office of the holy inquisition by friars of the Order of Preachers.
          Finally condemned at 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e628">Burgos</name>,
          he publicly abjured those errors with great ignominy and confusion,
          and deprived of the duty of preaching and thrust perpetually into either prison or a monastery assigned as a prison.
          He finally never appeared again.
          See what these absurd,
          not to say impious,
          trifles of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e646">John Major</name> 
          have accomplished.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e651">
          ¶ Moreover 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e653">Sepúlveda</name>,
          in confirmation of his impious opinion,
          cites the most learned father 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e660">Francisco de Vitoria</name>,
          that he approved 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Rd1e665">war on the Indians</ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e670">
          ¶ Sepúlveda adds,
          lest he be despoiled of his glory,
          that that most learned father by no means brought forth the principal arguments which he himself adduces.
          But whoever reads the two parts of that most learned man's First Relectio will easily perceive that that man,
          in the first part,
          proposed seven chapters and refuted them in a Catholic manner,
          by which war against the Indians could seem just.
          In the second part,
          however,
          that man adduced eight titles by which,
          or by some of them,
          the Indians could come under the dominion of the Spaniards.
          In which he supposes for the greater part certain things,
          most false,
          so that this war could be judged just,
          and these were reported to him by those plunderers who most lavishly lay waste that whole world.
          In some of those titles,
          however,
          he behaved somewhat more loosely,
          wishing to temper what seemed to have been said more harshly to the imperial supporters,
          although among lovers of truth in the first part all that he discussed was not harsh,
          that is not only true but Catholic and indeed most true.
          Which he himself sufficiently signifies when he speaks conditionally,
          fearing lest he suppose or say false things as true.
          But since the circumstances which that most learned father supposes are false,
          and he says some things timidly,
          certainly 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e732">Sepúlveda</name> 
          should not have thrust upon us his opinion based on false reports.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e740">
          ¶ Similarly,
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e744">Sepúlveda</name>,
          it would have been more decent of you not to cite the Reverend fathers 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e748">Michael de Arcos</name> 
          and 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e753">Master Herrera</name> 
          and 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e756">Master Esbarroya</name> 
          and the presented friar 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e762">Diego Victoriano</name>,
          learned monks from the institute of the blessed father Saint Dominic,
          whose names you boast as if they agree with you and approve your impious opinion.
          But since you,
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-Nd1e773">Sepúlveda</name>,
          are not ignorant of better things,
          how strongly some of them,
          present in this matter,
          resisted you boasting these things,
          complaining that you impute to them what they never said.
          Others,
          instructed by false reports and impious lies,
          responded not absolutely that this war could be just,
          supposing all those criminal lies by which they were led when they were consulted.
          Nevertheless they added that your work containing these impious things ought by no means to be published,
          lest this little book of yours,
          so greatly boasted,
          add courage to the impious,
          who lack nothing except opportunity,
          for plunder and murder.
          Which they themselves wrote to me voluntarily,
          provoked by no letters of mine.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e776-d1e810">
          Therefore cease to attach the names of so many men to your error,
          but rather assist the cause of Christ seriously,
          as befits a most learned man.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>