<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 43 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
            <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
            <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 43 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-17">April 17, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-17" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="189-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Hd1e97">Chapter 43</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e99">
          Chapter 43
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e104">
          Concerning this kind of persuasive compulsion,
          see I pray what Saint Thomas set forth in the third part,
          question 44,
          article 3,
          ad 1,
          where he says:
          Now to justify men was not fitting except for those willing.
          This would not be against the reasoning of justice,
          which implies the rectitude of the will,
          and also against the reasoning of human nature,
          which must be led to the good by free choice and not by coercion.
          Therefore Christ by divine power inwardly justified men,
          yet not against their will.
          And after many things (Saint Thomas says):
          concerning the souls of men,
          especially as to changing the lower powers,
          Christ worked certain miracles.
          Hence Jerome on Matthew 9,
          "Rising up he followed him"
          (namely Matthew) says:
          that very splendor and majesty of the hidden deity,
          which even shone forth in the human face,
          could draw those seeing it to himself at first sight.
          <pb ed="#P" n="190-r"/>
          And this was to invite and draw the Gentiles themselves sweetly through inspirations,
          illuminations,
          and by infusing in them wisdom and divine love.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e162">
          Saint Thomas adds in the same place:
          And on Matthew 21,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Qd1e166">"he cast out all who were buying and selling,"</quote>
          etc.
          The same Jerome says:
          to me among all the signs which the Lord made,
          this seems to be the most wonderful,
          that one man and at that time contemptible could cast out so great a multitude at the stroke of a single whip.
          Something fiery and starlike radiated from his eyes,
          and the majesty of the deity shone in his face.
          And on John 18,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Qd1e188">"they went backward and fell to the ground,"</quote>
          Augustine says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Qd1e195">"One word struck down a crowd fierce with hatred and terrible with arms,
            without any weapon,
            repelled them,
            laid them low.
            For God was hidden in the flesh."</quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e204">
          And Saint Thomas below:
          from all of which it is clear that when Christ willed,
          by divine power he changed the souls of men,
          not only by justifying and infusing wisdom,
          which pertains to the end of miracles,
          but also by outwardly alluring or terrifying or stupefying,
          which pertains to the miracles themselves.
          These things Saint Thomas said.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e225">
          Whence it appears that even the very manner by which Christ drew believers to knowledge of himself was miraculous.
          And there is no doubt that daily through the medium either of men or of angels,
          in illuminating men he uses such a manner.
          <pb ed="#P" n="190-v"/>
          This is clear in the conversion of blessed Paul.
          Acts 19,
          where we learn that Paul was made from a wolf into a lamb by a certain divine miracle,
          whereby surrounded by a heavenly light he was thrown down from his horse.
          Although we do not read of a similar calling elsewhere,
          therefore the Church celebrates it as unique and wonderful,
          as Thomas writes in 1a 2ae,
          question 113,
          last article in the body toward the end.
          Therefore such a calling should not be brought forward as an example.
          For it was particular,
          and particular privileges do not make a common law,
          etc.
          But the common manner by which the Lord draws men to himself without any compulsion,
          Saint Thomas explains in the Questions on Truth,
          question 22,
          article 8,
          and in the first part,
          question 105,
          article 3 and 4 throughout,
          and in other places of the Summa contra Gentiles.
          Saint Thomas says:
          God can change the will of necessity,
          yet he cannot coerce it.
          For however much the will is changed toward something,
          it is not said to be coerced toward it.
          The reason for this is that the very act of willing something is to be inclined toward it.
          But coercion or violence is contrary to the inclination of that thing which is coerced.
          Therefore when God changes the will,
          he makes it so that one inclination succeeds the preceding inclination.
          Thus the first is taken away and the second remains.
          Hence that toward which he leads the will is not contrary to the inclination now existing,
          but to the inclination which was there before.
          Hence there is no coercion or violence,
          <pb ed="#P" n="191-r"/>
          just as in a stone by reason of its gravity there is an inclination toward a place downward.
          But with this inclination remaining,
          if it is thrown upward,
          it will be violence.
          But if God takes away from the stone the inclination of gravity and gives it an inclination of lightness,
          then to be carried upward will not be violent to it.
          And thus an opposite motion can be without violence.
          And in this manner it must be understood that God changes the will without coercing the will,
          etc.
          These things Saint Thomas says in his own words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e344">
          Thus the Lord sweetly moves each thing to its end,
          according to that in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Rd1e350">Wisdom 8</ref>,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Qd1e352" source="http://scta.info/resource/sap8_1@1-12">"She reaches from end to end mightily and orders all things sweetly."</quote>
          Certainly most contrary is that motion by which divine wisdom draws created things to itself,
          especially rational creatures,
          to that which they imagine with unsheathed swords,
          fire-bearing devices,
          and cannons.
          For the human mind is such that it wishes to be taught,
          led,
          and kindly allured,
          not coerced by force and arms.
          For according to the Philosopher in the second book of the Physics,
          each thing is acted upon or drawn as it is by nature apt to be acted upon or drawn.
          For men naturally desire to be allured by sweetness and blandishments,
          as experience shows.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Rd1e383" target="http://scta.info/resource/sir6_5@1-7">Proverbs 6</ref>
          it is said:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Qd1e391">"A sweet word multiplies friends and softens enemies,"</quote>
          and 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Qd1e396" source="http://scta.info/resource/prov15_1@1-8">"A soft answer breaks wrath;
            a harsh word stirs up fury."</quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e404">
          And according to that of Valerius Maximus in book 5,
          the sweetness of humanity penetrates barbarian minds.
          <pb ed="#P" n="191-v"/>
          The cause of this is the generosity of spirit which,
          according to Seneca,
          is led rather than dragged.
          For the mind has something sublime and lofty and impatient of a superior,
          but it subjects itself through a certain delight of reverence or gentleness,
          by which it suspects it can ascend to equal things and not leap back from its own level.
          Thus 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-Rd1e428">the Philosopher in Ethics 8</ref>
          says that benevolence is the beginning of friendship.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e434">
          Therefore God uses his ineffable wisdom when he draws men to himself in these ways.
          And since no one can work those things upon the human will except God alone,
          namely that today it wills and loves what yesterday it shuddered at and avoided,
          sweetly disposing inwardly and inclining the minds of men to the contrary,
          which is all a miracle:
          for in vain would the tongue of the preacher labor outwardly unless the grace of the Savior were present inwardly,
          according to Augustine.
          But this appears clearly because many heard Christ's preaching,
          yet not all were converted,
          because Christ did not work the aforesaid effects inwardly in the minds of all the hearers.
          Therefore whoever comes to faith and changes his mind receives this from God.
          For all human terrors cannot change the human will unless Christ works inwardly.
          Again,
          among all the miracles of God,
          the conversion of a sinner is considered to be great,
          <pb ed="#P" n="192-r"/>
          both because of the magnitude of the work itself on account of the impediments which arise from sin—for 
          they separate man from God by an infinite distance—and 
          because it is directed to an eternal good.
          And according to this,
          Augustine,
          commenting on John chapter 14,
          explaining that passage "greater things than these he will do," says:
          it is greater to render a sinner just than to create heaven.
          Concerning this matter Saint Thomas treats in the first part,
          question 105,
          articles 7 and 8 throughout.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e504">
          Therefore,
          that Christ might show us the magnitude of his truth and the most powerful force of the divine word,
          by which he heals and cures those whom it is impossible according to nature—that is,
          without his help—to heal on account of their crimes,
          especially of idolatry and unbelief,
          making them sons of God and heirs of the heavenly kingdom,
          he used this word "compel to enter,"
          so that he might signify a change surpassing human powers.
          As if we should say,
          idolaters unwilling to cast off the worship of idols and other sins,
          by the word of Christ and of truth,
          with divine grace working inwardly,
          cast off the idols.
          To which also the example of good Christians preaching the Gospel helps.
          But that this literal exposition may be known to be the true one,
          let Theophylact be seen on the same parable,
          who says thus:
          by those who are in the road and at the hedges,
          the Gentiles are to be understood.
          For the Israelites were within the city as those who had received the law and obtained a more civilized life.
          <pb ed="#P" n="192-v"/>
          But the Gentiles were strangers from the covenants and from the law of God,
          and were not made citizens of the saints,
          nor in one but in many iniquities and great rusticity they lived,
          and at hedges—that is,
          sins.
          For sin is a great hedge and barrier dividing us from God.
          Therefore by roads he means the peculiar life of the Gentiles,
          divided into many opinions.
          By hedges he understands their life in sins.
          He does not simply command them to be called,
          but "compel," he says,
          although it is voluntary for all to believe.
          But that we may know it to be of great power of God that the Gentiles living in such great ignorance—
          therefore he said "compel."
          For unless great power were preached and there were great truth of the word,
          how would men raving in the worship of idols and doing foul works be persuaded so that suddenly they would recognize the true God and love the spiritual life?
          Therefore,
          wishing to signify the admirable transformation,
          he named it necessity,
          as if he were to say:
          even the Gentiles,
          unwilling to leave the idols and pleasures,
          were compelled by the preaching of truth to leave them.
          Or otherwise,
          the power of signs also brought great necessity so that they were transferred to the faith of Christ.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e621">
          And below:
          Therefore to those sinners wandering in the broad and spacious ways of sins,
          the father sends his son inviting to the feast,
          who according to the flesh was a servant,
          who came not to call the righteous but sinners.
          <pb ed="#P" n="193-r"/>
          And he invites them liberally,
          having taught those rich ones and those indulging the flesh.
          But by sending many illnesses and dangers,
          he makes them,
          even unwillingly,
          renounce this life,
          by which judgments he is accustomed to lead them to his feast,
          making necessity for them through danger.
          And of this there are many examples.
          But this parable teaches us that we should give rather to the simple,
          poor,
          and weak than to the rich,
          which he also had admonished a little before.
          We also learn another thing:
          we ought to be eager and generous in receiving the poor,
          and even so we should compel them unwilling,
          so that they may be partakers of our goods.
          Teachers are also admonished by this,
          that it is worthwhile to teach disciples even unwilling.
          All these things Theophylact said in his own words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e675">
          At the end he said to teach,
          not to wage war or inflict bodily or external violence.
          For weapons of war,
          as has often been touched upon,
          are not by their own nature ordered to the subjection of souls but of bodies,
          things,
          and places.
          Certainly far different is this exposition of Theophylact of the aforementioned parable "compel to enter" from that which the adversaries fabricate.
          To whom,
          I pray,
          shall we rather give credence in the exposition of Scripture—to 
          holy men whom it is most true that they had the Spirit of God in interpreting the sacred Scriptures,
          or truly to Sepulveda and his accomplices trying to destroy that immense world by deadly war against the law of Christ?
          Who dare to assert,
          as rashly as impiously,
          <pb ed="#P" n="193-v"/>
          that through the said parable Christ commanded us to disturb peaceful unbelievers living quietly through the enormities and turbulences of wars,
          to irritate the gentlest peoples,
          to despoil the poorest,
          to teach pride,
          cunning,
          malice to the most humble and most simple,
          to condemn free peoples into bitter servitude by tyrannical ferocity against the law of nations and nature,
          and lastly to make it impossible that nations most apt for faith should ever enter Christ's sheepfold.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e605-d1e753">
          Let the most vain dreams of these heads depart,
          not bringing forth solid doctrine to us.
          But what do they bring forth against evangelical truth and apostolic examples except calumnies,
          lies,
          and adulterated passages of Scripture?
          Therefore these wretches err,
          not knowing the Scriptures nor the power of God.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>