<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Dedication [English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Dedication [English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-21">June 20, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
          
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
        
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-21" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
          
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="f3-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-Hd1e97">Dedication</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#P" n="f3-v"/>
          Brother Bartholomew de Vega of the Order of Preachers,
          to the Supreme Royal Council of the Indies,
          Eternal Happiness
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e108">
          How much the author of this work has merited well of the kingdoms of Spain,
          illustrious judges of the royal council,
          can scarcely be said:
          indeed he was the first in matters concerning the Indians,
          both most difficult and supremely necessary for the wellbeing of the Spanish peoples,
          not to say of all the Indies,
          to discover the truth.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e119">
          For how much it matters in the business of the Indians to know the truth,
          to understand the causes,
          and to penetrate all the law,
          can be clearly established from the unheard-of plunderings and thefts,
          from the devastation of that new world,
          from the perdition of so many thousands of souls committed through ignorance of this matter.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e130">
          The ancient Romans and the cultivators of other kingdoms,
          whose republics employed just statutes,
          when undertaking some distinguished deed and inventors of things for public benefit,
          used to act in such a way that they would sculpt their images,
          which placed in temples or other locations they worshipped with the highest devotion,
          lest the memory of those be extinguished with death,
          whose life had brought benefit and utility to the republic.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e147">
          On this account there is no doubt that if the author of the present book had obtained those earlier times,
          mortals would worship his statue,
          and that he should be received by all as the discoverer of truth in the Indian business,
          and as the father of all who inhabit that new world,
          to be observed and loved,
          they would have decreed by public edict.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e158">
          Moreover,
          the doctors of sacred theology must be held in great esteem,
          and all the jurists,
          who devoting care to composing books have illuminated the world with their teaching,
          among whom those indeed must be valued much more highly who,
          receiving light from no mortals,
          themselves first shed light and truth upon the whole world.
          Wherefore the Most Reverend Bishop of Chiapas has merited especially well of the Spanish people,
          who not only first showed the way in recognizing the justice of the Indians,
          and by his work and labor in this highest and most difficult business the truth shone forth upon all Spain:
          but also for many years in the disputation and examination of this matter he waged war with certain doctors,
          who strove with all care to defend the opposite altogether to the truth,
          and to this very day are unwilling to desist from their insane opinion,
          who unless they had been repulsed and likewise convicted with full effort by the aforementioned Bishop,
          would have infected almost all of Spain with that most false dogma of theirs.
          Who since they err completely in the justice and causes of the Indians and are blind,
          are not afraid to teach a deadly sect and errors concerning the matter of the Indies,
          <pb ed="#P" n="f2-r"/>
          by which many are still held captive.
          Asserting that they fight no less securely for the truth,
          sustaining the just cause of our Spaniards.
          When they ought rather to defend the cause of God and of the Indian peoples,
          who have been redeemed by the blood of Christ,
          of whom so many thousands of souls through this so impious and so unjust disseminated dogma,
          we do not doubt are burned in eternal fire.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e209">
          This ignorance therefore so harmful to so many,
          this I say so profound darkness of the Spanish peoples,
          is far removed from the present work.
          In which by many arguments of nature itself and by very many most clear testimonies both of the sacred scriptures and of the holy doctors,
          and also by the decrees of councils and pontiffs,
          a clear demonstration of truth and justice in the Indian matter is made.
          In which work also many new things are taught but indeed necessary to all,
          which we acknowledge the aforementioned doctors of no common eloquence otherwise to have been.
          Here is taught the manner of preaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ.
          Here likewise is shown by what means unbelievers are to be converted to the faith.
          Here the tyrannies of the Indies are laid bare.
          Incredible plunderings are revealed.
          Impious slaughters are condemned.
          The way is opened for remedying injuries.
          All doubts are made clear.
          And what is far more wonderful to say,
          the Indian matter which hitherto for seventy passing years remained so obscure and so rough and disordered:
          now presents order,
          now is clearer than light itself,
          now escapes no one,
          now is known by all.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e244">
          Indeed this book is that by which darkness is driven from Spain,
          the mist is put to flight,
          men are awakened,
          the deceived return to better sense,
          those who were wise in their own eyes are confounded.
          Finally all Spain is illuminated which until now in so great a business of the Indies 
          (which without doubt is the greatest of all others that are under heaven)
          has remained ignorant.
          For there is no thing (unless I am mistaken)
          which can surpass this Indian business in magnitude.
          Inasmuch as in it nothing less is at stake than the salvation and perdition both of bodies and of souls of all the inhabitants of that newly discovered world.
          Therefore this work must deservedly be held in the highest regard since indeed it is necessary to the whole universe.
          In which the author expended so much labor,
          grew old with so many cares and vigils,
          pored through so many volumes,
          that in very fact anyone can easily discover.
          He will repay his zeal and labors perfectly,
          <pb ed="#P" n="f2-v"/>
          who promises a reward to those bringing forth into the light the truth and wisdom which is God,
          saying:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-Qd1e281">
            Those who illuminate me shall have eternal life.</quote>
          
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e01-d1e281">
          And since it is clearly established that so great a work will benefit all Spain,
          may your highness deign to order it to be printed and with royal favor and spirit,
          whose proper duty it is as moderator and protector of all the Indies concerning this most difficult and at the same time necessary matter to explore the truth.
          Lest through ignorance of this truth that new world be utterly extirpated and the residue of souls be consumed by eternal fire.
          But if by your command this work be committed to the press so that the truth of this matter may become known to all,
          many things (as I believe)
          will be restored to their pristine state.
          And it cannot be said how much increase will be added to the kingdoms of Spain.
          For which as I myself am especially bound I pray both temporal advancement from day to day and likewise eternal happiness.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>