<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 33 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
            <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
            <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 33 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-15">May 15, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a 
          diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-15" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="144-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Hd1e97">Chapter 33</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e99">
          Chapter 33
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Since therefore through the tumult of wars the innocent cannot be 
          distinguished from their oppressors,
          when nevertheless it is well known that there are innumerable innocent persons,
          both on account of the immense multitude of mortals and on account of the fury of war and 
          seditious tumult,
          in which a son does not respect his father,
          nor does a father show mercy to his son,
          to say nothing meanwhile of the greed for plunder or the shameless and cruel license of the 
          invaders for perpetrating evil.
          <pb ed="#P" n="145-r"/>
          Then finally there is the confusion and terror of those invaded,
          and the fact that many who seem evil are not evil;
          and in a doubtful matter,
          as Chrysostom said,
          it is more just for the unjust to escape justly than for the just or innocent insofar as they are 
          such to perish unjustly;
          whence according to him the first is according to justice,
          but the second is unjust.
          Similarly it is more holy to leave the crime of a guilty person unpunished than to condemn an 
          innocent person.
          Moreover,
          we ought not to help one person with injury or harm to another,
          etc.
          For which reasons indeed the human laws,
          both canonical and civil,
          seem to conform to Christ's prohibition;
          it follows that by natural and divine law and also by human laws it is forbidden that in a case 
          where there is no other remedy except through war we cannot meet the disadvantages of such 
          innocent persons,
          we are bound by natural,
          human,
          and divine precept to tolerate and overlook those things,
          lest infinitely many perish cruelly forever,
          who if drawn by gentle and moderate arguments to the yoke of Christ might perhaps obtain 
          salvation from the corruption of the weeds into healthful wheat.
          All of which Chrysostom comprehends in his homily 47 on Matthew,
          where he also asserts that heretics are not to be killed in these words:
          "But the Lord forbids lest perhaps together with the weeds they also pull up the grain of wheat,"
          which he said in order to prohibit wars and the shedding of blood.
          For if the wicked were slaughtered without a treaty of peace and truce,
          <pb ed="#P" n="145-v"/>
          war would be brought upon the world.
          Therefore he prohibited it for two reasons:
          one,
          because they would harm the grain little;
          the other,
          because unless they were healed,
          they would not escape extreme punishments.
          Wherefore,
          even if you wish to punish them and not at all harm the grain,
          you must wait for the opportune time.
          But what if you will uproot the grain along with them?
          Certainly either because if you take up arms (he says),
          it is necessary that when you slaughter heretics,
          you simultaneously kill many of the saints,
          or because many changed from those very weeds would convert themselves into the condition of 
          wheat.
          If therefore you pluck them up prematurely,
          those grains will perish that would come from the changed weeds.
          All these things Chrysostom says explicitly.
          You see therefore that divine and human decrees and natural reason itself support this sentence 
          full of equity and Christian moderation.
          Therefore let us recognize that it is iniquitous and impious to attack the Indians with war for 
          such causes.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e258">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> A fourth reason can be added to prove this through the analogy of the 
          punishment of crimes.
          For to punish crimes is not an act of justice except insofar as the offender is brought to a 
          better mind by the punishment or the peace and quiet of the republic is restored.
          For indeed if the punishment of a crime or the remedy that is assumed to prevent crimes produces 
          greater crimes either in quality or in number,
          or the whole republic is destroyed,
          it is a vice to punish crimes,
          not a virtue nor an act of justice.
          This is proved from Augustine in the second letter to Macedonius and is read in c. Prodest,
          23,
          q. 5,
          where he says:
          "Whether by punishing or by pardoning,
          this alone is done well,
          that the life of men may be corrected."
          These are his words.
          For in this life punishment is not inflicted so that it may be punishment,
          for this is not the place of full retribution;
          therefore punishment in this life is imposed as medicine,
          not as punishment.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e305">
          Again it is proved because punishment or the prevention of crimes is also assumed like a certain 
          medicine or remedy for disease.
          But a medicine,
          if it increases the disease of the body,
          is poison rather than medicine.
          For what if,
          in order to heal the foot,
          you harm the eyes?
          Would he be the best physician who,
          in order to treat a finger,
          cuts off the hand?
          Medicine sometimes harms lesser parts in order to bring health to the principal ones,
          but not the reverse.
          So if the punishment of a crime or the prevention of crimes increases crimes either directly or by 
          occasion,
          it would be a crime to punish crimes or to wish to prevent them,
          and it would be contrary to all virtue.
          Which Augustine asserts in book 2 against the letter of Parmenian,
          which is read in c. non potest,
          23,
          q. 4:
          "Indeed (he says),
          <pb ed="#P" n="146-v"/>
          when the contagion of sinning has invaded the multitude,
          the severe mercy of divine discipline is necessary.
          For counsels of separation,
          namely through death or excommunication,
          are vain and pernicious and sacrilegious because they are impious and proud,
          and they disturb the weak good more than they correct the bold wicked."
          These are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e365">
          Where Augustine sufficiently criticizes untimely punishment or the remedy that is assumed for 
          healing evils,
          calling it sacrilegious,
          pernicious,
          impious,
          and proud,
          from which greater evils are born than those it is intended to avoid.
          Again the same Augustine in the letter to Macedonius cited above and read in the same causa and 
          quaestio in the decrees:
          "But truly (he says),
          in such cases where through grave schisms of dissension not the danger of this or that man but the 
          slaughter of peoples lies at stake,
          something must be taken away from severity so that sincere charity may come to the aid of healing 
          greater evils,"
          etc.
          These are Augustine's words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e400">
          His words must be noted because he speaks about subjects of the Church who can be punished by it.
          Therefore punishment is not to be done or a remedy to be attempted when,
          for the punishment or remedy of that very crime,
          many would have to be killed.
          Now by law many are said to be more than forty,
          as in c. latores de clerico excommunicato vel deposito ministrante and de testibus,
          c. cum causam and c. significauerunt,
          and there the gloss and doctors note that the matter about which it is being discussed must be 
          examined so that we may judge who are many or few.
          But what if not forty or fifty men but innumerable thousands of men are endangered,
          among whom almost all are innocent and free from the crimes mentioned above?
          Would not then such a warlike prohibition be impious?
          <pb ed="#P" n="147-r"/>
          Third,
          the same is proved because the punishment of crimes or forcible prohibition is also remitted by 
          civil law by reason of multitude,
          as in the said c. latores and in c. 2 de temporibus ordinationum and 1,
          q. 7,
          c. quotiens,
          column 2,
          where it is said:
          "As often as a sin is committed by the people or by a crowd (because vengeance cannot be taken 
          against all on account of their multitude),
          it usually goes unpunished."
          And 9,
          q. 1,
          c. ordinationes and 10 distinctio,
          c. ut constituerentur and 44 distinctio,
          c. comensationes and 4 distinctio,
          c. denique and there extensively the glosses and doctors.
          Hence arose that little verse:
          "On account of a great people,
          the crime passes unpunished."
          But if a sinning multitude is spared,
          much more will they be spared in our case,
          where many thousands of men never offended or merited punishment,
          who will necessarily perish and be involved in destruction together with a few guilty persons.
          To these applies what Chrysostom writes on Matthew,
          chapter 1,
          homily 1:
          "Whatever is sinned by many usually remains unpunished."
          These are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e493">
          So also for the same reason the crime of one who is powerful and has very many defenders ought not 
          to be punished or prevented,
          so that his crime cannot be punished or prevented without the death of very many who,
          gathered together as one,
          will defend him,
          for instance if he is a prince.
          So teaches Saint Augustine in book 2 against the letter of Parmenian:
          "Correction by many cannot be salutary except when the one who is corrected does not have the 
          multitude as his ally.
          <pb ed="#P" n="147-v"/>
          But when the same disease has seized very many,
          nothing else remains for the good but sorrow and groaning,"
          etc.
          23,
          q. 4,
          c. non potest.
          Likewise in the same book:
          "When anyone's crime is known and appears execrable to all,
          so that he has either no defenders at all or not such ones through whom a schism can occur,
          the severity of discipline should not sleep."
          Therefore where such defenders are present,
          the severity of discipline ought to sleep.
          And a little above Augustine says:
          "Let this be done where there is no danger of schism,"
          etc.
          In that causa and quaestio,
          c. cum quis.
          Hence it happens that the sin of a prince is punished by chastising the people or his kingdom,
          who never sinned,
          chastising (I say) with the punishment of loss,
          as we touched upon above.
          And this is clear in c. non est nobis de sponsalibus.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e555">
          In sum,
          this is the common opinion both of theologians and of jurists,
          that punishment is not to be imposed or correction made,
          or some good work done in itself,
          when it is feared that sedition or some great scandal will arise.
          But scandal,
          omitting the magisterial definition,
          is said to occur when suddenly a tumult,
          sedition,
          or war arises among some,
          <pb ed="#P" n="148-r"/>
          according to Dominicus in c. licet,
          45 distinctio,
          and in c. 1 de officio legati,
          book 6,
          and the Cardinal after Paul in the Clementines 1,
          column 2,
          de officio ordinari.
          Scandal is also said to be whatever impedes a pious work,
          according to that passage in Matthew 16 where Christ said to Peter,
          who was trying to call him back from death:
          "You are a scandal to me."
          Therefore all pious works,
          except those that are necessary for salvation,
          such as baptism and similar things,
          it is not a sin to omit if scandal is expected therefrom.
          Indeed,
          not to omit them for the place and time would be a sin.
          And this is so true that all punishments imposed by the pope,
          even excommunication or any other greater spiritual punishment,
          can be overlooked,
          and we would be bound by divine law if from the observance of the papal precept,
          to whose transgressors excommunication is imposed,
          sedition or tumult or war or other atrocious evils can arise.
          So teaches Innocent in c. inquisitione de sententia excommunicationis,
          doctors in c. si quando de rescriptis,
          all more extensively Felinus there.
          And generally,
          to avoid scandal it is licit to transgress all laws,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Rd1e649" target="http://scta.info/resource/nqqq3t-d1e874-d1e1167@54-69">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Nd1e650">according to Philip Probus</name>
              in the additions to the gloss of John the Monk in c. licet,
              column 3,
              book 6
          </ref>.
          And lest scandal arise,
          a generally imposed punishment must be omitted according to the doctors in c. nisi cum pridem,
          § pro graui scandalo de renuntiatione,
          and 
          <pb ed="#P" n="148-v"/>
          in the rule qui scandalizauerit de regulis Iuris;
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Rd1e669" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e473-Qd1e678">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Nd1e647">Hostiensis</name>
              in the summa,
              title de renuntiatione § cum si renunciatur,
              briefly however
          </ref>,
          where he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Qd1e678" source="http://scta.info/resource/nbht7y-d1e149-d1e1284@125-157">
            "But if one who avoids does not sin mortally,
            scandal must always be avoided in avoiding,
            as is proved below,
            Nisi cum pridem and de noui operis nunciatione,
            Cum ex iniuncto,
            § super eo
          </quote>.
          These are Hostiensis's words.
          Therefore let us admit both the little verse which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Rd1e691">the gloss</ref>
          cites in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Rd1e697" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t41-d1e149">
            the said c. qui scandalizauerit
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Rd1e700" target="http://scta.info/resource/nbht7y-d1e149-d1e1070@615-626">
            Hostiensis where cited above
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Qd1e705">
            "It is true of the teaching of life and justice:
            I always hold the first,
            I leave two on account of scandal.
            And then it is rightly said:
            It is more useful that discipline be omitted than that scandal be allowed to arise
          </quote>.
          To this opinion 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Rd1e720" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e473-Qd1e736">
            Saint Thomas agrees in 2a 2ae q. 43,
            article 7,
            ad 1
          </ref>;
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Rd1e725" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1613-d1e1287">
            q. 66,
            article 6,
            ad 2
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Rd1e731" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1623-d1e236">
            q. 68,
            article 1 in the body
          </ref>
          and in other parts where he says that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-Qd1e736" source="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1494-d1e1692@6-51">
            "the infliction of punishments is not to be desired for its own sake,
            but punishments are inflicted as medicines to restrain sins,
            and therefore they have the character of justice insofar as sins are restrained through them.
            But if through the infliction of punishments it is manifest that many and greater sins follow,
            then the infliction of punishments will not be contained under justice
          </quote>.
          These are Saint Thomas's words formally.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e706">
          And this is so true that even if to kill a tyrant who is the plague of the republic is a pious 
          work and worthy of reward,
          nevertheless this does not hold when from his death sedition or tumult producing great evils for 
          the republic will arise.
          <pb ed="#P" n="149-r"/>
          For then it is unjust to kill the tyrant,
          but groaning will console the patient.
          So also teaches the same Saint Thomas in 2a 2ae,
          q. 42,
          article 2,
          ad 3,
          and more fully in book 1 of On the Government of Princes.
          So also,
          although an unjust law does not have the force of law (according to Augustine in book 1 of On Free 
          Choice) nor does it bind in conscience,
          nevertheless lest scandal or sedition arise,
          subjects are bound to observe it at least as to external acts,
          according to Saint Thomas in 1a 2ae,
          q. 96,
          article 4,
          in the body.
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> But that greater,
          indeed the greatest evils will arise if war is waged to prevent the innocent from being 
          sacrificed and eaten has already been sufficiently proved above,
          and truly the war would be most impious;
          which we do not hesitate to show more clearly.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e759">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Let us suppose that it comes to the notice of the Spaniards that the Indians 
          or other pagans eat human flesh or sacrifice human victims.
          Let us suppose moreover that the Spaniards are so well-behaved and upright that nothing else moves 
          them except the liberation of the innocent and the amendment of the guilty.
          Would it be just to invade and punish them without any warning?
          You will say no,
          but they will send ambassadors to them who will warn them to abstain from these crimes.
          I ask you,
          reader,
          in what language will the ambassadors speak,
          Latin or Greek,
          or rather Spanish or Arabic,
          so that they may be understood by the Indians,
          <pb ed="#P" n="149-v"/>
          who understand none of these?
          Unless perhaps we believe that the soldiers will be so holy from God that Christ will grant them 
          the gift of tongues so that they may be understood by the Indians.
          Then what period will be assigned to them so that they may repent and abstain from those crimes?
          For a long time is required so that they may understand what is being said to them,
          and by what authority,
          for what reasons,
          and why it is commanded to them that they abstain from the sacrifice of men,
          so that it becomes evident that such evils are contrary to the law of nature.
          Moreover,
          within that period to be assigned to them,
          which must be long,
          certainly the warning does not bind them nor do they incur contempt.
          For a warning does not bind except when the period has passed.
          Similarly,
          a law,
          constitution,
          or precept does not bind anyone unless the words of the language in which it is proposed are 
          distinctly understood,
          as the jurist doctors treat.
          And it suffices to cite Felinus,
          who accumulates many things in the rubric de constitutionibus,
          column 4,
          and more extensively Gometius on the rules of the chancery in the rule de idiomate,
          page 231 with following pages.
          Immediately I ask,
          while all that time assigned to the Indians to repent has passed,
          what will the soldiers do?
          Will they be at leisure,
          perhaps in fasting and prayers,
          just as the forty monks did who were sent by blessed Gregory to convert the English,
          so that the Lord 
          <pb ed="#P" n="150-r"/>
          might deign to open the eyes of the Indians so that,
          receiving the truth,
          they might abstain from such crimes?
          Or rather will they desire with their whole heart and whole mind that they be so blinded that they 
          neither see nor hear,
          so that they may obtain the much-desired opportunity for plundering and capturing them?
          He is utterly ignorant of military dispositions who foolishly or most vainly suspects these 
          things.
          Indeed,
          they will desire with all their vows that the Indians either not understand the warning or utterly 
          reject it,
          so that,
          having their wish,
          they may rage against them with sword,
          flames,
          and all the disadvantages of extreme war,
          so that with the blood of innumerable men shed they may acquire wealth for themselves and lead the 
          survivors into servitude,
          contrary to the Lord's precept and the rule of charity by which they were bound to pour out their 
          property and life for the salvation of their neighbors.
          Indeed,
          even if Caesar himself were present,
          they would not abstain from plundering and slaughter for even two days,
          especially if the matter seemed to tend toward famine.
          Furthermore,
          I have ascertained that several of our soldiers wounded with drawn swords Indians coming to the 
          Spanish camps loaded with chickens,
          apples,
          and all kinds of food,
          so that they might render and display every service to the Spaniards,
          and returning to the camps they told that they had encountered those Indians armed,
          and to give credence to this they themselves feigned that some arrows had been shot from bows,
          and then under this pretext,
          having made an assault on the most innocent peoples who were thinking nothing of the sort,
          <pb ed="#P" n="150-v"/>
          they either slaughtered them or led them into servitude.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e950">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Moreover,
          let us suppose that the Indians suffer nothing of this sort and after a long time,
          or briefly,
          understand the warnings of the Spaniards.
          What if they respond that they do not kill innocents either for eating their flesh or for 
          sacrificing,
          but only those whom they condemned to death for crimes,
          or captured in just war,
          or who died naturally?
          And therefore that they do no injury to any innocent person,
          but rather to themselves when they eat human flesh according to their custom?
          Will not in this case the reason for freeing innocents from unjust death cease?
          And therefore there is nothing that Christians can object to them.
          For a case can be given in which it is licit to eat human flesh,
          namely on account of necessity and extreme famine.
          For then it is licit without sin to eat one who died of hunger or was condemned to death.
          For to eat human flesh,
          which is a certain savage and bestial thing according to Aristotle in book 7 of the Ethics,
          is contrary to the law of nature for two reasons.
          First,
          if innocents are killed for eating their flesh.
          Then because to eat human flesh is savage;
          indeed,
          rare are the beasts that eat the corpses of their own kind.
          When however human flesh is eaten out of necessity and innocents are not killed,
          but the corpses of the dead or of criminals,
          then certainly nothing is done contrary to the law of nature nor is any sin committed.
          <pb ed="#P" n="151-r"/>
          <ref>
            Augustine narrates a case of this kind in the City of God,
            book 22,
            chapter 20
          </ref>:
          <quote source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l22-d1e3751@29-52">
            "For if someone worn out and compelled by hunger eats human corpses,
            which evil has sometimes happened,
            as ancient history testifies and the unfortunate experiences of our times have taught
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
          Where he relates the history narrated in the fourth book of Kings,
          chapter 6,
          namely that two women ate the son of one of them in the city of Samaria when the city was pressed 
          by siege by the army of the Assyrians.
          For they sinned because they killed an innocent;
          but if their sons had died naturally and they were suffering extreme famine,
          they would not sin at all by eating the flesh of the dead son.
          So the Spaniards ate the liver of a dead companion.
          For certain Spaniards returning to the island of Cuba from the newly discovered Yucatan descended 
          from ships into certain mountains with no provisions,
          and when a certain Biuerus by name,
          very well known to me,
          was dying of hunger,
          his companions,
          lest they suffer the same fortune,
          ate his liver.
          The same thing happened at Numantia,
          a very famous city of the Spanish lands.
          For the Numantines,
          besieged by Scipio,
          when they were pressed by extreme famine,
          ate human corpses,
          which the Bishop of Gerona relates in the Paralipomena of Spain,
          book 7,
          in these words:
          "And so the Numantines,
          thus besieged and driven by hunger to the point of eating human flesh at last,
          finally offered surrender to Scipio if he should command tolerable and humane things."
          These are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e1096">
          If therefore the infidels responded that they eat such men,
          <pb ed="#P" n="151-v"/>
          namely the dead or those who should be killed by right,
          but do not slaughter innocents,
          when the matter could be fully known,
          especially if the prince himself,
          whose word is by law presumed to be true,
          says so.
          But if war were waged against them before full and certain knowledge of the matter,
          would not the war be unjust?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e473-d1e1116">
          Then let us suppose that it is true and known that of their own accord and solely from a savage 
          vice they feed on the corpses of men,
          either those who died a natural death or were killed for their crimes or even captured in war 
          (which without doubt is the vice of bestiality and thus a sin).
          I ask whether solely for this cause war can be justly waged against them?
          Certainly not even then can we attack them with war for whatever crime they commit,
          even idolatry,
          as we proved above with ten reasons.
          For there is no judge or prince in the world who could punish such crimes except their own 
          princes,
          judges,
          and kings.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
