<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 54 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 54 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-12-12">December 12, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-12-12" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="229-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Hd1e90">Chapter 54 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e94">
          Chapter 54
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e99">
          ¶ Therefore 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e104">John Major</name> 
          teaches first:
          that a king should be stripped of his empire if the people are converted to the faith and he himself is unwilling to receive it:
          But 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e113">Major</name> 
          errs in fact,
          not knowing the disposition of the Indians,
          for none receive the faith more willingly or sooner,
          if they are rightly instructed,
          than the kings and princes of those nations (whom we commonly call caciques).
          Again he errs in law.
          For neither is a king to be compelled to the faith.
          Furthermore,
          one is not to be punished on the basis that he can do harm if he has not yet sinned or committed anything against his own people,
          because they have accepted the Christian religion.
          For innumerable things do not occur:
          which according to active and passive potentiality can happen,
          as per the Philosopher (5 and 9 Metaphysics):
          God never wills that an innocent person be punished,
          and a rightly begun work would perhaps be overturned if we tyrannically despoil a king of his kingdom for a sin not committed,
          even if he might commit it:
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e129">
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e156">John Major</name> 
          would act more prudently if he added that this should be understood when it is probably and vehemently presumed,
          not by vain conjectures,
          that the king would bring loss to the faith or punish the people:
          which is scarcely to be believed concerning Indian princes,
          given their most gentle nature.
          But if there were a vehement suspicion,
          then something should be given to him in compensation for the kingdom,
          as per 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e177" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t34-d1e225">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e178">Innocent</name> 
            in c. quod super his de voto
          </ref> 
          where,
          speaking of pagan princes who have occupied our provinces,
          he teaches that they are not to be despoiled or deposed from their kingdom,
          even if the people are converted to Christ:
          lest sedition and hatred of the Christian name be instilled in the minds of the pagans.
          How much more should this theologian have taught this,
          speaking of Indians whom he had never seen:
          who have not occupied Christian provinces:
          nor have they ever heard the Christian name,
          dwelling in kingdoms most remote from our world.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e212">
          ¶ Second,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e216">
            <sic>John</sic> Major
          </ref> 
          teaches that such a prince should be stripped of his lordship:
          so that his subjects can freely profess the Catholic faith.
          But he errs,
          because since the jurisdiction of princes,
          even pagan ones,
          is by natural law and by the law of nations and divine law,
          as we have proved elsewhere most extensively with irrefragable arguments and authorities of divine Scripture,
          certainly even if his subjects are converted to the faith,
          they owe him reverence and obedience in those things which are not against God,
          as to a lord,
          and his jurisdiction endures,
          and tributes must be paid to him if indeed they exercise jurisdiction without harm to the faithful.
          Even if the prince himself is unwilling to be converted to the faith.
          For Truth itself 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e255" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e255">Matthew 22</ref> 
          taught that the Jews should pay tribute to Tiberius Caesar,
          a pagan prince.
          He said,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e255" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt22_21@9-12">
            Render to Caesar what belongs to Caesar
          </quote>,
          to which response Paul the Apostle,
          in agreement,
          teaches that believers should be subject to principalities and powers,
          etc.
          This 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e270">Jerome</name> 
          teaches in the place cited below and says and adds the words of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e274" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e280 #lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e283 #lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e292 #lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e300">
            Saint Paul to the Romans 13.
          </ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e280" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_1@1-6">
            Let every soul be subject to higher powers
          </quote>.
          And below:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e283" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_5@1-8">
            Therefore by necessity be subject:
            not only because of wrath
          </quote> 
          that is,
          for the sake of avoiding temporal or corporal danger or punishment:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e292" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_5@9-12">
            but also for conscience sake
          </quote> 
          that is,
          lest there be sin in conscience:
          because 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e300" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_2@2-14">
            he who resists the power resists the ordinance of God and acquires damnation for himself
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e309">
          But that Christians are commanded to obey their princes,
          even though they are unbelievers,
          is proved first from the holy doctors thus explaining the words of Paul to the Romans 13.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e318">
          It is proved second:
          because as is clear from the histories,
          both sacred and profane,
          at the time when Paul wrote this,
          all princes were pagans under whom the apostles and the faithful lived.
          Which also teaches 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e332">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e333">Chrysostom</name> 
            on those words
          </ref>:
          for they are ministers of God.
          For at that time Christians were mostly common people,
          according to 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e341">Chrysostom's</name> 
          words.
          Therefore Paul transmits that precept to his own,
          that is to Christians,
          "let every soul",
          not to pagans who either ridiculed it or did not acknowledge it.
          Moreover Paul adds:
          "render to all their dues:
          tribute to whom tribute is due;
          custom to whom custom."
          Which the same Paul clearly teaches 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e359">1 Timothy 6</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e364" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_1@1-4">
            Whoever are under the yoke
          </quote> 
          namely of the unfaithful,
          according to the interlinear gloss,
          are 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e372" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_1@5-7">
            servants,
            let them consider their masters
          </quote> 
          namely unfaithful ones 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e376" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_1@8-17">
            worthy of all honor:
            lest the name of the Lord and doctrine be blasphemed
          </quote>.
          And it follows:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e388" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim6_2@1-13">
            But those who have believing masters,
            let them not despise them because they are brothers:
            but rather let them serve them
          </quote>.
          Therefore service should be rendered to unfaithful masters or princes by subjects,
          even if the subjects are Christians but the lord is an unbeliever.
          Which more clearly the 
          gloss 
          teaches on those words "let every soul be subject to higher powers".
          The 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e406">gloss</ref> 
          says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e408">
            For it seemed that unfaithful masters should be equals to the faithful:
            this arrogance too the apostle removes.
            For there is no power except from God.
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e419">This gloss</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e422">
          And again on those words 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e426">
            "lest the name of the Lord and doctrine be blasphemed",
            the interlinear gloss says:
            as if one invading another's property:
            but rather through the services of faithful servants,
            the unfaithful masters may be converted:
            and the doctrine,
            namely the Christian one,
            as if preached unjustly and contrary to law,
            may be blasphemed
          </quote>.
          This is it.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e446">
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e448">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e449">Saint Thomas</name> 
            on the first epistle to the Corinthians 6,
            lecture 1a at the beginning
          </ref> 
          says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Qd1e456">
            it is against divine law to prohibit:
            that the faithful not appear before the judgment of unfaithful princes if they are summoned:
            or before those appointed,
            that is magistrates or judges established by them,
            since it pertains to the authority of a prince to judge concerning subjects.
            For this would be against the subjection which is owed to princes
          </quote>.
          These things from him,
          as it were,
          in form.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-d1e464">
          Therefore an unfaithful prince should not be deposed and despoiled of his kingdom for the freedom of the Catholic faith;
          rather indeed his subjects should pay him tribute.
          Which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e487" target="http://scta.info/resource/jsnvu6-e146938-d1e441">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e488">Durandus</name> 
            in Sentences II,
            distinction 44,
            q. 3
          </ref> 
          confirms by evident reason:
          because that the subjects of some pagan prince are converted to the faith does not increase his sins nor is it a new crime for him,
          wherefore it is only their merit and not his fault.
          Therefore since he does not deserve to be deposed if his subjects did not receive the faith:
          much less would he be deposed if his subjects receive it.
          And certainly the opinion of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e508">John Major</name> 
          savors of the heresy of those who think through baptism they are liberated from all obedience and obligation of paying tribute:
          whom 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e517">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Nd1e518">Jerome</name> 
            on Paul's Epistle to Titus,
            c. 3
          </ref> 
          reports defend themselves by the words of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e750-Rd1e523">Paul to the Galatians 2a c. 4</ref> 
          namely (those words) "with what liberty Christ freed us."
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>