<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 41 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 41 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-21">April 21, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-21" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="181-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-Hd1e97">Chapter 41</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-d1e99">
          Chapter 41
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> From the foregoing it appears the difference of heretics 
          from other infidels, 
          especially those who have neither received nor heard the faith.
          <pb ed="#P" n="182-r"/>
          It appears furthermore that the Church has jurisdiction or authority over infidels,
          and over which ones, 
          either in habit and act simultaneously or in habit only. 
          And in what manner and when she can reduce the habitual to the actual, 
          both coercively and voluntarily. 
          Ignorance of this truth has brought forth the greatest evils to the Indian world 
          and has given occasion to turbulent men to afflict their brothers 
          with unaccustomed cruelty with great detriment to divine honor 
          among those who did not know God, 
          with loss and impediment to the faith 
          and horror of the Christian religion. 
          They have treated this matter (namely) 
          when war can be waged against infidels: 
          Oldradus in consilio 72, 
          Albericus in rubrica de paganis et sacrificiis, 
          Corsetus in tractatu de potestate et excellentia regia q. 82 columna 5 ibi primo poenam.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-d1e161">
          Others have attempted to bring Hostiensis and Innocent into agreement. 
          Of this class was Peter Ancharanus 
          in regula peccatum quaestione 3 columna 13 et 14 de regulis iuris, 
          Peter Bertrandus in tractatu de origine iuris quaestione 4, 
          Corsetus in the place cited above and others in c. quod super his de voto. 
          Yet all conclude, 
          besides Bartolus in l. Christianis C. de paganis et sacrificiis 
          and in l. hostes in finem, ff de captiuis et postliminio reuersis, 
          they give understanding of the truth of this matter through a certain distinction 
          which he makes concerning the nations that are subject to the Roman people 
          (that is) the Christian people.
          <pb ed="#P" n="182-v"/>
          Yet all have spoken very confusedly, 
          perhaps because they did not think there would be infidels in the world 
          such as there were formerly and we now see. 
          The lord <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-Nd1e200">Cardinal Cajetan</name> 
          alone left all theologians as well as jurists behind by a long interval. 
          Indeed, 
          he who brought light to this matter 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-Rd1e209" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAcCaj-d1e1613-Dd1e1633">
            in Summa Theologiae 2a 2ae question 66 article 8 ad 2um</ref>.
          For the distinctions of this most learned man the slanderers of the Indians 
          did not understand; 
          who moreover do not fear to dissent from the most erudite man's doctrine 
          with brazen face, 
          with no legitimate reason given by which they might be led to feel differently. 
          For they say that the words of <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-Nd1e230">Cajetan</name> 
          teaching that it is not lawful to wage war against infidels 
          for infidelity alone are to be understood 
          when they are only infidels but not when they are idolaters.
          For in this case they arrogantly reject 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-Nd1e241">Cajetan's</name> doctrine. 
          Moreover these men presuppose a falsehood when they say that one of the foundations 
          which <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-Nd1e248">Cajetan</name> adduces is that 
          the inhabitants of the promised land were not destroyed 
          on account of infidelity joined with idolatry. 
          But the swollen men add that this is false 
          from Deuteronomy chapter 9 and 12 and 18 and Leviticus 13 and 20. 
          Indeed those who assert these things have by no means understood Cajetan 
          or were unwilling to understand him. 
          For <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-Nd1e265">Cajetan</name> does not say that 
          the inhabitants of the promised land were not destroyed on account of idolatry 
          and other sins, 
          which Scripture asserts in many places of Deuteronomy and the book of Joshua; 
          but that he does not read in the Old Testament of war against infidels in those regions,
          <pb ed="#P" n="183-r"/>
          taking infidels for all who did not inhabit the promised land. 
          For the command of waging war handed down by God to the Jews 
          only comprehended those who inhabited the promised land, 
          not truly others dwelling outside that region. 
          And yet all were idolaters and sacrificed their sons to demons 
          just as all other nations did. 
          This was the mind of Cajetan, 
          whom being most practiced in the sacred scriptures, 
          it is not to be believed that he was ignorant that 
          the infidel inhabitants of the promised land were warred against 
          on account of idolatry and other sins. 
          The words of Cajetan are these: 
          "Nor in the Old Testament where by armed hand possession of the land of infidels 
          was to be taken do I read that war was declared on anyone 
          because of this, 
          that they were not faithful: 
          but either because they were unwilling to give passage: 
          or because they had offended them as the Midianites: 
          or to recover their own things granted by divine bounty etc." 
          Thus he. 
          Which opinion also <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-Rd1e331" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/victoria-relectio-de-indis">
            the most learned brother Francisco de Vitoria proves in his Relectio de Indis title 5</ref>.
          Therefore falsely do the slanderers of the Indians object to Cajetan 
          what he neither dreamed of nor thought. 
          He only says that no sins of infidels, 
          no idolatry, 
          no sins against nature have caused war to be waged against infidels 
          outside these three causes. 
          Again, 
          against the foundation of Cajetan,
          <pb ed="#P" n="183-v"/>
          adducing in proof of his opinion the example of Christ and the apostles, 
          they object that this is the foundation of heretics 
          against whom Saint Augustine wrote. 
          But we have already most extensively refuted their pernicious opinion above 
          from the sacred scriptures and the traditions of the holy doctors. 
          Further, 
          other theologians unworthy of this name, 
          whose name meanwhile we shall keep silent lest we harm them with public shame, 
          against the doctrine of Cajetan which sheds light on this matter, 
          devise certain ridiculous and absurd dreams. 
          It must not be passed over that a certain jurisconsult, 
          a shyster perhaps seeking (as human affairs are) 
          some greater fortune against Cajetan's doctrine, 
          so that through flattery he might gratify the king, 
          brought forth this argument: 
          The Indians of the new world descend from Hagar, 
          Abraham's handmaid. 
          Therefore it follows that they should be despoiled of all their possessions and kingdoms. 
          First, 
          Hagar was Abraham's wife though not the principal one, 
          yet she was not a cursed handmaid as he himself says. 
          Then how stupid, 
          how dull, 
          how shameless is the argument of this most vain man - 
          who can worthily declare? 
          Immortal God, 
          how it is to be lamented that our Spain, 
          otherwise most happy and mother of talents, 
          should look up to such dull heads as great men. 
          Then that men who ought to be the light and rule of virtue 
          should bring forth a most vain,
          <pb ed="#P" n="184-r"/>
          most dangerous, 
          impious thing worthy of the fire for the destruction of their soul, 
          so that innumerable mortals redeemed by Christ's blood 
          might perish eternally contrary to the example and teaching of Christ and the apostles 
          and be most cruelly slaughtered by the most rapacious Spanish people. 
          But to paint his vanity to the quick most briefly, 
          so that both he himself and others who under the pretext of these arguments 
          oppose evangelical truth and send so many myriads of mortals to hell, 
          may come to their senses both here and there and do penance, 
          and recognizing the truth, 
          may apply an antidote to the poisons which they have administered to the world.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-d1e496">
          Again this insipid jurisconsult brings forth against Cajetan Bartolus 
          in L. Hostes, ff de captiuis et postliminio reuersis. 
          And he makes a certain new distinction (namely) 
          that some infidels are those recognizing the dominion of the Church, 
          others truly who do not recognize it. 
          But Bartolus, 
          if he is read, 
          will set before our eyes this man's stupidity and ignorance.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-d1e517">
          For he treated this matter prudently in the said l. hostes 
          and in l. Christianis. C. de paganis et sacrificiis, 
          which we have taught more extensively in our other little works. 
          The shyster proceeds rather than the jurisconsult, 
          and so that he might completely bring forth his extreme stupidity to the world, 
          he asserts something intolerable to Christian ears, 
          namely that the Spanish can draw the sword against the Indians 
          without any preceding warning and plunder their goods,
          <pb ed="#P" n="184-v"/>
          since (he says) the warning of the apostles suffices for them: 
          "for their sound has gone out into all the earth" etc. 
          And moreover the Spanish warned them to receive the faith of Christ; 
          since they did not obey this warning but rather prepared arms, 
          by the best right they can be despoiled of their kingdoms 
          without any preceding warning. 
          The shameless sycophant adds laws and paragraphs; 
          he cites innumerable names of doctors. 
          But beside the point no less unlearnedly than foolishly. 
          I pray for a saner mind for him, 
          although he seems most learned to himself.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e579-d1e570">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> And through all these things which have been disputed and concluded 
          from chapter 24 up to this point, 
          we believe sufficiently to have satisfied the third cause 
          by which Sepulveda wishes those satanic expeditions or conquests 
          (as they call them) carried out by our people against the western and southern nations 
          to be justified. 
          But if you add to the predetermined things our twelve replies 
          related in the assembly, 
          and indeed most solemn, 
          of great men, 
          theologians and jurists, 
          by order of the emperor convened at the Council of the Indies at Valladolid 
          in the year of our Lord 1551, 
          you will see more clearly than light itself with what density of darkness 
          the eminent doctor and those adhering to his error are held, 
          and how most dangerously.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>