<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 61 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 61 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-02">July 02, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-02" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="249-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842">
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-d1e97">
          Chapter 61
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-d1e102">
          That the Catholic kings understood this to have been the mind of the pontiff,
          indeed even of Christ (namely that those peoples should be converted to the faith gently 
          and with Christian humanity,
          not truly by the terror of war being brought upon them):
          is proved from the words of the testament of the most serene 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-Nd1e120">Isabella</name> of Spain,
          ornament of the matrons of her age,
          to whom as Queen of Castile the concession was made especially by the pontiff,
          who speaks thus.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-d1e127">
          Item 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-Qd1e132" xml:lang="es">
            "Since at the time when the islands and mainland of the ocean sea,
            discovered and to be discovered,
            were granted to us by the Holy Apostolic See,
            our principal intention was,
            at the time when we supplicated 
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-Nd1e145">Pope Alexander the Sixth</name> of good memory,
            who made to us the said concession:
            to endeavor to induce and bring the peoples of them and convert them to our holy Catholic faith,
            and to send to the said islands and mainland prelates and religious and clerics 
            and other learned persons and God-fearing to instruct the inhabitants and residents of them 
            in the Catholic faith and teach them and endow them with good customs and to put in this 
            the diligence owed,
            as more fully is contained in the letters of the said concession.
            Therefore I beseech the King my lord most affectionately and I charge and command 
            the said princess my daughter and the said prince her husband that they thus do 
            and fulfill and that this be their principal end and that in it they put much diligence 
            and that they not consent nor give place that the Indians inhabitants and residents 
            of the said Indies and mainland gained and to be gained receive any injury in their persons 
            or goods:
            but command that they be well and justly treated:
            and if any injury they have received,
            remedy it and provide in such manner that they exceed in nothing 
            from that <add place="above-line">which</add> by the letters of the said concession 
            is enjoined and commanded to us."</quote>
          These are her formal words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-d1e212">
          You hear,
          reader,
          that the queen understood that war was not to be waged against the Indians 
          from the bull of the pontiff:
          but that they were to be instructed in Christian doctrine,
          this was commanded to her.
          You see also that she expressly orders:
          that from all injury both the Indians and also their neighbors be immune:
          for plunder had not been offered but a province.
          Therefore she commands her heirs that they make amends for every injury inflicted 
          on the Indians:
          and that they perform in all things what was enjoined upon her by the pontiff.
          And thus by many instructions,
          decrees,
          and mandates of our kings:
          it was expressly decreed and declared.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-d1e242">
          To these things agrees that the pontiff does not grant to the kings of Castile 
          that they subject those kingdoms to themselves,
          that they might amplify the boundaries of their empire by the addition of so many new kingdoms:
          but that those peoples might recognize Christ the true God and be drawn forth from darkness 
          into light,
          from death into life.
          And so it cannot be denied that that concession of the pontiff was made rather in favor 
          of the Indians than in favor of the kings.
          But if by war we utterly destroy that people and savagely afflict them,
          we act most unjustly:
          as is evident 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-Rd1e270">de regulis Iuris libro 6o</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-Qd1e272" source="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1612-d1e526">
            "what is granted on account of someone,
            ought not to be turned back to his disadvantage."</quote>
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-Rd1e279" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e204-d1e171">
            C. de legibus L. quod fauore</ref> 
          and ff 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-Rd1e285">eo titulo L. nulla juris</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-Qd1e294" source="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e81">
            "no reason or kindness of equity allows that things which are introduced wholesomely 
            for the utility of men:
            these we should by a harsher interpretation bring forth against their advantage to severity,"</quote> 
          thus there.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e842-d1e308">
          Therefore the kings of Castile can neither directly nor indirectly do anything adverse 
          to the spiritual or even temporal advancement of those peoples:
          indeed not even to their temporal good.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>