<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 51 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 51 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-16">July 16, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
      url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-16" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="216-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Hd1e97">
        Chapter 51 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e99">
          Chapter 51
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e104">
          In a very similar manner <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e110">Doctor Sepulveda</name> 
          perverts the correct and true understanding of the original texts of the most blessed Gregory the Great 
          and other saints. 
          Sepulveda asserts first of all that Gregory approved of wars 
          which Christians wage against infidels for this sole reason:
          that the faith might be announced more securely 
          to those subjected to Christian rule. 
          Therefore, because Gregory praises and gives thanks 
          to a certain exarch Genadius who waged a certain war against some infidels. 
          As in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e145">epistle 73</ref>,
          which is referred to by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e150">Gratian in c. si non ex fidei. 23. q. 4</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e156">
          Indeed Gregory, a most holy man, dreamed of no such thing. 
          For when he wished to lead the Angles to the faith, 
          out of the singular piety with which he was endowed, 
          he did not send armed forces against them as we reported above in chapter 45, 
          but <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e169">Augustine</name> 
          with forty monks who, by miracles and the word of God, 
          led that nation to Christ. 
          From the words of his epistle which Sepulveda cites, 
          it is gathered that Gregory praises Genadius not because he made war on the pagans 
          so that they might become Christians 
          (which Sepulveda falsely imputes to him), 
          but because he vindicated provinces 
          which had once been Christian from the power of pagans or heretics. 
          His words are these: "For," he says, 
          "we have learned that your excellency has provided very many advantages 
          for feeding the sheep of blessed Peter, 
          the prince of the apostles, 
          so that you restored with inhabitants 
          not a few places of his patrimony that had been stripped of their proper cultivators," 
          that is, the placement or restoration of the Dacians or Daci, 
          that is, of certain peoples according to the archdeacon. These are his words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e213">
          You see, reader, that Gregory is not speaking of a war 
          that is waged against pagans to subdue them 
          so that they might become Christians, 
          which Sepulveda wants done, 
          but of recovering provinces which had once been under Christian rule. 
          For it is manifest from many things deduced and fully proved above 
          that in the lands of infidels living peacefully 
          and not offending the Church, 
          blessed Peter has neither sheep actually nor patrimony that should be restored, 
          since they have not received the faith (as we suppose). 
          It is also clear from the word "restored" 
          that it presupposes a spoliation previously made. 
          For it is established that in the age of blessed Augustine, 
          the Vandals, first pagans, then Arians, 
          occupied Africa and possessed it 
          for more than ninety years until the time of Emperor Justinian, 
          as in l. 1. c. de officio prefecti pretorio africae. 
          And in the proem of the Institutes, and in the Authentics de haeredibus et falaci. 
          Vincent writes this in the Speculum Historiale book 21. c. 28 and 31. 
          But Gregory flourished fifty years after Justinian, 
          in whose time the Vandals were devastating Africa, 
          as is clear from the histories, 
          especially <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e275">Eutropius book 16 and book 17</ref>.
          Therefore in Gregory's age pagans possessed Africa.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e285">
          Nor does it present an obstacle that Sepulveda alleges 
          the Vandals had already been conquered by <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e290">Belisarius</name>. 
          For as appears from the history of Eutropius book 16, 
          in the seventh year of Justinian's empire, 
          he proceeds to Africa to fight three times with the Vandals, 
          about which something is found through Volaterranus 
          and Rupertus in his Dictionary. 
          And so it could be that they were not entirely cast down by Belisarius 
          (although some say that they were), 
          and consequently lasted until the time of Gregory the Great 
          and rose up again against the Roman or Christian people. 
          But whatever the case with the Vandals, 
          there were other pagans in Africa 
          and diverse peoples as Eutropius says in the same place, 
          besides the Marusii who descended from the peoples 
          whom Joshua and the sons of Israel drove out from the promised land, 
          or rather who fled from their sword, 
          and these were Canaanites or from those seven nations. 
          These, arriving in Egypt and not being received by them, 
          came to Libya which they named Hoen, 
          erecting two monuments above a great spring 
          from white concave stones having Phoenician letters saying: 
          "We are those who fled from the face of Jesus the robber, son of Nun." 
          So reports Eutropius in the same place. 
          These Marusii stirred up battle against the Africans 
          in the time of Justinian, 
          against whom went <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e360">Solomon</name>, 
          who was appointed governor of Africa in place of Belisarius, 
          and he killed fifty thousand of them. 
          From which it is clear that in Gregory's age 
          there could have been infidels in Africa 
          who might trouble the faithful 
          and usurp places belonging to the universal Church. 
          Therefore Saint Gregory gives thanks to Genadius himself, 
          the exarch of Africa, 
          because he recovered that region for the Church, 
          which is sufficiently clear from the inscription of the epistle, 
          which is such: 
          "Gregory gives thanks to Genadius, patrician and exarch throughout Africa, 
          for the benefits conferred on Saint Peter." 
          These words are there. 
          And since subduing those pagans was to expand the Church, 
          Gregory says: 
          "Your fame is that you frequently undertake wars 
          not from a desire to shed blood, 
          but only for the sake of expanding the republic 
          in which we see God worshipped, 
          so that the name of Christ might run about everywhere 
          through subject peoples by the preaching of the faith." 
          Gregory closes the epistle with these words: 
          "We ask the Lord and our Savior that He might mercifully protect your eminence, 
          whom He sent for the consolation of the holy republic, 
          and might strengthen you more and more by the might of His arm 
          for expanding His name through neighboring peoples." 
          These are his words. 
          The same thing we also ask with highest vows daily from the Lord, 
          that it be granted to us against the Turks 
          and Moors who harass the Christian Church. 
          Not indeed solely so that they might become Christians, 
          but because they bring injuries upon the Church 
          and tyrannically possess its provinces. 
          Therefore Gregory does not praise Genadius 
          because he made war on pagans so that they might become Christians, 
          but because he recovered from them provinces or places 
          which had once belonged to the Christian Church, 
          and because, with those savage enemies subjugated, 
          the evangelical light could be propagated through neighboring regions occupied by them. 
          These were Gregory's pious vows.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e452">
          Again, at that time the Donatists, 
          most savage heretics, had occupied the African churches, 
          who boasted that the Church was with them alone, 
          adding many other heretical dogmas 
          which <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e465">Augustine</name> 
          relates in his book on heresies and in a book labored against them particularly. 
          And Isidore in his Etymologies book 8, c. 5. 
          But that in Gregory's time there were still Donatists 
          is proved from epistle 72 of that book, 
          where he exhorts Genadius to see that a council 
          of Catholic bishops be celebrated against heretics. 
          And in epistle 75 he commands the orthodox bishops 
          that they should not ordain any Donatist reconciled to the Catholic Church as bishop. 
          Therefore Gregory praises Genadius 
          because he subdued the Donatist heretics 
          and took away churches from them, 
          just as he had previously recovered Christian provinces 
          by expelling the pagans. 
          This Gregory says in the said epistle 7 with these words: 
          "Just as the Lord has made your excellency shine with the light of victory 
          in this life through wars with enemies, 
          so it is fitting that you oppose the enemies of the Church 
          with all the vivaciousness of mind and body, 
          so that from both of your triumphs your reputation might shine forth more and more, 
          since both in foreign wars (namely) 
          which are waged against pagans you vehemently resist adversaries of the Catholic Church 
          for the Christian people, 
          and in ecclesiastical battles, namely which are brought against heretics, 
          you fight bravely as warriors of the Lord. 
          For it is known that men of heretical religion 
          (if, which God forbid, they have license to do harm) 
          rise up vehemently against the Catholic faith, 
          so that they might pour out the poisons of their heresy 
          to waste (if they should prevail) the members of the Christian body. 
          For we have learned that they rise up against the Catholic Church, 
          with the Lord opposing them, 
          and wish to overthrow the faith of the Christian name. 
          But let your eminence suppress their attempts 
          and press their proud necks under the yoke of rectitude." 
          And below: 
          "Great indeed is the glory that accrues to your excellency before the Creator 
          if through you the society of scattered churches can be restored." 
          These are Gregory's words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e550">
          From these things, reader, see that Genadius subdued by war 
          the Donatist heretics 
          and restored to Catholic bishops scattered churches occupied by heretics, 
          and that he fought against pagans 
          so that he might assert for the Church provinces 
          which had once been under Christian rule 
          and in which perhaps Christians dwelt. 
          For these things piously done by Genadius, 
          Gregory gives him thanks in the epistle immediately following, 
          namely 73, which Sepulveda cites outside the matter. 
          For Genadius is not there praised 
          because he subdued with armed forces the Vandals or Moors or other infidels 
          so that afterward, with the gospel preached, 
          the pagans might be converted, as has been proved. 
          But that <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e587">Gratian</name> 
          inserted those epistles in the ecclesiastical decrees 23. q. 4 
          is nothing to the point. 
          For he adduces those places only 
          to prove that it is not against Christ's law to kill the impious, 
          which the epitome of each chapter indicates.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e601">
          For the chapter "Sicut excellentiam" is inscribed with these words of its sense: 
          "Enemies of ecclesiastical religion are also to be restrained by wars." 
          And in c. "si non ex fidei" this inscription is read: 
          "By the merit of faith, victory in wars is prepared." 
          But who denies that enemies of the Christian religion 
          are to be restrained by war when the war cannot otherwise be ended?
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e623">
          Who denies that victory is prepared by faith? 
          But what do these things have to do with the opinion of Sepulveda, 
          alien to all reason and Christian doctrine? 
          Sepulveda proceeds and in confirmation of his error 
          also cites the same Saint Gregory, book 9, epistle 60, 
          where he exhorts Aldibert, king of the Angles, 
          to overthrow the worship of idols 
          and destroy pagan temples, 
          following the example of Constantine the Great, 
          who did the same for the Roman republic. 
          Indeed, since King Aldibert was already a member of the Church 
          through the faith which he had received, 
          by the best right Gregory the pontiff exhorts him 
          to overthrow the worship of idols, 
          and that exhortation had the force of a precept. 
          For the king himself was bound by divine law 
          to take care by all means that his subjects be led to the faith, 
          yet in the proper manner, 
          by the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e667">Augustine, City of God book 5, c. 24</ref> 
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e672">26</ref>, 
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e674">book 19, c. 16</ref>.
          It is proved in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e679">c. duo ista nomina 23. q. 4</ref>,
          there: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Qd1e684" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e668@70-73">
          "To a king ruling his own nation."</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e688">
          Moreover, it should be noted that the subjects of that king 
          were already in a certain way subjects of the Church, 
          even if they were pagans. 
          For when a king is subjected through baptism, 
          his entire kingdom is considered to be subjected 
          to him to whom the king has subjected himself, 
          as held by the doctors in Authentics ingressi. C. de sacrosanctis ecclesiis; 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e705">Baldus</name> 
          in l. si paterfamilias in the first reading, ff. de adoptionibus; 
          Lasso in Authentics ingressi column 8, C. de sacrosanctis ecclesiis; 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e711">Antonius de Butrio</ref> 
          in the repetition of the final chapter de causa possessionis et propriis. 
          But what Saint Gregory urges the king to do, 
          he was bound to do, 
          since those pagans were in a certain way his subjects (as has been said). 
          And the king without arms could, by edict, 
          overthrow the worship of idols in his own kingdom, 
          especially since it is probable that the nobles received the Christian religion 
          together with him. 
          For subjects always imitate their prince, 
          which Saint 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e739">Thomas writes in this matter, 2a2ae q. 10, a. 10 in the body</ref>.
          This was the mind of Gregory the Great 
          in proposing to him the example of Constantine with these words: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Qd1e750">
          "For thus Constantine, once a most pious emperor, 
          recalling the Roman republic from the perverse worship of idols, 
          subjected it along with himself to the almighty Lord our God Jesus Christ, 
          and converted himself with the subjected peoples to Him with his whole mind."</quote>
          These are his words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e768">
          For a prince can and ought to prohibit the worship of idols in his kingdom, 
          just as other public sins, 
          provided that it be done without great tumult or scandal 
          and without greater detriments than proceeded from idolatry, 
          as has been most extensively treated above. 
          Yet also, for the worship of demons which he wishes to overthrow, 
          he should offer them what is better, 
          namely the knowledge of the true God. 
          But if a king should prohibit the worship of idols by enacted laws 
          and not instruct his people in another religion, 
          certainly he could not do this. 
          For it is impossible for a man not to worship the true God, 
          or whom he thinks to be the true God. 
          Therefore princes, upon whom it falls to care for the utility of their kingdoms, 
          can overthrow impious religion 
          and introduce the worship of true religion, 
          since by natural law they have power over their own. 
          Hence (namely) because they were subjects, 
          Constantine forbade the worship of idols 
          under penalty of death and confiscation of goods, 
          perhaps by the counsel of blessed Sylvester, 
          moved by this reason, 
          as in l. 1 with those following, C. de paganis et sacrificiis. 
          And since Julian the Apostate restored the worship of idols 
          after Constantine's death, 
          by the authority of <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e828">Hugh of Fleury</name>, 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e833">Theodosius</name>, 
          the most pious emperor, completely overthrew idolatry in the empire, 
          with the temples of the pagans destroyed. 
          Arcadius and Honorius, sons of Theodosius, 
          who reigned after him, followed his example, 
          by the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e846">Vincent, Speculum Historiale book 19, c. 5</ref>.
          Likewise in cases in which infidels are subjects of the Church 
          or of its members, 
          we see laws prescribed to them by Theodosius 
          and by Arcadius and Valentinian, 
          who by enacted law provided that Jews should not celebrate marriages 
          according to the law of Moses, 
          but according to Christian custom, 
          not within the 2nd, 3rd, or 4th degree, 
          as in l. nemo Iudaeorum, C. de Iudaeis. 
          But if infidels were not subjects of the Church, 
          laws could in no way be prescribed to them by the Church, 
          as has been proved. 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e875">Theodosius</name> 
          mentions laws enacted on this matter 
          in the ecclesiastical history book 11, c. 19, 
          and book 9, and Tripartite book 9, c. 27, 28. 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e883">
          Augustine, City of God book 5, c. 26</ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e887">
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e888">
          the Archbishop of Florence</name> 
          in the second part of his history, title 8, c. 7, § 2</ref>. 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e894">
          Augustine in Epistle 43 against Vincent the heretic and Donatist</ref>,
          which are referred to in c. non invenitur 23. q. 4. 
          For this purpose also 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e906">
          Ambrose 
          exhorted Theodosius, epistles 30 and 31</ref>.
          No pious person fails to approve such laws, 
          and if a similar case should occur 
          where idolatry could be restrained in subjects 
          by the authority of princes without greater evil, 
          who would not care to have a similar law enacted, 
          if indeed he loved Christ from his heart? 
          But what has this to do with our case, 
          where pagans have never been subjects of the Church or its members, 
          and whose prince is pagan, 
          and who are not killed by their own prince 
          but by Spanish soldiers 
          and inhumanely subdued by war brought upon them, 
          so that the worship of idols might finally be overthrown 
          with an infinite multitude of men slain?
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e937">
          But someone may object that if it is pious to kill one going, 
          after the prohibition of law, to the worship of idols, 
          it will also be pious to overthrow idolatry by war. 
          Certainly this argument is no objection. 
          First, because in non-subjects there is lacking power and jurisdiction, 
          and thus the authority by which just war is supported; 
          second, because an idolatrous subject is killed 
          who can still be converted to Christ by the ministry of preachers, 
          since he sins through ignorance; 
          also the guilty one is killed without the ruin of the innocent; 
          but in war thousands of innocents are killed 
          with very few guilty ones, as has been proved above. 
          Therefore to subdue infidels by war so that they might receive the faith is impious. 
          Therefore the example of Constantine, Theodosius, 
          and other princes who by enacted laws ordered temples closed 
          and prohibited the worship of idols in their own kingdoms 
          has nothing to do with our case, 
          for the reasons given above, 
          and principally because, since they were princes, 
          they could give whatever laws they wished to their subjects. 
          But the Indians are not subject to us or to the Church, 
          because they are pagans and legitimate and free princes in their own kingdoms; 
          therefore we can in no way give them laws. 
          For that no one can impose law except on subjects 
          is most certain law, 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e1005">
          l. c. 1, de summa trinitate</ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e1007">
          l. final, C. de incestuo nuptiis</ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e1009">
          l. 3, ff. de officio presidis</ref>, 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Rd1e1014">
          c. a nobis, de sententia excommunicationis</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e1020">
          Also on the part of the Church a special reason applied 
          (namely) that the very princes of the infidels, or kings, 
          already pertained to its members, 
          and not the smallest part of their kingdoms, 
          who had already received the faith. 
          But the others not yet converted 
          also in a certain way pertained to the Church, 
          because (as we have said) they were in nearer potentiality than before. 
          Hence if in a kingdom already beginning to be converted 
          they should allow temples to be open 
          and the worship of idols to be publicly exercised, 
          not only was there imminent danger of apostasy from the faith 
          for the plebeians and common men, 
          but truly also for the prince himself. 
          Therefore it was most fitting, indeed altogether necessary, 
          that the Church and its prelates exhort Christian princes 
          to the destruction of idolatry, 
          and attempt with their might to overturn the temples. 
          And this is what Gregory was earnestly doing 
          in his epistle to Aldibert, king of the Angles.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-d1e1070">
          But concerning other peoples or infidels, 
          neither their princes nor anyone ever heard anything about the faith, 
          nor did they bring any offense to the Church through any of the aforementioned cases; 
          indeed, it never even came to mind what the Church was 
          or whether it existed in the nature of things, 
          by which they are in every way outside the Church. 
          Since indeed it is clearly apparent 
          that none of the aforesaid qualities occur in these people, 
          but rather directly all are contrary, 
          therefore the reasoning is very different concerning all infidels, 
          however much they may be devoted to idolatry, 
          provided they are not culpable in any of the six aforesaid cases — 
          very different (I say) from the reasoning by which Gregory and Ambrose and Augustine 
          were moved to exhort Christian princes 
          to destroy idolatry 
          and to commend their Christian laws concerning this. 
          From these things, therefore, it is apparent 
          how the original texts of the holy doctors of the Church are understood, 
          and also of human laws, 
          the reasoning of which the venerable doctor 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e710-Nd1e1128">Sepulveda</name> 
          ineptly adduces for himself, 
          when nevertheless they manifestly militate against him.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>