<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 52 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 52 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-12">July 12, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-12" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="223-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Hd1e97">Chapter 52 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e99">
          CHAPTER 52
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Moreover Sepulveda brings forward Augustine and Thomas,
          teaching that the Romans had a just cause for subjugating the world,
          because since they were superior to other peoples in prudence and justice,
          God willed that the world be governed by them.
          Sepulveda falsely attributes these things to Augustine and Thomas.
          For first,
          the Roman empire was not justly acquired but obtained through tyranny and violence,
          as we have proven elsewhere from historians,
          jurists,
          and theologians.
          What Augustine and Thomas taught I will set forth in good faith.
          Those first Romans,
          the original inhabitants of the city of Rome,
          were endowed with certain moral virtues,
          namely love for their country and zeal for public utility,
          which they preferred to their own advantages.
          They also established just laws and treated peoples subjected to their rule by war or otherwise gently and kindly:
          although in truth these were not real virtues,
          according to the same 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e154" target="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l5-Dd1e236">
          Augustine, On the City of God, book 5, chapter 12.</ref>
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e161" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q1-d1e553@1-9">
          chapter "Where there is sound faith," question 24.1,</ref>
          he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e165">
          Where there is not sound faith,
          there cannot be justice</quote>,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e170">
          Augustine therefore teaches that God,
          in his ineffable prudence and goodness,
          granted to these men the empire of the world because he was not going to grant them eternal life.
          So says 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e187">Augustine in the place cited above</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e190">Jerome</ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e192" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c28q1-d1e338">
          in question 28.1, § "From these things therefore," chapter "All."</ref>
          Saint Thomas, On the Government of Princes, book 3, chapters 4, 5, 6.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e201" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e206">
          Augustine, book 4, chapter 33,</ref>
          says,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e206" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l4-d1e649@1-20">
          Therefore that God,
          the author and giver of happiness,
          because he alone is the true God,
          he himself gives earthly kingdoms both to the good and to the wicked</quote>;
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e215" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e217 #lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e233">
          in book 5, chapter 28,</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e217" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l5-d1e825@1-36">
          Since these things are so,
          let us not attribute the power of giving kingdoms and empires to anyone except the true God,
          who gives happiness in the kingdom of heaven to the pious alone:
          but earthly kingdoms both to the pious and the impious,
          as it pleases him to whom nothing pleases unjustly</quote>.
          And a little below:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e233" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l5-d1e825@65-91">
          Therefore that one true God,
          who neither abandons the human race in judgment nor in assistance,
          when he willed and as much as he willed,
          gave the kingdom to the Romans:
          who also gave it to the Assyrians or even the Persians</quote>,
          etc.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e248" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e247 #lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e259">
          chapter 15:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e247" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l5-d1e778@1-53">
          Therefore to those to whom he was not going to give eternal life with the holy angels,
          if he did not grant them even this earthly glory of the most excellent empire,
          the reward would not be rendered for their good practices,
          that is,
          for their virtues</quote>.
          And at the end he concludes:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e259" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l5-d1e778@149-161">
          There is no reason to complain about the justice of the supreme and true God;
          they received their reward</quote>.
          These are his words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e267">
          The reason for this according to Augustine in various places is that it befits the admirable goodness of God that even the smallest virtue be rewarded:
          which is proven from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e282" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e299 #lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e327">
          Ezekiel chapter 29,</ref>
          where God,
          speaking of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Nd1e282">Nebuchadnezzar</name>,
          who by waging war against the inhabitants of Tyre had rendered him a pleasing service,
          says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e299" source="http://scta.info/resource/ez29_18">
          Son of man,
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Nd1e288">Nebuchadnezzar</name>,
          king of Babylon,
          caused his army to serve with great servitude against Tyre:
          every head was made bald and every shoulder was stripped of hair,
          yet neither he nor his army received wages from Tyre for the servitude with which he served me against it</quote>.
          And since such tyrants do not merit an eternal reward for their merits or services rendered to God,
          the Lord adds:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e327" source="http://scta.info/resource/ez29_19@6-31 http://scta.info/resource/ez29_20">
          Behold,
          I will give 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Nd1e313">Nebuchadnezzar</name>,
          king of Babylon,
          the land of Egypt:
          and he shall take away her multitude and plunder her spoils and seize her prey,
          and it shall be wages for his army and for the work by which he served against her:
          I have given him the land of Egypt in return for the labor he performed for me,
          says the Lord God</quote>.
          Likewise the Lord,
          in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e363" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e367">
          Isaiah chapter 45,</ref>
          addresses Cyrus,
          king of the Persians,
          with these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e367" source="http://scta.info/resource/is45_1@1-19 http://scta.info/resource/is45_2@1-8 http://scta.info/resource/is45_3@1-5">
          Thus says the Lord to my anointed,
          to Cyrus:
          whose right hand I have grasped to subdue nations before him,
          and I will turn the backs of kings.
          I will go before you and humble the glorious ones of the earth,
          and I will give you hidden treasures</quote>,
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e361">
          For his empire,
          although unjustly held,
          produced many things pleasing to God.
          First,
          he granted freedom to the Jews oppressed by captivity:
          giving them the faculty to rebuild the city and temple of Jerusalem so that God might be worshiped there,
          as is evident from the book of Ezra,
          chapter 1.
          Then Cyrus showed himself to be an executor of divine justice by killing Belshazzar,
          who,
          wishing to worship his idols,
          had the vessels of the Jerusalem temple that had been brought by Nebuchadnezzar brought out:
          and both he and his wives and harlots drank from them,
          as appears in Daniel chapter 5.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e391">
          Therefore divine providence grants a reward to tyrants whom it uses as instruments for the execution of its justice.
          And so the Romans received their reward.
          With this agrees what 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e404" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e410 #lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e423">
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Nd1e405">Gratian</name>
          brings forward in question 23.5,
          § "Hence it should be noted," chapter "They are remitted":</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e410" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q5-d1e937@3-38">
          Such men,
          he says,
          in that they punish,
          are said to serve God.
          But in that,
          ignorant that they are ministers of the wrath of God,
          they grow proud with impious vanity:
          nor do they find the reward of their virtue from God except a temporal one,
          but they do not escape the punishment of their pride</quote>.
          And below:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e423" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q5-d1e941@3-36">
          Similarly,
          when God decreed to punish through the Romans the sin of Christ's death:
          they presumed to ascribe the destruction of the city and the miserable captivity of the Jewish people to their own powers:
          Wherefore against them the prophet rebukes,
          saying:
          Lift up your hands against their pride,
          those who hate you and who have done many evil things,
          the monuments of their victory</quote>,
          that is,
          the standards and weapons they placed in the midst of your courtyard,
          that is,
          in the temple as a sign of victory,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e447">
          the gloss on Psalm 73</ref>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e450">
          Afterward 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Nd1e452" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e454">Gratian</name>
          </ref>
          adds:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e454" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q5-d1e948@3-51">
          When indeed by a hidden instigation some are moved to persecute the wicked,
          just as Sennacherib and the others who persecuted the sinful people:
          although by a hidden instigation,
          working through their merits,
          they are incited to persecute,
          nevertheless because with perverse intention they do not seek to punish the sins of the delinquents but to seize their goods or subject them to their dominion:
          they are not immune from crime</quote>,
          etc.
          These are Gratian's words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e478">
          Therefore,
          although such men serve God in a certain way:
          nevertheless they sin mortally because they wage war with the intent of plundering and ruling more widely,
          not truly with the intent of serving God.
          Which,
          beyond the above,
          is also proven from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e493">
          Isaiah chapter 10</ref>
          concerning Sennacherib:
          "Woe to Assyria,
          the rod of my fury,
          and he is the staff:
          in his hand is my indignation.
          I will send him against a deceitful nation:
          and I will command him concerning the people of my wrath,
          that he may take away spoils and divide the prey."
          And it follows:
          "But he shall not think so,
          and his heart shall not so esteem,
          but his heart shall be to destroy,"
          etc.
          From which it is clearly gathered,
          first,
          that God sometimes in a hidden act moves the impious and thus uses their ministry to punish sinners:
          which Ambrose writes in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Rd1e527" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e530">
          the said chapter "They are remitted."</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-Qd1e530" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q5-d1e927@10-23">
          Often,
          he says,
          even by foreigners raised up by God's command,
          on account of the offense of the divine majesty,
          the people of the Jews have been carried away</quote>.
          These are his words.
          Similarly,
          so that he may elicit good that he has disposed to gather from their evil acts,
          according to Augustine.
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> 
          Second:
          that the tyrants themselves neither intend that toward which he moves them nor wish what God wishes,
          but only direct their perverse heart toward despoiling peoples and subjecting them to their dominion.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e557">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> 
          Third:
          that because they do these things from lust for domination and not from love of virtue,
          they sin most gravely mortally and at the end of life are to be assigned to infernal fires:
          this is clear through that "woe" placed against Sennacherib:
          which Scripture never uses (according to the testimony of Jerome and Chrysostom) except from the process of mortal sin:
          which is finally to be punished by eternal damnation.
          God therefore used the Romans both to prepare the world,
          insofar as that part of it,
          for his gracious and sweet advent,
          and also to signify the unity of the church or of his holy kingdom through the union of peoples:
          who were to occupy the entire world.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e724-d1e594">
          Moreover he chose the Romans as executioners or executors of his justice to punish those peoples against whose crimes he was angry.
          Wherefore just as Nebuchadnezzar,
          for that which he served God in the plundering of Tyre:
          God permitted him to disturb,
          usurp,
          and dominate over Egypt:
          similarly Cyrus,
          to capture Babylon and kill Belshazzar:
          because nevertheless they did not do this to render obedience to the Lord:
          but all peoples they subjected to war out of ambition and lust for ruling more widely:
          therefore he finally cast them down into hell on account of their violences and injustices:
          and so he permitted and assisted the Romans to dominate the world as a reward for the effects already mentioned that he intended to elicit from their tyranny.
          Therefore Sepulveda should not thrust at us the tyranny of the Romans:
          to justify our tyranny against the Indians,
          which they called the conquest.
          For the Romans,
          the Persians,
          and the Assyrians perished forever because their wars were displeasing in the eyes of the Lord,
          as we have proven above from the holy fathers,
          and will appear more fully below with the Lord's help.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>