<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 46 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
            <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
            <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 46 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-08-25">August 25, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-08-25" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="201-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645">
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-d1e97">
          Chapter 46
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-d1e102">
          We must now see what more Christ commanded when sending his disciples to preach.
          For Luke says:
          take nothing for your journey,
          neither staff,
          nor bag,
          nor money etc.
          Where 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Rd1e121">Ambrose on chapter 9</ref> 
          says:
          What kind of person he who evangelizes the kingdom of God ought to be is designated by evangelical precepts:
          that without bag,
          without shoes,
          without money that is,
          not seeking the supports of secular aid and safe in faith he should think that the less he seeks these things,
          the more can be supplied.
          These are his words.
          And on chapter 10 the same Ambrose says:
          and therefore the good shepherd sends his disciples as lambs among wolves,
          because they are directed not to plunder but to grace.
          Therefore Christ does not want his faithful to be preceded by guards who intend nothing other than 
          to plunder the resources of others.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-d1e161">
          And the same 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Nd1e165">Ambrose</name> 
          expounding those words "do not possess gold" says:
          if we are forbidden to possess gold,
          why do we try to seize,
          why to take away?
          If you have been commanded to give what you have,
          how do you accumulate what you are forbidden to possess?
          Which words all true Christians ought to consider:
          For if Christ permitted us to accept gold from those to whom we preach the gospel,
          the pagans would think that the evangelizers announce the faith for the sake of gain.
          But if preachers are forbidden to accept gold that is offered,
          how much less will they be able to seize or steal the resources of others?
          Ambrose proceeds there:
          you who preach "do not steal," do you steal?
          You who say "do not commit adultery," do you commit adultery?
          You who abhor idols,
          do you commit sacrilege?
          You who glory in the law,
          do you dishonor God through transgression of the law?
          For the name of God is blasphemed among the nations because of you.
          Not thus Peter,
          who was the first executor of the Lord's sentence,
          so that he might show that the Lord's commands were not spread in vain,
          when he was asked by a poor man that he give him some money,
          said:
          silver and gold I have not etc.
          All these things are from Ambrose.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-d1e226">
          But the Spaniards waging war on the Indians under the pretext of spreading religion,
          will they give away their own money,
          or rather will they violently seize and plunder the money of others?
          Then the Indians,
          seeing the Christian people lusting after gold and collecting with the greatest diligence,
          preserving and all but worshiping the gilded fragments of broken idols,
          will surely think that gold is the God of the Christians,
          which we know for certain they have very often believed.
          Moreover,
          will those wagers of war meanwhile be so chaste,
          so continent and temperate that they will not violate the wives of others?
          Will they not rape their daughters?
          But after those nations have learned from the teaching of religious men that these and similar things 
          are sins prohibited by the law of the Christians,
          and that so few observe it—namely the religious—and so many act against it,
          that is all those men with none excepted,
          will they not reasonably think that whatever the preachers of the faith announce about the faith,
          about religion,
          about Christ himself,
          are ravings or fabricated lies?
          Will this wickedness in those who have given cause for so great a scandal and for the infamy of Christ 
          be expiable by any sacrifice?
          What then do these satellites of Satan boast to us that they amplify the glory of Christ,
          when by their impious works they defame the name of Christ,
          which ought to be adored among the idolaters,
          and render it hateful?
          And upon them most truly falls that saying of Paul 
          (which a little before Ambrose lamented):
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Qd1e311">through you the name of God is blasphemed among the nations</quote>?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-d1e311">
          Hear,
          reader,
          the blessed Ambrose himself on Luke book 7 chapter 44:
          What is the rod but the emblem of the power to be exercised and the instrument of avenging pain?
          Therefore the humble command of the Lord—for in humility his judgment was exalted—
          the humble command of the Lord,
          I say,
          the disciples of his humility execute with the offices of humility.
          For he sent those to sow the faith who would not compel but teach.
          Nor would they exercise the force of power but would bear the teaching of humility.
          In which place he thought patience should also be joined to humility,
          because he himself,
          according to the testimony of Peter in 1 Peter 2,
          when he was cursed did not curse,
          when he was struck did not strike back,
          that is to say:
          be imitators of me,
          lay aside desires for vengeance,
          bear the insolence of those striking not by returning injury but by the magnanimity of patience.
          No one should imitate in himself what he reproves in another.
          And a little further on:
          and you have elsewhere that when the apostles wished to call down fire from heaven to consume the Samaritans,
          who did not wish to receive the Lord Jesus into their city,
          he turned and rebuked them saying:
          You do not know of what spirit you are,
          the Son of man came not to destroy souls but to save them.
          And a little further on he says about Paul:
          he cast aside the rod and assumed the affection of charity.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-d1e384">
          What can be produced more clearly against these organs of Satan,
          ignorant of Christ,
          blind,
          miserable,
          opposing the doctrine of Christ and the traditions and examples of apostolic men,
          and disturbing the new world and indeed also our provinces with pestilential doctrine and destructive dissension?
          We have from Christ 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Qd1e408" source="http://scta.info/resource/mc13_37@1-6">
            what I say to you,
            I say to all.
          </quote> 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Rd1e414" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e645-Qd1e408">Mark 13.</ref> 
          But if Christ thus instructed his disciples that he commanded them to teach not to compel,
          to display and exalt humility not military pride and to carry around with him a band of robbers,
          why does Sepulveda dare to profess that the Indians must be subdued by war before the gospel is preached to them,
          so that before they understand it they may begin to hate it,
          so that they may fall by the savage hand of soldiers before they understand the evangelical truth?
          What do these men have to bring forward against the words of Christ and the fathers?
          Or did Christ teach that the Indians should be dealt with differently than other idolaters?
          Or has that command given to the apostles been revoked: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Qd1e446" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt10_12/critical/transcription@1-6">
            but entering the house,
            greet it saying:
            peace to this house
          </quote>,
          and through 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Rd1e453" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e645-Qd1e446">Luke</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Qd1e455" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc10_5@5-9">
            first say peace to this house
          </quote>?
          What is consistent with the example of Christ:
          to pierce with lances ignorant Indians before the gospel is preached to them,
          and to terrify a most innocent people with proud arrogance and warlike fury,
          driving them either to death or to flight?
          See what 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Rd1e476" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e645-Qd1e481">
            Gregory says about such preaching in Epistle 25 book 2
          </ref> 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Qd1e481">
            but this is a new and unheard-of preaching which demands faith by blows
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
          Those words which Christ commanded his disciples to say,
          "peace to this house," signify every felicity,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Rd1e494" target="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l19-d1e3112@315-327">
            Augustine in The City of God book 9 chapter 13
          </ref>,
          for it signifies that peace by which men quietly enjoy their own things,
          harming no one and receiving harm from no one.
          Therefore peace is loved by all creatures,
          even the insensible ones,
          as Augustine notes there.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-Rd1e513" target="http://scta.info/resource/KJde3s-d1e199-d1e108@1-35">
            Dionysius teaches in book 11 on Divine Names
          </ref>.
          Therefore those words "peace to this house" spoken by the apostles signified the same as if they had said:
          we have not come to plunder your things or to disturb your peace.
          Which most holy words brought the pagans to hear the announcers of the gospel.
          But we,
          before we announce the gospel,
          kill the innocent,
          and having brought war we overthrow kingdoms and cause all peace to be exiled.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e645-d1e537">
          Let Sepulveda produce one place where Christ or the holy fathers taught that pagans should be subjugated by war 
          before the gospel is preached to them.
          Sylvester the pontiff,
          a holy man,
          therefore it is most credible that he was not ignorant of how Christ instructed his own whom he sent 
          to announce the gospel.
          Did Sylvester wish to dissent from Ambrose or Chrysostom,
          whom it is probable had the Holy Spirit in interpreting the scriptures?
          Truth does not fight with truth,
          nor does the Holy Spirit speak discordant things.
          Therefore Sepulveda dreams.
          For Constantine did not wage war on the pagans at the urging of Sylvester from the sole fact that they were pagans,
          nor is there any place from which this can be gathered.
          Nor has Sepulveda,
          as he boasts,
          diligently examined all the sacred doctors.
          For if he had been versed in them,
          he would by no means bring forth these impious things.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
