<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 18 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 18 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-12-24">Dec 24, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
          
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
        
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-12-24" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
          
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="85-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Hd1e97">Chapter 18 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e99">
          Chapter 18.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e104">
          ¶ Nevertheless,
          against what was predetermined is the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e108"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Nd1e109">Damascene</name> and also of certain saints and indeed of philosophers,
            who say that knowledge of God is naturally implanted in the minds of men</ref>.
          But the first knowledge about God must be that God exists,
          therefore that God exists is self-evident.
          Likewise the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e122" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e125">Apostle to the Romans 1</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e125" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom1_21@1-8">because when they had known God,
            they did not glorify him as God</quote>,
          et cetera.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e133">
          ¶ To which it must be said:
          It is true that a common knowledge of God is naturally implanted in the minds of men.
          But that knowledge is very confused and universal and only shows that there is some orderer of the things which we see running according to a certain order.
          But who or what kind,
          or whether there is one or many,
          is not immediately obtained by this common consideration.
          But this is not to know simply that God exists.
          Just as when we see a man moving and performing other works,
          we perceive there to be in him a certain cause of these operations which is not present in other things,
          and we call this cause soul,
          not yet knowing what the soul is,
          whether it is a body,
          or how it effects the aforesaid operations.
          Or just as to know someone coming is not to know 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Nd1e174">Peter</name>,
          although it is 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Nd1e178">Peter</name> who is coming.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e181">
          And therefore that proposition,
          that God exists,
          is not self-evident to us,
          but needs to be demonstrated through things which are better known to us,
          namely through effects.
          But the authority of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Nd1e191">Damascene</name> is understood that knowledge of God is naturally implanted in us according to his likeness and not according to what he is in his nature,
          just as it is also said that all things desire God,
          not indeed himself as he is considered in his nature,
          but in his likeness,
          because nothing is desired except insofar as it has a likeness to him.
          And also nothing is known.
          See 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e211" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e56-d1e300">Saint Thomas 1 part,
            q. 2, a. 1, c</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e216" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l1d3q2-Dd1e101">1 Sentences distinction 3,
            q. 1, a 2</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e221" target="http://scta.info/resource/v8naTA-d1e2018">book 3, c. 38,
            against the gentiles</ref>.
          
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e228">
          ¶ To the authority of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Nd1e230">blessed Paul</name> it is said that he speaks of the philosophers who,
          having knowledge of God,
          did not use it for good but became foolish.
          For they knew that God is supereminent over all things.
          And thus they should have given glory and honor which is owed to the superexcellent,
          and thus when they had known God,
          they did not glorify him as God,
          either because they did not render due worship to him or because they imposed a limit on his power and knowledge.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e257">
          ¶ They also knew God as the cause of all good things.
          Whence thanksgiving was owed to him in all things,
          which however they did not give to God,
          but rather ascribed their good things to their own ingenuity and power.
          Whence the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e284"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Nd1e285" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e287">Apostle</name></ref> adds:
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e287" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom1_21@9-22 http://scta.info/resource/rom1_22@1-8">but gave thanks.
            Professing themselves to be wise,
            they became fools</quote>,
          et cetera.
          These things do not apply to all in common.
          And therefore the Apostle does not speak about them,
          et cetera.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e300">
          ¶ Secondly,
          the minor of the principal argument is proved principally,
          namely that such negative unbelievers are invincibly ignorant,
          et cetera,
          by the opinion of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Nd1e308">Saint Augustine</name> and 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Nd1e313">Saint Thomas</name> who say that those are excused from the sin of unbelief who have never heard anything about the faith,
          according to that of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e320" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e323">John 15</ref>.
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e323" source="http://scta.info/resource/io15_22@1-10">If I had not come and spoken to them,
            they would not have sin</quote>,
          namely of unbelief.
          Thus 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e337" target="http://scta.info/resource/iuy75t-d1e769-d1e128@161-168">Augustine explains</ref> there,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e341" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1324-d1e297">Saint Thomas 2a 2ae:
            q. 10, a. 1</ref>.
          and that of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e346" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e351">Romans 10</ref>.
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e351" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom10_14@9-19">How shall they believe in him of whom they have not heard?
            How shall they hear without a preacher?</quote>
          Whence such unbelievers are not damned for lack of faith which was never preached to them,
          but for other sins which cannot be remitted to them without faith.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e366">
          ¶ From these things it follows that since this proposition,
          God is one,
          is undoubtedly of the faith,
          and those worshiping idols cannot be informed about their error and the truth of the faith either by themselves or by their ancestors,
          they have invincible ignorance about the existence and especially the unity of God,
          just as they suffer it not knowing Christ to be the son of God and redeemer of the world,
          and thus about other supernatural things,
          until the faith has been fully and effectively preached to them.
          This is proved because since it is not implanted in the nature of things that there is one true God,
          and even if they contend that there is a god,
          nevertheless they could believe that the true God is the one whom their ancestors worshiped,
          and thus any province could claim that the true God exists among them.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e408">
          Nor would they be bound to believe that the true God is among the Christians rather than among other nations.
          Whence just as they could legitimately suppose that the god or gods whom other nations worship are not true gods or God,
          so also concerning the God of the Christians,
          since nothing in the nature of things would cause otherwise,
          unless it were made known by the workings of miracles.
          Therefore negative unbelievers worshiping idols labor under invincible ignorance.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e432">
          ¶ And if it be objected that to worship stones as god is against natural reason and thus indicated in the nature of things,
          and therefore they cannot be invincibly ignorant or excused,
          it is answered that the common and final intention of those who worship idols is not to worship stones,
          but in them,
          as in certain divine powers,
          to venerate through religion that orderer of the world,
          whoever he may be,
          naturally knowing that because of the defects which they sense in themselves they need to be helped and directed by him,
          and therefore through religious worship or rather superstitious worship,
          which consists principally in sacrifices,
          they strove to conciliate him to themselves.
          On this see 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e471" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1711-d1e255@4-132">Saint Thomas 2a, 2ae,
            q. 85 ar. 1</ref>.
          
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e478">
          ¶ Thus says 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e480" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e485">Jerome on Psalm 95</ref>:
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e485">So therefore both we and all the human race naturally understand God.
            For there are no nations which do not naturally understand their creator.
            For although they venerate stones and wood,
            nevertheless they understand that there is something greater than themselves,
            and in their error they show that they have wisdom,
            that is,
            there is no nation which does not naturally understand God.
            Finally the pagans worship idols,
            that is,
            they venerate stones and wood.
            And if perhaps they have made a quarrel and if some oath has come among them,
            they do not say these stones see,
            the wood sees,
            but God sees and God hears.</quote>
          Thus Jerome.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e519">
          A certain idolater,
          
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e521" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e530">a Roman named Maximus,
            writing in a certain letter to Augustine</ref>,
          seems to show that he contended this very thing.
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e530">Indeed," he says,
            "that there is one God without beginning,
            without offspring of nature,
            or a great and magnificent father,
            who so insane,
            so mentally captive would deny is most certain?
            His powers diffused through the work of the world we invoke by many names,
            since we all clearly are ignorant of his proper name.
            For God is a name common to all religions.
            Thus it happens that while we pursue his,
            as it were,
            certain members piecemeal with various supplications,
            we indeed seem to worship the whole</quote>,
          et cetera.
          Thus he.
          In 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e560">the letter which is numbered 43 among Augustine's letters</ref>.
          From which it appears that the intention of those worshiping idols tends principally toward the true God,
          whoever he may be,
          to be worshiped and adored.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e573">
          ¶ We said above 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e577">until the faith has been sufficiently and fully preached to them</quote>,
          et cetera,
          because unless the faith has been of such a kind,
          fully proposed and explained to negative unbelievers,
          and through suitable ministers to whom anyone prudent ought rightly and reasonably to give faith because of the splendor of their life,
          they are not bound to believe.
          For they can say not absurdly what the Jews from the beginning of the preaching of Christ and the Gentiles afterward everywhere used to allege:
          What is this teaching?
          What is this new religion which overthrows totally what was approved by the whole world before and for so many centuries?
          That God is three and one,
          and God himself crucified.
          How can these things be?
          And because of this novelty they can reasonably doubt about the teaching,
          hold it suspect,
          and refuse to hear the faith and not admit the preachers,
          as they rather consider deceivers than messengers of true religion.
          Otherwise they would be most fickle of heart 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e628" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e633">according to that of Ecclesiasticus</ref>
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e633" source="http://scta.info/resource/sir19_4@1-5">he who believes quickly is light of heart.</quote>
          
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e637">
          And the reason for these things is because such truths surpass every faculty of nature.
          Therefore no one is bound to believe them unless by this manner in which it becomes possible for him,
          which is that he has sufficient testimonies for believing,
          namely either that he sees some miracle specially done for the confirmation of such teaching,
          or is moved to believe by efficacious reasons,
          or some other thing which supplies the place of a miracle.
          One of which is sufficiently efficacious,
          namely the blameless and Christian life of the preachers,
          by which the mysteries of faith are rendered credible to the hearers,
          that is,
          they see that they are to be believed.
          For no one would believe unless he saw that they were to be believed,
          either because of the evidence of signs or because of something else of this kind,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e673" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1277-d1e934@5-60">Saint Thomas 2a 2ae,
            q. 1, a. 4, ad 2</ref>;
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Rd1e679">quodlib. 2, ar. 6</ref>.
          
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e682">
          ¶ But truly because today miracles are not done,
          therefore to make the things of faith credible to unbelievers,
          the life of Christians shining with works of virtue needs to be an example to them.
          Whence Chrysostom:
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e695">There would be no need for words if our life shone with the light of holiness.
            There would be no need for teachers if we displayed upright acts of virtue.
            Surely no Gentile would exist if we Christians took care to be as we ought.
            If we obeyed God's commands and decrees,
            if when cursed we blessed,
            if for evils we returned good things,
            no one would be so savage a beast that he would not immediately hasten to the worship of true religion if he saw these things done by all.</quote>
          And below:
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e720">But if indeed they see us also seeking the same things with them,
            desiring the same things,
            seeking the ambition of honor and private advantage,
            how will they be able to admire the Christian religion?
            Whence therefore will they be able to believe?
            Perhaps from signs?
            But these are not done now?
            Or indeed from holiness of life?
            But that has clearly perished.
            Now truly because of charity?
            But never is any trace of it perceived.
            Wherefore we shall indeed give account not only for our sins but also for others' harm of which we ourselves are the cause.</quote>
          Thus Chrysostom.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-d1e750">
          And elsewhere the same Chrysostom:
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e276-Qd1e753">For many of them (namely of the unbelievers),
            when they see some of ours called Christians in word and name indeed,
            but nevertheless like themselves plundering,
            being desirous of money,
            envying,
            plotting,
            deceiving deceitfully and doing all other things,
            will no longer hear us,
            nor if our admonitions are reasonable,
            but they think all our things are deceptions and all are subject to the same crimes.
            Consider,
            I beseech,
            how great punishments they are worthy of,
            since indeed they heap up inextinguishable fire not only for themselves but are also authors to others that they remain in error,
            and they block ears lest they learn virtue,
            and they are the cause that even students of virtues are accused and reproved (and what is more serious than all)
            through them the Lord is blasphemed.
            Do you see how great the destruction of malice?
            Do you see how they make themselves liable to no ordinary punishments who pursue evil?
            But they will also pay most grave penalties for all things:
            not only for their own perdition,
            but also for the scandal of those in error and for the abuse of the just and for blasphemy against God</quote>,
          et cetera.
          All these things from Chrysostom.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>