<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 47 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 47 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2024-08-09">August 09, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
          </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
      url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-08-09" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="204-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Hd1e97">Chapter 47 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-d1e100">
          CHAPTER 47
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-d1e99">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Again,
          that Sylvester,
          a holy man,
          did not persuade Constantine to bring pagans to Christ by war.
          It was proved seventhly because preparing kingdoms by war is for tyrants and robbers,
          not for Christians:
          indeed not even for prudent men.
          For nothing violent is lasting:
          and to subjugate a kingdom by force is tyrannical,
          hateful and abominable,
          according to the Philosopher in the third book of the Politics and the eighth of the Ethics.
          A kingdom truly acquired by duties,
          gentleness,
          virtue and persuasion,
          not violently,
          is lovable and most pleasing to all peoples,
          and enduring for many ages:
          according to that saying of Cicero in the Philippics:
          "There is no greater safeguard," he says,
          "of armed men than the love and goodwill of citizens:
          with which a ruler ought to be fortified,
          not with arms" —
          these are his words.
          Of the same opinion was Gaius Sallustius.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-d1e142">
          And of this kind is the kingdom of Christ according to that saying of the prophet Zechariah,
          chapter 9,
          and Matthew 22:
          "Behold your king comes to you meek."
          And that of Isaiah chapter 42:
          "He will not cry out nor show partiality nor will his voice be heard outside:
          the crushed reed" (which Jerome interprets as the Jews) "he will not break:
          and the smoking flax" (that is the pagans) "he will not extinguish."
          These words the evangelists interpret concerning the apprehension and possession of the 
          kingdom of Christ:
          as appears in Matthew 12.
          And from Isaiah chapter 2:
          "It will be in the last days," he says,
          "the mountain prepared,
          that is Christ;
          (a mountain I say) of the house of the Lord,
          that is the Catholic Church,
          and all nations will flow to him:
          and many peoples will go and will say: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Qd1e183">'Come,
          let us ascend to the mountain of the Lord and to the house of the God of Jacob:
          and he will teach us his ways and we will walk in his paths.'
          </quote>
          This is that mountain which grew from a stone cut from a mountain and which destroyed 
          the statue (that is) all empires,
          and grew until becoming a great mountain it occupied the world,
          according to the words of Daniel chapter 2.
          Note those words of Isaiah:
          "And all nations will flow to him and many peoples will go:
          and they will say 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Qd1e207">'Come'
          </quote>,
          etc.
          These words exclude all force,
          all terror,
          and signify a spontaneous willingness to come to the sheepfold of Christ:
          thus our wars which we excuse under the pretext of overthrowing idolatry:
          Isaiah condemns a little below with these words:
          "They will beat their swords into plowshares:
          and their spears into pruning hooks:
          nation will not lift up sword against nation nor will they train any more for war," etc.
          These signify:
          that the Christian people will not bring anyone to the faith by swords or spears or 
          inflicted war:
          which the gloss teaches upon these same words.
          But Christ being born,
          who is our peace,
          who made both one,
          in whose nativity the angels sang "Glory to God in the highest,
          and peace to men of good will":
          all wars ceased,
          etc. —
          this is the gloss.
          And in this discourse the gloss interprets that covenant:
          which Judas Maccabeus made with the Romans:
          the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Rd1e258">gloss on 1 Maccabees chapter 8</ref>
          says thus:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Qd1e262" source="http://scta.info/resource/gom-Imac8-d1e89@4-31">
          "What is this that Judas,
          who sends legates to the Romans to establish friendship and alliance with them:
          signifies our redeemer offering the gospel of peace to the gentiles through his preachers 
          and calling them to his faith."
          </quote>
          And below: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Qd1e279" source="http://scta.info/resource/gom-Imac8-d1e89@156-185">
          "And what is it that Judas sent two legates for the sake of making peace to the Romans:
          except that our redeemer,
          for calling the gentiles to faith and fellowship of peace,
          sent two testaments into the world,"
          </quote>
          and again the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Rd1e293">gloss explaining chapter 12</ref>,
          where it is narrated that Jonathan,
          brother of Judas Maccabeus,
          after his brother's death renewed the covenant he had made with the Romans,
          the gloss says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Qd1e301" source="http://scta.info/resource/gom-Imac12-d1e89@4-132">
          "That Jonathan sends legates to the Romans and to the Spartans and to other places:
          so that he may renew the peace with them which his brother Judas first entered into 
          willingly with them:
          demonstrates that great solicitude should be for holy preachers:
          that the peace which Christ offered in the world,
          Christians should strive with all zeal to renew and preserve everywhere:
          because the very Son of God,
          who came to earth to pacify in his flesh things heavenly and earthly:
          immediately at the rising of his nativity wished to be sung by angels 
          'Glory to God in the highest and on earth peace to men of good will.'
          This peace indeed the mediator of God and men,
          now made man,
          commended to his disciples saying: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Qd1e338" source="http://scta.info/resource/io14_27@1-7">
          'Have peace among yourselves,
          peace I command you,
          my peace I leave you.'
          </quote>
          Also by peace and concord the entire body of Christ is united:
          ruled and established"
          </quote>
          etc. —
          this is the ordinary gloss.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-d1e352">
          Note that word "is united" which signifies to join together diverse and most remote peoples,
          infected with diverse rites and errors:
          to be inserted into the body of Christ (namely) the Church by peace.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-d1e365">
          Which is also proved by reason:
          since the kingdom of Christ is spiritual.
          For Christ reigns in the souls of the faithful endowed with charity,
          faith and hope,
          according to Jerome on the last chapter of Matthew.
          But these three virtues are virtues of the soul in which God reigns,
          according to that saying in Luke chapter 17:
          "The kingdom of God is within you."
          But the human soul cannot be coerced,
          as was shown before.
          Therefore,
          so that Christ may truly reign in the souls of pagans,
          they are not to be forced to the faith by war:
          but by duties,
          blandishments and Christian charity they are to be attracted and led to the sheepfold 
          of Christ.
          To bring to the faith by slaughters and terrors is Mohammedan.
          For Mohammed said he was sent in the terror of the sword and the force of arms,
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Rd1e404">
          Vincent in the Mirror of History,
          book 23,
          chapter 49
          </ref>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Rd1e409">
          Saint Thomas in book 1 Against the Gentiles chapter 6
          </ref>.
          And Vincent in chapter 42 of that work says:
          "Consider if such expeditions should pertain to the prophet of God:
          in which nothing else was done except fraud and violence and effusion of human blood,
          and whatever utterly robbers and ambushers of roads do."
          And in the following chapter 45:
          "Whose operation or meditation," he says,
          "was nothing else than to kill men:
          to seize others' property,
          to perpetrate incests and adulteries," etc. —
          these are Vincent's words.
          What then,
          Sepúlveda,
          do you wish that the law of Christ be propagated not by Christian but by Mohammedan 
          reasoning?
          Do you wish the name of Christ adorable to angels to be blasphemed by pagans?
          Do you wish the ocean of all evils (namely) war to be thrust upon pagans in place of 
          the gentleness of Christ which we ought to teach?
          What have the proclaimers of the gospel to do with armed robbers mixing all things 
          with flames and sword?
          What does the institution of Christ have in common with these mad ravings of men?
          Indeed I think Sepúlveda wrote that little book hastily and without sufficiently 
          weighing the matters and circumstances:
          and if there are any —
          I know not whether more impious or foolish —
          who follow his authority,
          let them fear God the avenger of perverse machinations:
          and let them hear Christ and the sacred doctors of the Church,
          not Sepúlveda:
          who will readily yield to Christ,
          Ambrose,
          Augustine and Chrysostom.
          Sepúlveda says he does not wish the Indians to be baptized unwillingly nor forced to 
          the faith.
          What greater compulsion can there be than that which is done by an armed phalanx 
          discharging muskets and bombards,
          which even by horrific thunder,
          even if nothing else were added,
          can dismay anyone,
          however strong,
          especially one unaccustomed and ignorant of the art.
          If vessels tremble from bombards,
          earth quakes,
          heaven is hidden by blind darkness,
          old men are killed,
          youths,
          women,
          houses are plundered and all things resound with the fury of war:
          shall we not truly say these are forced to the faith?
          Is this not a just fear?
          What will the Indians refuse when affected in these ways?
          Or what freedom of mind is left here for receiving the faith of Christ from the heart 
          so that they may persevere?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-d1e537">
          I wish the reader to consider:
          what will the Indians think of our religion which these most impious tyrants boast to 
          teach,
          with the Indians to be subjugated by slaughters and force of war before the gospel is 
          preached to them?
          When I speak of force of war,
          I speak of the sum of all evils.
          Then what does it profit to break idols if the Indians,
          treated in these ways,
          keep them,
          secretly adore them in their hearts?
          Hear what Saint Augustine says about those who violently break idols,
          in the sermon On the Words of the Lord,
          sermon 6 on the centurion's boy:
          "Many pagans have these abominations on their estates:
          do we approach and break them?"
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-d1e572">
          "For first we act so that we may break the idols from their hearts."
          And a little later,
          speaking about those who violently break idols,
          he says:
          "It is characteristic of wicked men,
          furious circumcellions," etc.
          Which passage of Augustine we left explained more fully above in chapter 7.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-d1e588">
          With these agrees what is said about receiving the faith:
          that all direct or indirect force should be absent,
          as is prohibited in c. maiores de baptismo,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Rd1e596">45 distinctio c. qui sincera</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Rd1e599">c. de iudaeis</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e658-Rd1e602">23, q. 5, c. ad fidem</ref>
          and the doctors teach there and elsewhere.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>