<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 48 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 48 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-31">July 31, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-31" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="207-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Hd1e97">Chapter 48 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e99">
          CHAPTER 48
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e104">
          This truth is further corroborated: 
          for the Church not only had temporal power in the time of Sylvester, 
          but obtained greater strength in the time of Pope Gregory, 
          in whose age Maurice and Phocas, 
          pious men for some time and the greatest Caesars, 
          possessed the Roman empire. 
          Nevertheless,
          Gregory never dealt with them so that they might wage war against the pagans 
          who were not doing injury to the Church, 
          even if Maurice was the spiritual godfather of Pope Gregory, 
          and therefore it is probable that there was a not uncommon friendship between them. 
          This is clear first because if Saint Gregory had incited them to such a war, 
          the matter would have been worthy of memory and would be recounted by the writers of that time. 
          <pb ed="#P" n="207-v"/>
          Secondly, 
          because Gregory, 
          in order to lead the English people to the faith, 
          by no means sent armed forces against them, 
          but a certain monk Augustine and forty pious monks distinguished by Christian integrity, 
          who before they entered the city of England, 
          beseeched the Lord with these words: 
          "O Lord, 
          who created and redeemed these souls, 
          deign to take away Your anger from them, 
          so that with us together mercy and clemency may enter to them." 
          Thus it is read in the life of blessed Gregory written by Paul the Deacon and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e171">
          the history of the Lombards, 
          book 3, chapter 12</ref>.
          And concerning this prayer and the preaching of those holy monks,
          the venerable Bede writes at length in the history which he wrote concerning the peoples of that island. 
          Those holy monks proceeded, 
          and having performed many miracles which led Gregory himself into admiration, 
          as he himself wrote to Eulogius, 
          Bishop of Alexandria, 
          in book [gap], 
          letter [gap], 
          and to Augustine himself in book 9, 
          letter 58.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e201">
          Do you see that the Church, 
          even in the time when it flourished with the greatest strength, 
          used not material but spiritual arms in the preaching of the gospel, 
          in no way departing from the example and instruction of its teacher? 
          Again, 
          in the days of that same blessed Gregory, 
          before he was assumed to the supreme pontificate, 
          there were popes and emperors who were most Christian men, 
          namely Pope John III 
          <pb ed="#P" n="208-r"/>
          and Benedict I and Pelagius II, 
          Roman pontiffs; 
          nevertheless they did not induce Justin the Greater and Maurice, 
          who were Roman caesars in their age, 
          to overthrow idolatry by war. 
          Then that most holy man Gregory himself, 
          in homily 28 on the gospels, 
          expounds those words of Christ "compel them to enter," 
          written in the parable of the wedding feast, 
          concerning the compulsion which is made by holy admonitions and examples of morals and Christian life 
          and by the most efficacious force of the divine word.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e247">
          And lest the error of these men be confounded by the doctrine of the sacred doctors alone, 
          let there be added to the aforementioned exposition of the saints that which the professors of canon law understood, 
          especially Innocent in c. maiores de baptismo, 
          who speaks with these words: 
          "and thus no one is to be compelled to become a Christian." 
          Nor does it stand in the way that it is said to the servant that he compels those invited to the wedding to enter 
          Luke 14 
          and 23 q. 4, c. displicet, 
          because it is understood concerning compulsion made by the insistence of reason, 
          not by the severity of the material sword or by temporal violence 45 distinctio, c. de iudaeis, 
          because the execution of such a sword is forbidden to that servant, 
          that is to the order of preachers or the apostles in the person of Peter by the Lord 23 q. 1 c. Item cum Petro. 
          These are the words of Innocent.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e287">
          Therefore, 
          the servant who invites to the wedding, 
          that is, 
          the preacher of the gospel, 
          should not be armed with bombards like a wolf among sheep to kill and plunder, 
          <pb ed="#P" n="208-v"/>
          but instructed with holy morals and the word of God, 
          he ought to announce the gospel, 
          exposing his life to death for the extension of the gospel and the glory of Christ. 
          For then the preaching of the gospel will be efficacious when preachers undergo death, 
          not when they have killed others and affected them with death, 
          according to Chrysostom on Matthew chapter 22, 
          homily 41 in the imperfect work.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e322">
          The prophets and apostles, 
          in announcing the gospel, 
          were despoiled of life; 
          Christ also died for us all. 
          Nor did the fruit of preaching appear before the death of Christ and the apostles. 
          For just as no one eats the entrails of a living animal, 
          so no one received the words of the living prophets and apostles, 
          but after their death. 
          Finally, 
          just as the entrails of the lamb, 
          so men did not eat the words of Christ until after he was slain. 
          For after his death, 
          the gospels were preached and believed, 
          and in them men are daily nourished. 
          So also the entrails of his prophets and apostles. 
          These are from Chrysostom.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e355">
          Which Christ himself, 
          the eternal truth, 
          wished to signify to us in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e362" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e671-Qd1e364">John 12</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Qd1e364" source="http://scta.info/resource/io12_24@5-12 http://scta.info/resource/io12_25@1-10">
          "Unless a grain of wheat falling into the earth dies, 
          it remains alone; 
          but if it dies, 
          it brings forth much fruit."</quote>
          But he speaks there of the preaching and conversion of the gentiles, 
          according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e376">
          Saint Thomas in the third part, 
          question 42, 
          article 1 in the body</ref>. 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e382">Saint Augustine in his tract on John</ref>, 
          expounding those words of Christ, 
          says: 
          he said he was the grain to be mortified in the unbelief of the Jews 
          <pb ed="#P" n="209-r"/>
          and to be multiplied in the faith of all peoples. 
          For that very death illuminated the teaching of the holy apostles 
          and added faith to their words. 
          Innocent also infers from these things: 
          therefore it appears that war is not to be declared against the Saracens so that they become Christians. 
          These are his words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e401">
          Therefore, 
          neither is war to be undertaken as a means for preparing the minds of infidels or for removing idolatry. 
          The gospel, 
          therefore, 
          is propagated not by lances but by the word of God and the Christian life, 
          but by the insistence of reason, 
          as Innocent has stated. 
          Which Saint Gregory also teaches in book 11, 
          letter 15, 
          to Pascasius, 
          Bishop of Naples, 
          with these words: 
          "Therefore it must be done that rather, 
          provoked by reason and gentleness, 
          they may wish to follow us, 
          not flee." 
          These are his words. 
          Gregory speaks there about the Jews. 
          But if the Jews, 
          who are servants of the Church and prepared to serve, 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e440" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q8-d1e273">
          c. dispar 23 q. 8</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e445" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t6-d1e301">
          c. etsi iudaeos: de iudaeis</ref>, 
          are to be led to the faith by gentleness and doctrine, 
          how much more must the same be taught concerning the pagans, 
          who have been instructed by no words of God, 
          and are not bound to depart from their own religion or princes 
          before they see what is better.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e443">
          Therefore, 
          to announce the gospel with armed forces is utterly alien to the doctrine of Christ, 
          whose whole life and doctrine breathes gentleness and charity. 
          The Lord sent his own to preach the gospel instructed with most pious words: 
          <pb ed="#P" n="209-v"/>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Qd1e476" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt10_12@1-6">
          "Entering a house,
          he says, 
          "salute it,"</quote> 
          and say first, 
          peace to this house. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Qd1e483" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt10_16@1-6">
          "Behold, 
          I send you as sheep"</quote>; 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Qd1e488" source="http://scta.info/resource/io10_10@11-18">
          "I came that they might have life and have it more abundantly"</quote>; 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Qd1e496" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt11_29@7-15">
          "Learn from me, 
          for I am gentle and humble in heart"</quote>. 
          But armed forces are suitable to Mohammed the false prophet, 
          who said that he was in the terror of the sword, 
          as has been stated above. 
          The Indians, 
          since they have a probable reason for following the institutions of their ancestors, 
          approved for so many centuries, 
          supported by the authority of so many princes, 
          priests, 
          and learned men among them, 
          are not bound to depart from it at the exhortation of robbers, 
          surpassing all Turks and plunderers in savagery and ferocity. 
          For who would believe that such tyrants are messengers of the true God? 
          Who by their depraved morals defame the gospel and undermine the cause of Christ. 
          Those things please human minds and are inserted into hearts as consonant with reason 
          which are taught by good and trustworthy men. 
          Who, 
          if they have done sensible works conformable to reason—
          for instance, 
          if they have shown charity, 
          if gentleness, 
          if modesty—
          will please all, 
          and faith will be given to their words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e525">
          Which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e529">
          Scotus wisely confirms in the fourth book of the Sentences, 
          distinction 3, 
          question 4</ref>, 
          saying: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Qd1e562">
          "that no one is bound to any positive precept, 
          even divine, 
          unless it be promulgated to him by someone suitable and authentic, 
          <pb ed="#P" n="210-r"/>
          or by a truthful form and testimony of good men to whom anyone ought reasonably to believe,"</quote> 
          etc. 
          These are his words. 
          Concerning which matter 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e547" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAcCaj-d1e1277-d1e1688">
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Nd1e548">Cajetan</name> 
          also learnedly discourses in 2 2ae, 
          question 1, 
          article 4, 
          in the response to the second objection</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e556">
          But what faith will be given to the Spaniards, 
          rapacious, 
          savage, 
          and ferocious men, 
          who slaughter the unarmed and harmless peoples of the Indians and plunder them with unheard-of avarice? 
          Hence it follows that the Indians, 
          seeing their impious works, 
          do not sin nor are they worthy of punishment if they do not receive the gospel; 
          nor would any people be culpable for not having received the faith of Christ, 
          if the apostles, 
          per impossibile, 
          had been endowed with the morals with which the Spaniards are endowed. 
          Concerning this we have the word of the Lord in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Rd1e631">John 15</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-Qd1e633">
          "If I had not done among them the works which no one else did, 
          they would not have sin."</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e671-d1e605">
          From what has been so extensively deduced, 
          therefore, 
          it clearly appears what or what kind is the literal sense which Christ understood in the aforementioned parable 
          "Compel them to enter": 
          namely, 
          that the compulsion which must be understood there concerning unbelievers who have never heard the faith 
          is that which is done by the insistence and human persuasion of reason, 
          or by spiritual and interior means through the ministry of angels. 
          And consequently it is false and impious to assert that Christ bound us by precept through that parable 
          <pb ed="#P" n="210-v"/>
          that war against peaceful infidels should precede the preaching of the gospel 
          when the Church had great strength, 
          as the distinguished doctor Sepulveda has not blushed to put forth in a new doctrine.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>