<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 5 [English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
            <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
            <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
            <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
            <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 5 [English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-08-05">August 6, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-08-06" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="28-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Hd1e97">Chapter 5 [English Translation]</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e99">
          Chapter 5
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e104">
          ¶ There is a fourth species of barbarians,
          comprehending all who do not acknowledge Christ.
          For every nation,
          however civilized,
          every man,
          however philosophical,
          is subject to the greatest barbarisms of vice,
          if he has not been imbued with the mysteries of Christian philosophy.
          Moreover,
          he cannot be purged of these vices except by the sacraments and virtue of the Christian law,
          which alone is
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e125" source="http://scta.info/resource/ps18_8">
            the law without blemish,
          </quote>
          converting souls,
          freeing and cleansing the hearts of men from every vice and superstition of idolatry,
          from which arises the fountain of all evils that render life miserable and unhappy both privately and publicly,
          according to that saying from
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e139">Wisdom 14</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e141" source="http://scta.info/resource/sap14_12@1-12">
            For the beginning of fornication is the seeking out of idols,
            and the invention of them is the corruption of life.
          </quote>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e149">
          The Christian faith procures the grace of the Holy Spirit,
          which wipes away all that is depraved,
          unclean,
          and foolish from human hearts.
          This manifestly appeared in the Roman people,
          praised at that time by the name of political prudence and wisdom,
          which desired to give laws at its pleasure to the other nations of the world.
          For how many wicked vices and abominations this people was subject to,
          especially in those most shameful games and abominable sacrifices,
          such as in the circus and theatrical games,
          and in the most obscene sacrifices of Priapus and Bacchus,
          where all things were so indecent,
          deformed,
          and alien to right reason that they left all nations far behind in mental stupor and barbarity.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e185">
          This was clearly and extensively taught by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e189">
            Saint Augustine from book 2 up to book 7 of the City of God,
          </ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e195">
            Saint Cyprian in treatise 4 against Demetrianus,
            the idolater and persecutor of Christians,
          </ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e200">
            Lactantius in book 1,
            chapter 2 of the Divine Institutes,
          </ref>
          discoursing on the religion of the Romans and Greeks who wished to seem to excel the other nations of the world in wisdom.
          He writes that they were accustomed to prostitute their children in gymnasiums so that anyone might use them wickedly at pleasure.
          To worship and render service to their gods.
          Moreover,
          he adds these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e225">
            What wonder if from this people all shameful deeds flowed,
            among whom the very vices are religious,
            those which are not only not avoided but even worshiped?
          </quote>
          Thus he writes.
          These are they who called all nations except themselves barbarians,
          although no wild barbarians could do anything more absurd or stupid.
          They excelled perhaps in keenness of judgment and cleverness of wit,
          so that,
          presenting themselves as tyrants to the human race,
          they might subjugate foreign provinces with great slaughters.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e249">
          But that the Greeks and Romans abstained from these horrendous crimes and most foul vices,
          to whom should this be attributed if not to the splendor of the Gospel,
          which,
          spread throughout all the nations of the world,
          dazzled even the eyes of that ambitious people?
          Since,
          therefore,
          through the foul and corrupt morals and other abominations of unbelievers,
          which arise especially from superstitious opinions about divine matters,
          and those things which follow from them,
          they are made like brute beasts,
          according to blessed
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e271">
            Paul in Romans 1,
          </ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e276">
            Thomas there in lecture 7 and in 2a 2ae q. 94 a. 3 ad 3um,
          </ref>
          certainly whoever has not been initiated into Christian mysteries is judged barbarous and wretched,
          and thus behold the fourth species of barbarians is demonstrated.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e289">
          The peoples of the Turks and Arabs are said to be politically organized,
          but how they should be decorated with this honorable name,
          since the nation is unbridled toward every license of the flesh,
          effeminate with luxury,
          among whom especially the Turks,
          impure and horrendous vices are not deemed worthy of punishment.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e305">
          ¶ Finally,
          neither the Greeks nor the Romans nor the Turks nor the Moors should be said to employ justice,
          for neither prudence nor justice can be found in a republic that does not acknowledge Christ,
          as
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e315" target="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l2-d1e271@954-1016">
            Augustine proves in the City of God book 2 chapter 21,
          </ref>
          and it is read among the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e321" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q1-d1e553">
            papal decrees at dist. 24 q. 1 c. ubi sana,
          </ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e326" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c33q3d2-d1e323">
            c. non est de penitentia dist. 2.
          </ref>
          And thus he asserts,
          speaking of the Roman republic in that work
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e333" target="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l19-d1e3156@97-241">
            the City of God book 19 chapter 21,
          </ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e340">
            Lactantius happily proves the same in book 1 chapter 20 of the Institutes.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e346">
          Since,
          therefore,
          those who are devoid of Christian truth,
          however much they are skilled in political prudence,
          are overwhelmed by vices and crimes and in many things depart from reason,
          certainly all who do not worship Christ,
          either because they have not heard His words even by report,
          or because,
          having heard them,
          they do not receive them,
          are truly barbarians,
          which appears in the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e363" target="http://scta.info/resource/act28_4">
            Acts of the Apostles chapter 28,
          </ref>
          where,
          after it is narrated that
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Nd1e368">Paul the Apostle,</name>
            having been cast ashore by shipwreck at Mitylene,
            it adds:
            <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e373">
              the barbarians showed us no little kindness.
            </quote>
            Thus
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Nd1e380">Saint Luke.</name>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e383">
          Mitylene is a port of the island of Lesbos,
          which gave us the lyric poets Alcaeus and Sappho,
          and Pittacus surnamed the Mytilenean,
          who was one of the seven sages of Greece,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e393">
            and Theophrastus,
            disciple of Aristotle,
            according to Aulus Gellius.
          </ref>
          By which name it is celebrated by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e406">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Nd1e407">Horace:</name>
          </ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e409">
            Others will praise (he says) famous Rhodes or Mitylene.
          </quote>
          Nevertheless,
          it is called by the Apostle a barbarous people,
          not indeed because they were stupid or wild,
          but because they did not acknowledge Christ,
          although
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e431">Lyranus therefore</ref>
          writes that they were called barbarians because they knew neither Hebrew nor Greek nor Latin.
          Thus
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e437">
            Saint Jerome in his Epistle to Evander or Eugenius the Bishop
          </ref>
          says,
          and it is also contained in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e447" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d93-d1e470">
            the decrees dist. 93 c. legimus,
          </ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e450" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c32q7-d1e283">
            32 q. c. offerebat,
          </ref>
          there among barbarous peoples:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e455">
            For also Africa,
            and the Persians,
            and the East,
            and India,
            and all barbarous nations adore one Christ,
            observe one rule of truth.
          </quote>
          The same
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e469">
            Jerome to Heliodorus and in the epistle to Leta in the same volume page 68.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e475">
          The laws and decrees speak generally,
          as
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e481" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e486">
            7 q. 1 c. temporis qualitas,
          </ref>
          there:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e486" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c7q1-d1e786@27-31">
            they can more easily avoid barbarous danger,
            for he speaks there of the Turks or Saracens,
          </quote>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e493" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e499">
            23 q. 2 c. sex differentiae,
          </ref>
          there:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e499" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q3-d1e123@19-20">
            some of the barbarians,
          </quote>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e502" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q3-d1e181">
            c. fortitudo which protects in war from barbarians.
          </ref>
          Also in the laws
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e509">
            cod. de officio prefecti cretorio africae l. 1,
          </ref>
          there
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e511">
            they were subjugated most harshly under the barbarous yoke,
          </quote>
          and he was speaking of the Vandals who by their tyranny had usurped the entire province of Africa.
          And
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e523">
            ff. de re militari l. non omnes § a barbaris remissus miles,
          </ref>
          and in the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e528">proem of the Institutes,</ref>
          there
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e531">
            and indeed the other labors of the barbarous people brought under our yoke are known.
          </quote>
          Where the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e537">gloss</ref>
          says
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e540">
            barbarians are those who are outside the universal boundaries of the Roman empire,
            that is,
            the Church,
          </quote>
          as if outside it there is no empire,
          as will be evident below in the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e547">chapter.</ref>
          And the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e552">gloss</ref>
          adds
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e555">especially enemies.</quote>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e559">
          ¶ Against these barbarians,
          however,
          who are enemies of the Church,
          the Church prays on Good Friday with these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e565">
            Let us pray for the most Christian emperor that God our Lord may make all barbarous nations subject to him for our perpetual peace.
            And below:
            May the barbarous peoples who trust in their own ferocity be subdued by the power of your right hand.
          </quote>
          But concerning barbarians who do not molest the Christian people,
          the Church does not pray that they be subdued,
          but that He may remove iniquity from their hearts so that,
          having left their idols,
          they may be converted to the living and true God.
          And
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e589">a little later:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Qd1e591">
            Almighty eternal God,
            who desire not the death of sinners but always seek their life,
            graciously receive our prayer and free them from the worship of idols,
            and gather them into your holy Church for the praise and glory of your name.
          </quote>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e619">
          Where it is manifestly shown that there is some difference of barbarians from barbarians,
          according to what the Church indicates in sufficiently express words.
          And through all those things which have been adduced,
          it appears that there are four kinds of barbarians,
          namely the 1st and 2nd and 4th,
          in a qualified sense,
          that is,
          from some wild customs and principally from defect of faith.
          The first kind,
          however,
          can also comprehend Christian men if they show themselves savage,
          wild,
          cruel,
          and inhuman in some matter,
          by which name the Spanish,
          who afflicted the Indians with so many horrendous slaughters,
          so many massacres,
          and more than Tartar evils—peoples indeed most gentle and innocent to all—are barbarians and worse than barbarians.
          They also showed themselves barbarians when they fiercely rebelled against Caesar,
          taking up arms.
          The fourth species of barbarians,
          however,
          pertains to those alien from the faith of Christ,
          and thus comprehends all unbelievers.
          But properly barbarians are those of whom we discoursed in the third species,
          namely those overwhelmed by mental stupor,
          foolish,
          alien from reason,
          incapable,
          savage,
          wild,
          corrupt in morals,
          seditious,
          either by nature or by wicked habit of sinning,
          and of these specifically speaks
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-Rd1e675">the Philosopher in Politics book 1.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e105-d1e678">
          Let impious men therefore cease to throw the Philosopher at us,
          and those who dragged Sepulveda with lies to the defense of an impious cause,
          not understanding or not willing to understand the difference between the Philosopher and the holy doctors which has been demonstrated concerning barbarians.
          And therefore let them have mercy on their souls and ask from Christ that vanity may die in them and truth may live.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>