<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 50 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 51 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-23">July 23, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-23" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="214-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Hd1e97">Chapter 50 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e99">
          Chapter 50
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> It is manifest from the words of Saint Augustine cited above that 
          the Church does not compel pagans according to that saying:
          what have I to do with those who are outside?
          It only compels to enter the banquet those who have already once been made guests through baptism.
          This signifies there:
          whence God himself orders that guests be brought first to his great supper,
          afterwards compelled;
          in those therefore who were brought gently at first,
          the prior obedience is enforced when completed.
          And below he teaches that the hedges are heresies and schisms.
          Which he also teaches in book 2 against the letter of Gaudentius,
          saying that diverse errors and heresies are the ways:
          but the hedges signify depraved opinions and schisms.
          These two times and the difference between pagans and heretics who have already received the faith,
          namely that the former are to be allured and the latter compelled:
          the same most blessed father Augustine teaches in Letter 48 to Vincent the heretic Donatist:
          where he expounds those words of the parable "compel them to enter" concerning heretics.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e156">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Which also Innocent does,
          as we have already adduced above in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e164">
            c. maiores de baptismo
          </ref>
          with these words.
          Say that first he commanded the servant,
          that is the order of preachers who are great in the Church of God concerning heretics 
          <pb ed="#P" n="215-r"/>
          c. cum ex iniuncto.
          That he should go out into the streets and lanes of the city and bring in the poor and weak,
          the blind and lame,
          and not compel them to enter.
          Afterwards he also said that he should go out into the highways and hedges and compel those whom he 
          found there to enter,
          as in the aforementioned chapter displicet 23. q. 4:
          suggesting through this that Jews and similar people who do not have the faith are not to be forced to 
          the faith by the material sword:
          but to be brought in through the efficacy of reason and the law so that they may be convinced from 
          their own books:
          as in the aforementioned 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e1gg">c. de Iudaeis</ref>.
          But those who turn away from the bosom of the Church,
          like heretics and schismatics,
          are to be compelled to return to it since they are from the forum of the Church,
          even through secular power.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e206">
          Speaking below concerning the former he says:
          whom indeed he wishes to call to the wedding without compulsion,
          however,
          because we have nothing to do with those who are outside,
          Infra de diuortiis Gaudemus.
          But through this that he says that he should go out into the highways and hedges:
          he indicates heretics and schismatics:
          who with thorns tear the seamless tunic of the Lord,
          that is the unity of the Church.
          And these,
          as being from the forum of the Church,
          are to be compelled to enter and to hold the faith which they received in baptism,
          et cetera.
          These are Innocent's words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e233">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Therefore Augustine's exposition is to be referred to heretics,
          which beyond the above is also proved in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e241" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e711">
            c. displicet
          </ref>,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e247" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e480">
            c. ipsa pietas
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e250" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e492">
            c. quid faciet
          </ref>.
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e254" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e729">
            c. quando
          </ref>.
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e257" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e74X">
            c. qui peccat
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e260" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e1205@32-48">
            c. Nimirum 
            <pb ed="#P" n="215-v"/>
            § Utilius: 23. q. 4.
          </ref>
          and thus the glosses and doctors expound and teach there.
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> And note that it is generally true that men are to be compelled to provide the good 
          which they promised;
          if it was not promised,
          no one is compelled to do good.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e278">
          Thus the gloss and doctors note in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e280">
            c. 1o
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e285" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q5-d1e609">
            c. Et qui. 45 distinctio
          </ref>
          and in the said 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e288" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e696">
            c. Nimirum
          </ref>.
          where it is proved that from the beginning no one is to be compelled to good,
          but someone is compelled to persevere in that which he began,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e295" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q5-d1e609">
            c. ad fidem. 23. q. 5.
          </ref>
          these things from the glosses where above.
          And thus that common saying of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e303">
            Augustine in the enchiridion, c. 71
          </ref>
          is understood,
          that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Qd1e308" source="http://scta.info/resource/augen-d1e195-d1e113@125-129">
            many good things are provided to the unwilling
          </quote>:
          because their benefit is consulted,
          not their will:
          and he speaks there specifically of subjects doing evil works.
          Whence Augustine says thus:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Qd1e321" source="http://scta.info/resource/augen-d1e195-d1e113@71-81">
            he who amends with a lash one over whom power is given or restrains with some discipline
          </quote>.
          And below:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Qd1e326" source="http://scta.info/resource/augen-d1e195-d1e113@101-124">
            Not only in that which he pardons and prays:
            but truly also in that which he corrects and punishes with some amendatory penalty he gives alms:
            because he shows mercy.
            For many good things are provided to the unwilling
          </quote>
          etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e340">
          Note that Augustine speaks of those who are subject to us.
          But pagans are not subject to the Church,
          as has often been touched upon and determined above.
          Concerning this matter it is treated in the said 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e350" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d45-d1e274">
            c. et qui
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e355" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q1-d1e157">
            c. et qui paratus, § agenda. 23. q. 2.
          </ref>
          and in the said 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e360" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e711">
            c. displicet
          </ref>.
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e363" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q5-d1e736">
            c. non vos hominum
          </ref>
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e368" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q6-d1e151">
            q. 6. c. vides
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e372">
          Therefore no one is compelled 
          <pb ed="#P" n="216-r"/>
          to receive the faith,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e377" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d45-d1e179">
            c. de iudaeis 45 distinctio
          </ref>
          unless he has already received it.
          But the Church of Christians,
          using the ministry of princes,
          not only compels heretics to return to her bosom but also rightly avenges them with terrible 
          punishments.
          Both because the crime of heresy is most grave,
          inasmuch as it is committed directly against divine honor and results in derogation of the dignity of 
          Christ 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e398" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1390-d1e1342">
            c. cum secundum leges. de hereticis. libro 6
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e402" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d13q2-d1e238@4-43">
            Saint Thomas 4 Sentences distinction 13, q. 2, a. 2 throughout
          </ref>
          And it is far more grave to offend the eternal than the temporal majesty l. Gazaros C. de hereticis.
          Both because it is most dangerous and highly infectious.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e416">
          Whence heretics are the worst of men and most harmful to the whole universal Church.
          because they do not preserve concord:
          they preserve strife:
          they disturb peace 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e434" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1473-d1e341@5-90 http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1473-d1e377@1-37">
            Saint Thomas 2a 2ae q. 39, article 1 ad 3
          </ref>
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e439" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d13q2-d1e238@4-43">
            4 Sentences where above
          </ref>
          they strive to corrupt simple faithful.
          Therefore 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e446">
            the Apostle says in 2 Timothy 2
          </ref>
          concerning heretics,
          that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Qd1e451" source="http://scta.info/resource/IItim2_16@5-9 http://scta.info/resource/IItim2_17@1-6">
            they advance much toward impiety and their word spreads like cancer
          </quote>.
          And because of this they are to be separated from the fellowship of the faithful with harsh penalties.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e461">
          Whence:
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e463">
            Jerome
          </ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Qd1e465">
            Putrid flesh must be cut away and the scabby sheep must be driven from the folds:
            lest the whole house,
            dough,
            and cattle burn,
            be corrupted,
            rot,
            and perish.
            Arius was one spark in Alexandria:
            but because he was not immediately suppressed 
            <pb ed="#P" n="216-v"/>
            his flame ravaged the whole world
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
          And it is found in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-Rd1e486" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q3-d1e372">
            24. q. 3, c. resecandae
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e491">
          Third,
          because heretics are unfaithful to Christ and the Church or the Christian republic with that 
          unfaithfulness which leads to treason,
          they are traitors,
          rebels and disobedient,
          enemies and public enemies,
          etc.
          Concerning whom we have spoken most extensively in book 1 On the Only Way of Calling to True Religion.
          Since therefore heretics have been made from the forum of the Church (as has been proved),
          rightly it can punish them through the hands of faithful princes for the reasons often already stated.
          But other infidels,
          since neither have they been members of the Church:
          nor do they corrupt the Christian people with their superstitions because,
          as we suppose,
          they inhabit their own kingdoms far removed from our provinces,
          and consequently they are not from the forum of the Church,
          certainly their case ought to be very different from that of heretics.
          Wherefore Saint Augustine expounds the parable concerning heretics,
          but he does not truly speak of infidels.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e697-d1e541">
          And thus the confusion of the distinguished doctor appears manifestly:
          who,
          by his usual inept perversion,
          has attempted with all his strength to twist against simple infidels ignorant of God's law and 
          Catholic doctrine those things which the holy doctors either said or established against heretics:
          and likewise what faithful emperors established.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>