<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 39 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 39 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-29">April 29, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-29" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="172-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-Hd1e97">Chapter 39</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e99">
          Chapter 39
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> There still remains the sixth and final argument for the confirmation
          of the truth proven above,
          namely,
          because of the great hope and vehement presumption which is held concerning the conversion
          of such infidels and because of the correction of such people.
          Both because they do not commit such things with an obstinate mind,
          but certainly,
          as already appears from many cases,
          out of ignorance of divine things.
          And also because such sins could never be uprooted or cured in any way,
          especially the dregs of idolatry.
          So much does it cling to the hearts of idolaters,
          whether in its root,
          or in its trunk,
          or in its branches,
          or even in the rest,
          as William of Paris beautifully teaches in his book on the laws.
          But at every time,
          in every age,
          and among every people,
          it was extinguished solely by evangelical preaching with divine help.
          As we are taught by apostolic 
          <pb ed="#P" n="172-v"/>
          examples and the traditions of the doctors.
          For evangelical truth,
          since it has most efficacious power,
          shatters stony and iron hearts with its splendor,
          according to that passage of Jeremiah chapter 23:
          <quote>
          Are not my words like fire,
          says the Lord,
          and like a hammer that breaks the rock in pieces?
          </quote>
          Again Paul to the Hebrews 4:
          <quote>
          For the word of God is living and effective and sharper than any two-edged sword,
          and piercing even to the division of soul and spirit,
          of joints also and marrow,
          and a discerner of the thoughts and intentions of the heart.
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e180">
          Blessed Peter also testifies to this same thing,
          speaking of the efficacy of preaching through which faith is received,
          by which the hearts of infidels are cleansed from all error.
          Thus he speaks in Acts 15:
          <quote>
          Men and brethren,
          you know that in former days God chose among us that the Gentiles should hear from my mouth
          the word of the gospel and believe,
          and God who knows hearts bore witness,
          giving them the Holy Spirit just as he did to us,
          and he made no distinction between us and them,
          purifying their hearts by faith.
          </quote>
          And by the authority of Saint Thomas 2a 2ae question 7 article 2,
          this is the proper and peculiar effect of faith as the first principle of purification
          of the heart,
          namely,
          to purify the impurity of errors,
          which if it is perfected through charity informed,
          causes perfect purification.
          In these words of blessed Peter it is shown that through the signification of doctrine
          the Gentiles believe,
          and through believing,
          <pb ed="#P" n="173-r"/>
          with the Holy Spirit assisting,
          they receive purification from the errors of infidelity and the dregs of other sins
          by which infidels were contaminated.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e238">
          Eusebius teaches this most learnedly in his book on the preparation for the gospel,
          repeating often that idolatry and wicked vices were removed not by war,
          not by fire,
          but by the preaching of the word.
          Whence in treating of the efficacy of the word of God,
          by which the world was converted to Christ,
          among other things he puts forth these words in book 1 chapter 3:
          <quote>
          But as soon as the most pious and most peaceful doctrine of our savior appeared,
          the worship of many gods was held in check,
          wars ceased,
          the entire race of men rested from great evils and dangers.
          Which I would not hesitate to say is the greatest sign of his divine and ineffable power.
          But truly how much men have profited from his preaching,
          and how much usefulness even of this life they have obtained,
          if you pay attention with your very eyes,
          you will see that never at any other time in the memory of men has it been done
          by any illustrious man or people,
          except now by his words and doctrine alone diffused throughout the entire world,
          that the laws of all nations should be rightly and humanely established,
          those very laws which before his coming were foul,
          hideous,
          and monstrous.
          No longer do those who have followed him know their mothers in wicked marriages,
          nor do the Scythians feed on human flesh,
          since the preaching of Christ has reached even them,
          nor do they slay their dearest children,
          impelled by false religion.
          These and such things nearly infinite once vexed human life.
          The Massagetae and Derbices are reported to have thought their neighbors and relatives
          who were worn out by old age most miserable,
          and therefore sacrificing them,
          they feasted on their flesh which they had made most foul.
          The Tybareni used to throw down their elderly men.
          The Hyrcanians were accustomed to throw them to the rapacious race of birds,
          the Caspians to dogs.
          And indeed all these things they formerly did most religiously,
          but now by evangelical virtue alone this most savage pestilence has been driven out
          everywhere.
          So that they are no longer thought to be gods,
          nor empty and deaf images,
          nor evil demons dwelling in them,
          nor parts of the world which are seen,
          nor shades of dead men,
          nor whatever most harmful animals,
          but instead of all these,
          by the savior's teaching alone,
          all Greeks and barbarians who have heard the word of Christ with sincere mind,
          have arrived at such philosophy 
          <pb ed="#P" n="174-r"/>
          that they worship and follow the one true God,
          king and lord of heaven and earth,
          of the sun,
          stars,
          and the entire world,
          as creator,
          </quote>
          etc. He teaches the same in other places of the same work,
          and Clement had taught it before in book 9 to James the brother of the Lord.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e385">
          Again Saint Jerome in the Epitaph of Nepotian to Heliodorus says:
          <quote>
          The Indian,
          the Persian,
          the Goth,
          the Egyptian philosophize.
          The savagery of the Bessi and the crowd of skin-clad peoples,
          who once in the feasts of the dead,
          that is in the parentalia,
          that is in the obsequies of their parents,
          used to sacrifice men,
          have broken their hissing into the sweet melody of the cross,
          and Christ is the one voice of the whole world.
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e414">
          To which Saint Augustine agreed in Epistle 64 to Aurelius the Bishop:
          <quote>
          Therefore not harshly,
          as far as I judge,
          not severely,
          not in an imperious manner are these things taken away,
          more by teaching than by commanding,
          more by warning than by threatening.
          For thus must we act with the multitude of sinners.
          </quote>
          And below:
          <quote>
          Therefore they will first be warned,
          namely to believe or to cease from such things,
          the spiritual or those nearest to spiritual things,
          that is those who with respect to others are more capable of reason and spiritual things,
          such as are the nobles and principal lords,
          that they may acquiesce and consent,
          and thus others may be drawn more easily.
          </quote>
          This is the gloss of Cardinal Torquemada on the chapter commensationes, 44 distinctio,
          which is a fragment of his epistle,
          after which is added:
          <quote>
          By whose authority,
          namely of the nobles,
          and by the gentlest but most insistent admonitions,
          the rest of the multitude may be broken.
          </quote>
          Thus Augustine.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e461">
          It should be noted however that Augustine 
          <pb ed="#P" n="174-v"/>
          there speaks of the crimes of Christians,
          that if Christian doctrine wishes them to be removed not by severity,
          how much more shall we use the same moderation toward those who sin through ignorance
          and have not yet entered the Church of God?
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e480">
          With this opinion agrees what we related above from Gregory,
          and what the same Saint Gregory writes in c. qui Syncera 45 distinctio:
          <quote>
          What utility is there when,
          even if they are forbidden against long custom,
          nothing is profited for the conversion to faith,
          or why do we set rules for infidels concerning how they ought to observe their ceremonies,
          or do we entirely remove them,
          if through this we cannot gain them?
          Therefore it must be done that rather provoked by reason and gentleness,
          they may wish to follow us,
          not to flee,
          </quote>
          etc. Thus Gregory with few words interposed.
          He asserts the same in c. licet immediately following.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e511">
          And Pope Leo in c. Licet of the same distinctio in these words:
          <quote>
          Let benevolence do more toward those to be corrected than severity,
          exhortation more than threat,
          charity more than power.
          But by those who seek their own things and not those of Jesus Christ,
          one easily departs from this law,
          and while it pleases them to dominate rather than to counsel their subjects,
          honor inflates into pride,
          and what was provided for concord tends to harm.
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e536">
          Gregory speaks there of the crimes of priests,
          that if he wishes them to be cured with such moderation,
          certainly the same moderation must be used in healing the vices 
          <pb ed="#P" n="175-r"/>
          of infidels who have never heard evangelical truth.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e558">
          This sixth argument is assigned by Saint Thomas and Ulrich in his summa book 6,
          treatise 3,
          chapter 8,
          § ad quod respondemus,
          the summa of confessors book 3,
          treatise 30,
          question 8,
          Cardinal Torquemada in § hinc etiam 23 q. 4 in the third conclusion.
          These doctors cite Ulrich,
          who was,
          as we have already said above,
          a man of the greatest authority from the institute of Saint Dominic,
          as the author of the summa of confessors asserts in the first preface.
          I will append the words of Ulrich asserting that sinners must be spared
          if they offend through ignorance:
          <quote>
          The third cause is when one may probably presume concerning their correction,
          and they sin from weakness or ignorance and not from obstinate malice.
          </quote>
          To these agrees what Saint Gregory responded to Augustine,
          Archbishop of England,
          in book 12,
          response 7:
          <quote>
          But because there are many in the nation of the English who,
          while they were still in infidelity,
          are said to have been involved in this wicked marriage,
          when they come to the faith they are to be admonished to abstain,
          and to know that this is a grave sin,
          and to fear the dreadful judgment of God,
          lest for carnal pleasure they incur the torments of eternal torture.
          Yet for this reason they are not to be deprived of communion of the sacred body and blood
          of the Lord,
          lest we seem to avenge in them those things in which they bound themselves through
          ignorance before the bath of baptism.
          For in this time the holy Church corrects certain things through fervor,
          <pb ed="#P" n="175-v"/>
          tolerates certain things through gentleness,
          dissimulates certain things through consideration,
          so that often by bearing and dissimulating,
          she may restrain the evil which opposes.
          But all who come to the faith are to be admonished that they may not be able to perpetrate
          anything of the kind.
          But if any have perpetrated it,
          they are to be deprived of communion of the body and blood of the Lord.
          Because just as in those things which they did through ignorance the fault is to be
          tolerated in some measure,
          so it is to be pursued strongly in those who do not fear to sin knowingly.
          </quote>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e552-d1e655">
          Behold,
          Gregory wishes vices committed through ignorance to be suppressed by holy admonitions,
          the word of God,
          and the terror of hell,
          not by lances or cannons,
          which differs no less from the doctrine of Christ than heaven from earth.
          Where also blessed Gregory hints at three things:
          first,
          that to avenge the sins of infidels committed within the limits of their infidelity
          and territory does not pertain to the Church;
          second,
          that those crimes which are committed through ignorance ought to be corrected
          with gentleness;
          third truly that those who recently come to the faith are to be frightened to abstain
          from evils more by the threatening of eternal punishments than by the infliction of
          present ones.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
