<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 57 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 57 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2026-01-06">January 06, 2026</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2026-01-06" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="238-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e789">
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e789-d1e97">
          Chapter 57
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e789-d1e102">
          It does not seem that what contributes somewhat to the truth of this question should be omitted,
          namely that Sepulveda,
          with an incredible desire to publish the impious work which he wrote on this matter,
          presented it to the Supreme Council of the Indies.
          There,
          when the impiety of the work and its most present poison were observed,
          the most prudent senators rejected the work,
          not wishing it to be printed.
          But again Sepulveda,
          lest this work should perish for him,
          attempted by wondrous intrigues to approach the judges of the Supreme Royal Council,
          thinking it would come to pass that men ignorant of Indian affairs would not perceive the poison.
          They however,
          according to their gravity,
          <pb ed="#P" n="239-r"/>
          referred the judgment of the work to the academies of Salamanca and Complutense,
          which finally,
          with mature deliberation having been sent ahead,
          and many disputations having preceded on both sides,
          responded that the work was unworthy of the press because it contained doctrine that was 
          hardly sound,
          and as it seemed to some Complutensian theologians,
          most pernicious.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e789-d1e155">
          Sepulveda had sent the work before to the Council of Trent.
          But certain fathers,
          when they had read through the work and understood that the matter was hardly Christian,
          did not wish to treat of it,
          surely intending to prohibit the work from being printed and to impose silence on the author,
          if they had known that Sepulveda desired so greatly to publish it.
          Thus a man worthy of faith who attended the most sacred council narrated to me as certain.
          Sepulveda did not rest,
          but indeed,
          having scorned the judgment of the academies and of each royal council,
          sent the work secretly to Rome so that it might be printed there,
          understanding the liberty of that city,
          and that there was no one there who would turn back his poisonous arrows by opposing his breast.
          But what ruin that impious work will bring,
          perhaps the outcome of the matter will teach.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e789-d1e202">
          But I do not know why an old man,
          a priest,
          and a theologian,
          wished to have printed a work condemned by so many and such great men of two academies and 
          finally of the fathers who attended the council.
          Perhaps he does not wish so many vigils to perish for him,
          but it would be better that so many souls should not perish,
          to whose destruction Sepulveda seems to have devoted himself.
          <pb ed="#P" n="239-v"/>
          I pray for a better mind for him.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e789-d1e230">
          He brings forward in confirmation of his most pestilential opinion a certain Oviedo who wrote a 
          history,
          as he himself calls it general,
          about Indian affairs,
          who in book 3 chapter 6 of that work writes that the people of the island of Hispaniola are 
          vagrant,
          idle,
          mendacious,
          prone to evil and subject to many vices;
          furthermore of failing memory,
          inconstant,
          cowardly,
          ungrateful and hardly capable.
          Then that if there is any virtue in them,
          it flourishes in adolescence.
          But those who have entered manly age are overwhelmed by abominable vices.
          Again in book 6 chapter 9 of that work,
          speaking of the inhabitants of the continent,
          he calls them wild,
          savage,
          incorrigible,
          who can neither be corrected by severity nor led to virtue by blandishments or friendly 
          admonitions;
          shameless,
          prone to evil,
          cruel and who do not know how to be moved to mercy.
          He also writes that their little ones,
          when baptized,
          can attain eternal happiness;
          but those who have entered adolescence care little for the Christian religion even if they 
          receive baptism then or have already received it before.
          Both because the Christian religion seems to them burdensome and troublesome,
          and then because,
          since they are of failing memory,
          they immediately commit to oblivion whatever is handed down to them.
          <pb ed="#P" n="240-r"/>
          These lies scattered in various places of his history,
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e789-Nd1e328">Oviedo</name>
          did not blush to write in that history from which he foolishly promises himself immortality.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e789-d1e337"> 
          Since criminal lies falsely written against a most sincere and most modest people have rendered 
          them infamous,
          when that people,
          praised for docility and talent and a very well constituted republic (as we shall say in its 
          place),
          was worthy of commendation above all.
          Oviedo has his judge.
          Christ lives and has a scourge in his hand.
          This most vain trifler will render account to him,
          by his most virulent slanders he gives courage to most impious plunderers,
          so that they may utterly destroy a people deserving no such thing,
          and he diminishes the zeal of pious men who will think they are announcing the gospel not to men 
          but to beasts.
          If to falsely defame one single man is a sin worthy of eternal death,
          and the more serious the greater the loss of property or honor proceeds from it;
          if a sin of this kind is scarcely remitted by recanting a palinode,
          what should be thought or who could worthily exaggerate the sin of this most wretched man,
          making an insult to almost the entire human race,
          from which so many slaughters,
          so many fires,
          so many bereavements,
          finally so great an ocean of evils is derived?
          Outside this cause,
          how many lies has that miserable man heaped up?
          He professes that he will write the truth,
          and he thrusts pure fables upon the reader.
          I know one should spare a man who is uneducated and occupied with depicting the genealogies 
          of any people.
          <pb ed="#P" n="240-v"/>
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>