<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 9 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] [English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 9 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] [English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-26">September 2, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-09-02" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="49-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Hd1e97">Chapter 9 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e99">
          Chapter 9
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e104">
          ¶ Furthermore it is proved — as the seventh principal argument —
          that the infidels of whom we speak are not subject to the Church,
          nor within its jurisdiction,
          and that therefore idolaters cannot be punished by the Church:
          because they do not dwell within the boundaries of the universal Church,
          but are outside its district and territory.
          For no prince, king, emperor,
          or anyone else whatsoever can exercise jurisdiction beyond his own borders;
          for borders or limits are so called
          because they limit, determine, or constrain
          the thing, power, or jurisdiction of someone —
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e132" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e1565-d1e191">ff. de periculo et commodo rei venditae, l. ed quod</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e137" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e349-d1e301">cod. de officio prefecti pretorio africae l. 2a § postquam vero</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e142" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e349-d1e291">§ pro limitaneis</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e147" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e349-d1e301">§ ex sequenti</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e149" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e7721-d1e110">Cod. de fundis limitrophis l. 1a</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e155">
          That infidels do not dwell within the borders of the Church
          is proved as follows:
          because the Church is circumscribed by certain limits.
          For the Church is nothing other than the whole Christian people,
          united by fellowship and communion in the sacraments
          and strengthened by faith —
          as in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e172" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p3d4-d1e842">c. est unitas ecclesiae de consecratione distinctione 4</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e177" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e179">c. loquitur, 24 q. 1</ref> where it says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e179" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q1-d1e392@13-22">the Church is one,
            which extends itself more broadly in the multitude of its fruitful growth</quote>
          and so forth,
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e189" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d93-d1e470">93 distinctione c. legimus</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e192" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c1q1-d1e680">1 q. 1, c. multae in fine</ref>.
          And these sacraments are the limits or walls
          within which the Church is contained.
          Or we can say that the limits of the Church are the faith —
          the faith promised to God and to the Church in baptism
          by those who are converted.
          Likewise, the unity infused by charity and peace through the Holy Spirit,
          and preserved and perpetuated
          by the active and passive administration of the sacraments.
          Or else they are the very multitude of the faithful,
          gathered together in the unity of faith and charity —
          just as <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e221">Augustine, in Book 1 of the City of God, chapter 15</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e226">Book 15, chapter 8</ref> says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e229" source="http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l1-d1e90@35-43 http://scta.info/resource/adcd-l15-d1e2186@202-209">a city is a multitude of people
            bound together by some bond of fellowship:
            or a harmonious multitude of people</quote>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e237">
          ¶ The gateway of this city — that is, the Church — is baptism
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e241">de consecratione distinctio 4 capito cum itaque</ref>.
          Those who have been washed in baptism according to the word of the Lord
          are members of the Church and stand within it;
          but those who have not been reborn through baptism,
          or who waver in the vows made to God and the Church in baptism,
          or who withdraw from the unity of the Church or from the Christian religion
          through heresy or apostasy —
          these are outside the Church,
          even if they are not formally expelled.
          Although therefore Catholics may live together with pagans or heretics
          in the same house or city,
          the Church certainly consists in those who are united by faith and charity,
          and they are called the house or Church of God —
          according to that saying of <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e278">Jerome, 24 q. 1 c. omnibus consideratis</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e283">I think I may say without rashness
            that some are thus in the house of God,
            which is said to be built upon the firm rock</quote>.
          So says he.
          And <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e291">de penitentia distinctio 4 c. in domo</ref> where it says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e296" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c33q3d4-d1e227@16-24">the house of God,
            the temple of God,
            the kingdom of heaven are just people</quote>
          and so forth.
          This is also what <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e303">Paul</ref> signifies
          when he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e307" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor5_12@1-9">What is it to me to judge those who are outside?</quote>
          And speaking of the faithful he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e314" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor5_12@10-17">Is it not those who are inside that you judge?</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e319">
          The same is taught by <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e321">Gregory, 24 q. 1 c. quia ex sola</ref>,
          where he refers these words "inside" and "outside"
          to the faithful and the infidels,
          in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e328">from the Catholic Church alone (he says)
            truth is perceived;
            the Lord forbids having among oneself
            the place of infidels, so to speak</quote>.
          And further on:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e337">concerning the sacrificial lamb the Lord commands, saying:
            in one house you shall eat it;
            and you shall not carry any of its flesh outside the doors</quote> —
          that is, you shall not share it with infidels,
          since they are outside the doors of the Church,
          lacking baptism (that is),
          which is the gateway of the Church —
          as Gregory immediately explains:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e353">for in one house it is eaten,
            because in the one Catholic Church
            the true sacrifice of the Redeemer is offered;
            and divine law forbids carrying its flesh outside,
            because it forbids giving what is holy to dogs;
            it alone guards with a strong bond of charity
            those placed within it:
            hence too the waters of the flood lifted the ark
            to greater heights,
            but destroyed all those it found outside the ark</quote>
          — so says Gregory.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e381">
          ¶ Again, <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e383">Origen in his commentary on Leviticus</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e388" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q3-d1e228@22-64">as cited in 24 q. 3 c. cum aliquis</ref>
          says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e393">one who departs from truth,
            from the fear of God,
            from faith,
            from charity —
            departs from the encampment of the Church.
            Even if he is not cast out by the voice of a bishop;
            just as conversely,
            if someone is sent outside by an unjust judgment
            but has not previously departed on his own —
            that is,
            if he has not acted in such a way as to deserve to be cast out —
            he suffers no harm.
            For sometimes one who is sent outside is truly inside,
            and one who is outside appears to be held inside</quote>.
          So it is there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e414">
          And these words "outside" and "inside" are repeated frequently
          in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e418" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q3-d1e228@22-64">c. sic autem</ref>,
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e421" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c1q1-d1e60X">c. nec foris 1 q. 1</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e426">in the following passages</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e429">
          Therefore there is a place to which the Church does not extend:
          namely where the truth of the faith is not known,
          and where the true sacrifice is not offered —
          which is not to be shared with dogs,
          that is,
          with heretics, schismatics, Jews, idolaters,
          or pagans.
          Now, to be within the Church or outside the Church
          is nothing other than either to lack baptism
          or to have been reborn through it.
          For those who have been baptized and hold the faith,
          which is the gateway of the Church —
          these are assuredly within the Church;
          but those who lack faith are outside the Church,
          outside of which no salvation is to be hoped for —
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e457" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c1q1-d1e60X">24 q. 1 c. alenus</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e462" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q1-d1e523">c. quicumque: de consecratione, distinctio 4</ref>
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e466" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p3d4-d1e781@49-57">c. ecclesia</ref> where it says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e470">the gift of blessed life
            is found nowhere but within the Church</quote>.
          So it is there.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e476">
          Although therefore the Church is spread throughout the whole world,
          it nonetheless has its own borders and limits —
          not ones consisting of walls or physical barriers
          or a fixed expanse of land,
          but rather those of baptism and faith,
          beyond which lives (if living they can be called)
          every kind of infidel.
          For if among the Garamantes
          there are two Christians,
          there too the Church exists —
          even if there are very many thousands of pagans around;
          the Church consists in those two persons,
          in whom its limits are defined,
          and over them alone does it have its jurisdiction.
          The rest are outside the Church,
          and with them the Church has no concern.
          Just as <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e520"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Nd1e521">Paul</name></ref> says to a few believers
          living among countless pagans:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e527">Is it not those who are inside that you judge?
            As if he were saying openly:
            you do not judge others who are outside,
            that is, the infidels,
            nor ought you to judge them,
            since God has reserved their judgment to himself</quote>,
          and thus it must be understood in the Catholic sense —
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e539">c. ipsi met</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e541">c. cuncta per mundum</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e546">sequentibus, 9, q. 3</ref>,
          where it is written that the Roman Church and the Vicar of Christ
          can judge concerning the universal Church
          and concerning particular churches.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e558">
          For this must be understood as the power to judge all Christians —
          not however all pagans.
          This is sufficiently proved in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e566">c. Nouit de judicijs</ref>
          where the text says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e571">No one of sound mind is unaware
            that it belongs to our office
            to rebuke any Christian whatsoever
            for any mortal sin</quote> —
          therefore not any infidel whatsoever,
          because if that were the case,
          it would surely have said "any person"
          so as to include both the faithful and the infidel.
          Similarly, in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e588">c. maiores, § etem queritur. de baptismo</ref>
          it is proved that an infidel who receives baptism
          even under coercion —
          namely conditional coercion —
          belongs to the jurisdiction of the Church by reason of the sacrament.
          Therefore, by the contrary argument,
          if he does not receive the sacrament,
          he does not fall under ecclesiastical jurisdiction.
          And so <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e606"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Nd1e607">Antonio de Butrio</name></ref> annotates there in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e611">Note here that those who are not baptized
            are not under the jurisdiction of the Church;
            and that those who bear the character of baptism
            are subject to the jurisdiction of the Church
            in this respect:
            that they may be compelled to keep the faith they have assumed</quote>.
          So says he.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e624">
          And <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e626">Johannes de Anania, in the rubric de Judaeis, column 3</ref> says
          that Jews belong to the Church neither in body nor in soul,
          because they are not baptized —
          and therefore much less will the other infidels be so,
          since Jews are servants of the Church
          while the others are not.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e640">
          Therefore those who have not received baptism
          are outside the borders and jurisdiction of the Church.
          From this it is manifestly inferred
          that the Church cannot punish idolaters,
          since they are outside the borders and territory,
          and accordingly outside the jurisdiction of the Church.
          For no judge pronounces law beyond his own borders:
          neither does the King of France pronounce law for Spain,
          nor does the King of Spain give laws to the French,
          nor again can Caesar himself exercise imperial authority
          beyond the borders of the empire.
          For assuredly he lacks the power and jurisdiction
          which the author of nature,
          in his ineffable wisdom,
          has prescribed within certain limits for each people and prince,
          for the protection and preservation of every commonwealth.
          Hence this jurisdiction is said to be implanted
          in the place or territory
          or in the very bones of the people
          of every community or commonwealth:
          from which it cannot be torn away,
          no less than food from the preservation of life.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e686">
          ¶ And because nature's author has granted this privilege
          to all the kingdoms and communities of the world,
          the jurisdiction of one kingdom therefore does not go beyond its own borders,
          nor does it extend itself into the territory of another kingdom or province.
          Now the law of grace perfects the acts of nature —
          but does not overturn or abolish them:
          which all schools, all theologians, and all sacred doctors teach.
          <note type="marginal-note" place="margin-left" hand="F">
            Pagans and infidels have their own jurisdiction
            and can exercise it
          </note>
          Therefore pagan princes can lawfully defend their own borders,
          and they lawfully exercise jurisdiction;
          for their jurisdiction in this respect
          is no less natural than the jurisdiction of Christian princes.
          Since, according to <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e729">the Philosopher in the Politics</ref>,
          every commonwealth ought to be self-sufficient;
          and territory is the totality of lands
          lying within the borders of any given place,
          where someone holds the right to command —
          as in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e741" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t19-d1e240">c. licet de probationibus</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e746" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e5147-d1e2858">ff. de verborum significatione l. pupillus § territorium</ref>.
          And it is said that
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e751">"district" comes from "to constrain";
            "territory" from "terrifying"
            or from "to frighten"</quote>
          at that said place —
          concerning which <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e758">Felinus at length
            in c. Rodulphus § de hoc verbo territorio
            folio 173 de rescriptis</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e766">
          That it is forbidden by divine law
          for anyone to violate or transgress
          another's territory or jurisdiction
          is shown by scripture.
          For we read in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e775" source="http://scta.info/resource/prov22_28@1-8">Proverbs 22</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e780">Do not move the ancient landmarks
            which your fathers have set</quote>,
          and upon those who transgress the borders of others
          sacred scripture pronounces terrible curses in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e790">Deuteronomy 27</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e792" source="http://scta.info/resource/deut27_17@1-11">Cursed be he who moves
            his neighbor's landmark;
            and all the people shall say, Amen</quote>.
          The same is proved from the traditions of law in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e801" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e1488-d1e177">l. final ff. de jurisdictione omnium judicum</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e807">the gloss there</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e809" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e249-d1e128">in l. 3, ff. de officio presidis</ref>
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e814" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e88-d1e159">c. vt animarum de constitutionibus libro 6o</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e818">the doctors in both places</ref>
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e820" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t2-d1e301">c. cum contingat de foro competenti</ref>
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e826" target="http://scta.info/resource/kdhaWs-d1e326-d1e116 http://scta.info/resource/kdhaWs-d1e326-d1e128">clementina pastoralis de re judicata</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e832">
          For acts performed by a judge outside his territory have no validity:
          for jurisdiction is embedded in the bones of the people
          of every territory,
          as has been said —
          as the doctors attest in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e840" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e182-d1e123">l. 1 § cum urbem ff. de officio prefecti vrbis</ref>
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e845" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e182-d1e172">l. finali eo titulo</ref>
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e849" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e1509-d1e393">l. in modicis ff. de contrabenda emptione</ref>
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e852" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e249-d1e128">l. 3 ff. de officio presidis</ref>
          and in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e854">l. 2 ff. de jurisdictione omnium judicum</ref>.
          Supporting this is <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e859">c. diaconi 93 dist ibi</ref>:
          every person is commanded to possess something in this visible world
          in such a way that he is content with his own possession alone
          and does not seize the goods of others —
          he shall not take away the poor man's field,
          nor his vineyard,
          nor any means of transport,
          nor his servants,
          nor his produce,
          and so forth.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e876">
          Now so true is it that a judge cannot pronounce law outside his territory
          that:
          even if someone commits an offense within my territory —
          in which case I would be able to punish him
          even if he is a foreigner
          and a subject of another prince,
          as in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e889" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e249-d1e128">l. 3 ff. de officio presidis</ref> —
          yet if he flees beyond the borders of that judge's territory,
          the judge can no longer punish him.
          For the jurisdiction that arises by reason of a crime
          is not natural but accidental,
          just as is that which arises from domicile;
          and so as soon as the offender leaves that territory,
          the jurisdiction of that judge or prince comes to an end —
          as is proved in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e906">clementina Pastorali § denique: de re judicata</ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e913">
          <del rend="crosshatch" hand="B">¶ Since therefore infidels —
            however much idolaters and sinners
            who have not received the faith,
            especially those who have never even heard anything of it,
            possessing their own lands
            and kingdoms and territories separate from Christian borders —
            sin and offend
            outside the bounds and territory of the universal Church,
            so that her jurisdiction does not encompass them:
            it manifestly follows
            that it does not pertain to the Church,
            nor to any member of it,
            to punish them for idolatry
            or for any crime or offense whatsoever
            committed precisely within the limits
            of their own rule or infidelity —
            such as our Indians and their like.</del>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-d1e949">
          Consonant with these things is what <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Rd1e951">Cajetan writes
            in his commentary on those words of the Apostle</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e157-Qd1e956">What is it to me to judge those who are outside?
            Christians (he says) he punishes as subjects of his judgment;
            but non-Christians,
            as those who are outside,
            as those who are beyond his jurisdiction,
            he does not punish,
            because it does not fall to him to judge them.
            Is it not those who are inside that you judge?
            He makes clear the distinction
            from the common practice of judges.
            For the pronoun "you" points to persons
            when they are exercising the office of judge:
            for it is common to persons
            to judge those who are comprehended within the limits
            of their jurisdiction,
            and so forth</quote>.
          So says Cajetan.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
