<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 21 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 21 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-10">Apr 10, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-10" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="99-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Hd1e97">Chapter 21 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#P" n="99-v"/>
          Chapter 21
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e106">
          In agreement with these things is what 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e110">Saint Thomas writes in 2a 2ae, q. 10, ar. 9</ref>
          , where he says that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e115">
            the Church has no judgment concerning infidels who have in no way received the Christian faith, 
            namely, pagans and Jews, by spiritual judgment: 
            but by temporal judgment in the case when living among Christians they commit some fault: 
            and they are punished temporally by the faithful. 
            And in the response to the second argument he says: 
            that the Church does not have judgment against infidels as to inflicting spiritual punishment on them: 
            yet it has judgment over some infidels as to inflicting temporal punishment: 
            to which pertains that the Church sometimes for certain special faults withdraws from some infidels the communion of the faithful</quote>
          . These are the words of Saint Thomas.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e151">
          Note those words 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e155">
            temporal in the case: when living among Christians: they commit some fault</quote>
          . Likewise note those words 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e162">
            it has judgment over some</quote>
          . Again note those words 
          "for certain special faults". 
          From these things it is most manifestly proven that the Church cannot punish infidels temporally except only when they live among Christians: 
          nor can it do this except in certain cases, 
          as for instance if they do not remit usury to Christians: 
          if they have Christian slaves: 
          if they are blasphemers against Christ the Lord or against the saints and in similar 
          <add place="margin-right" hand="F">1 case</add>
          cases, concerning which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e192">in d. c. sepe with the following</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e198">glossa. 28. q. 1</ref>
          . and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e200">c. multorum</ref>
          . and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e205">c. etsi iudaeos</ref>
          . And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e207">c. cum sit nimis de iudaeis</ref>
          . And in many other places of both laws.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e215">
          And those words of Saint Thomas 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e218">they are punished temporally by the faithful</ref>: 
          signify that infidels in those cases in which it is permitted to punish them: 
          ought to be punished by secular princes, 
          and by their ministers to whom they are subject: 
          unless in cases in which the Church punishes secular persons.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e233">
          Again through those words of Saint Thomas "it has judgment over some infidels": 
          he teaches that the Church does not have jurisdiction generally over all infidels: 
          but only over some (I understand contentious jurisdiction) 
          namely in those cases in which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e249">above in chapter six</ref>
          we have taught that the Church is able to reduce into act the jurisdiction which it has over infidels in habitu. 
          Therefore it is manifestly evident that the Church does not indifferently interpose itself to judge concerning the faults of all infidels: 
          nor on account of all faults: 
          nor in all cases, which can be reduced to three as can be gathered from the sayings of Saint Thomas, 
          Innocent and the canonists.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e271">
          First when those dwelling among Christians commit some atrocious crimes: 
          for then they can be punished as subjects of the Church or at least of its members.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e280">
          <add place="margin-left" hand="F">case 2</add>
          ¶ The second case is when they possess kingdoms from which they have despoiled the Christian people and they commit shameful crimes: 
          such as the crime of idolatry or against nature: 
          by which they defile and pollute places dedicated to Christ.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e300">
          ¶ Third when not content with their native kingdoms and lands: 
          they would invade the provinces of Christians and molest the Church with warlike tumult or be blasphemers against Christ or the saints: 
          all these things are sufficiently evident through what has been deduced above.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e313">
          ¶ But it is necessary to remember 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e317">
            the gloss in c. ius quiritum 1 distinctio</ref>
          and some other 
          <add place="above-line" hand="B">canonists</add>
          who speaking generally without distinction entangle matters and obscure the minds of men. 
          For these not distinguishing Gentiles from gentiles, 
          and infidels from infidels say with that gloss: 
          that gentiles are under the Roman empire. 
          This, taken absolutely, I say is foolish. 
          But because it must not be believed that the gloss and the others, 
          who say similar things, have fallen into this error: 
          it must be said that the gloss should be understood concerning gentiles or infidels, 
          Jews, Saracens or of another religion who live within the provinces of the Church: 
          either because they inhabit the kingdoms of Christian princes: 
          or because they possess kingdoms taken away from Christians. 
          Since those kingdoms are included within the boundaries of the Roman empire: 
          which do not exceed the boundaries of the Christian people.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e365">
          For the Roman Empire is distinguished by certain limits and always has been according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e371" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e376">
            Boethius in the Consolation of Philosophy, book 2, prose 7</ref>
          where he says 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e376" source="http://scta.info/resource/hy7y6y-d1e59-d1e272@198-225">
            in the age of Marcus Tullius, as he himself signifies in a certain place: 
            the fame of the Roman Republic had not yet crossed Mount Caucasus and it was then mature that is known from ancient times: 
            to the Parthians and also to the other peoples of those places it was formidable</quote>
          and so on. These are the words of Boethius.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e394">
          Therefore the Roman Caesars were not lords of the whole world, 
          even when Roman power was most extended through the world. 
          And today the Roman empire does not exceed the limits of the Catholic Church: 
          <note place="margin-right" hand="F">
            the Roman empire now does not exceed the limits of the Catholic Church</note>
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e410">
            the Authentic on not alienating or exchanging things of the Church, § sicut</ref>
          there: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e415">
            Not indeed caring for one thing but leaving another uncared for but in every land which the law of the Romans contains and the sanction of the Catholic Church 
            namely this law extends and determines what are its own</quote>
          and so on.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e429">
          And thus explicitly teaches 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e433">
            Hostiensis in the Summa in the title who are legitimate sons § qualiter. from whom sons word</ref>
          then by the authorities of the saints Hostiensis says. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e442" source="http://scta.info/resource/nbht7y-d1e1630-d1e1204@504-524">
            For the law of the emperor cannot bind except those whom the law of the Romans holds and the sanction of the Catholic Church: 
            because outside, namely, the Church, there is no empire</quote>
          this is expressly proven in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e456">
            l. 2, C. de Officio prefecti pretorio africae</ref>
          there: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e461">
            before the invasion of the Vandals and Moors, the Roman republic had boundaries: 
            and 
            <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e467">
              where the ancient guardians</quote>
            kept watch</quote>
          and so on. And there 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e473">
            we hope soon in our times to advance: 
            so that both in security and peace: 
            the provinces with their ancient boundaries may be preserved intact</quote>
          and so on. And in many paragraphs that law touched upon.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e487">
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e489">
            Bartholus in l. hostes glossa in l. non dubito, ff de captiuis et postliminio</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e496">
            Angelus de Perusio in the Authentics vt liceat matri et auiae § quia vero column 8: notable 2</ref>
          . where he says that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e505">
            princes make laws against barbarians because those barbarians were subject to them</quote>
          .
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e517">
          Therefore where they are not subject and the reason for subjection ceases, 
          the prince cannot make law: 
          because the reason for jurisdiction ceases. 
          It is also proven in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e525">
            l. 1. 2. and 3. C. de fundis limitrophis lib. 11</ref>
          . and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e530">
            l. 2. C. de Eunuchis there</ref>
          : 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e536">
            outside the places subject to our empire</quote>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e541">
            l. mercatores. C. de commerciis et mercatoribus</ref>
          there 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e546">
            lest of a foreign kingdom</quote>
          , and so on. Therefore the kingdoms of gentiles were foreign to the dominion of the Roman empire. 
          And the emperors themselves confessed this very thing and consequently neither by right nor in fact did they obtain rule over the whole world.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e561">
          ¶ There are those who assert that the Roman Caesar is lord of the world by right although not in fact, 
          but these most foolishly boast these things: 
          they cannot prove them with solid arguments. 
          Indeed it is manifestly false. 
          For neither up to now in any age has anyone been lord of the world: 
          nor did the tyrannical arms of the Romans subdue the world. 
          Thus therefore should be understood 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e580">
            l. deprecatio ff. ad legem Rhodiam de lactu</ref>
          . and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e585">
            authe. vt omnes obediant iudicibus prouincialibus § haec considerantes</ref>
          where it is said 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e593">
            we command all who obey our scepters in the entire dominion, 
            which sees the rising sun, and which sees the setting sun and which is on either side</quote>
          these words there.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e607">
          Any prince can say the same thing. 
          For there is no kingdom which does not look toward the east, 
          west, south and north. 
          Nevertheless it is true that the Roman Caesar is the universal lord of Christians. 
          Which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e628">
            Baldus teaches in the proem ff. column 2</ref>
          . 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e633">
            the doctors in l. 1, C. de summa trinitate</ref>
          and there 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e638">
            Jason, column 2</ref>
          , and there 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e640">
            Baldus in the said l. 1. column 2</ref>
          .
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e647">
          But to assert that the Roman emperor is the legitimate 
          <note type="marginal-note" place="margin-right" hand="F">
            The emperor is not lord of the world</note>
          lord of the whole world, is the emptiest nonsense and to deceive emperors by flattery: 
          and a handle for mixing the world in dissensions. 
          And more ridiculous is what besides others 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e665">
            Michael Vlcurrunus writes in the treatise on the government of the world</ref>
          (namely) that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e672">
            the Roman Caesar whom seven princes of Germany elect in place of the whole world: 
            all nations of the world are bound to obey</quote>
          .
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e680">
          He cites 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e684">
            John Andreas in the additions to the Speculator in the title on rescripts presentia § last at the word "likewise what was obtained"</ref>
          : but John Andreas writes no such thing but that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e695">
            these to whom these princes succeeded elected as a college and university consisting (namely) of princes, 
            and the entire people subject to the Roman empire: 
            or the army elected representing that university</quote>
          and so on. these are his words. 
          Therefore he does not say that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Qd1e713">
            in place of the entire university of the world</quote>
          and so on, although even if 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Nd1e717">John Andreas</name>
          had said it he would not be less reprehensible than 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Nd1e723">Michael</name>
          who attributes these things to him. 
          Although rather because neither does 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Nd1e727">John Andreas</name>
          assert those things but reports a certain doctor 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e731">
            named Vpoldum saying</ref>
          . But because we hope with the grace of God's favor elsewhere to show individually how full of errors is 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-Rd1e741">
            the aforementioned treatise on the government of the world</ref>, 
          for the present we will refrain from speaking more about this.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e315-d1e749">
          ¶ Therefore the words of blessed Cyril do not oppose our Catholic and most proven doctrine which all doctors both sacred and secular follow.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>