<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"
  type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"
  type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 10 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] — English Translation</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 10 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] — English Translation</title>
          <date when="2024-09-03">September 3, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-09-03" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="54-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Hd1e97">Chapter 10 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e99">
          Chapter 10
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e104">
          ¶ Eighth: that the Church cannot punish idolaters
          is proved from Augustine on Psalm 145,
          where, expounding the verse, "The Lord renders judgment
          for all who suffer injustice,"
          he says: concerning those who are not under its own jurisdiction
          (that is, of the Church),
          upon whom discipline cannot be exercised —
          although I find those very words nowhere in that place.
          But because
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e123">Augustine</ref> is cited by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e125" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e354">Gratian, Causa 23, q. 4, § "To these, therefore, a reply is made,"
            under the canon <hi rend="italic">Cum in lege</hi></ref>
          where Gratian subjoins the following:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e133"
            source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e357@5-51 http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e547">there are certain things
          which are to be corrected by wholesome admonition alone,
          not to be punished by bodily chastisements;
          and their retribution is to be reserved to divine judgment alone,
          when we cannot exercise discipline upon offenders —
          either because they are not subject to our jurisdiction,
          or because, even if their crimes are known to us,
          they cannot be proved by clear evidence.
          Concerning those who are not subject to our jurisdiction,
          the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e164" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e167">Apostle says in the First Letter to the Corinthians</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e167"
            source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor5_12@1-9 http://scta.info/resource/Icor5_13@1-7">For what is it to me
          to judge those who are outside?
          The Lord will judge these.</quote></quote> And so forth.
          <pb ed="#P" n="54-v"/>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e175">Thus Gratian.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e178">
          Therefore, if they are not subject to our jurisdiction,
          we cannot punish them in any way.
          The same is taught by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e183">Augustine in Homily 50 on the Worthlessness and Necessity of Penance,
            col. 6.</ref>
          And from there
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Nd1e188">Gratian</name>
          drew what he reports in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e193" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c2q1-d1e407">c. <hi rend="italic">Multi</hi>, C. 2, q. 1.</ref>
          More explicitly,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e198">Augustine in the book <hi rend="italic">On Baptism</hi></ref>
          is read in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e203" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c2q1-d1e407">c. <hi rend="italic">Non ne</hi>, C. 1, q. 1,</ref>
          where he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e207">Were not the Sodomites Gentiles,
          that is, pagans,
          and worse therefore than the Jews,
          to whom the Lord says:
          "It shall be more tolerable for Sodom on the day of judgment than for you,"
          and to whom the prophet says:
          "You have justified Sodom,"
          that is, by comparison with you
          Sodom has been made just?</quote>
          And further:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e224">For even the Gentiles themselves,
          if they were able to hold anything divine and right in their teachings,
          the holy men did not disapprove.
          Although those Gentiles, on account of their superstitions and idolatry,
          their pride and their other corrupt morals,
          were to be abhorred;
          and unless corrected, were to be punished by divine judgment.</quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e240">Thus Augustine.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e243">
          Do you see that
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Nd1e247">Augustine</name>
          holds that the punishment of crimes committed by pagans or idolaters
          is reserved to divine judgment?
          Therefore, such punishment does not belong to the Church.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e257">
          ¶ Ninth: this truth is proved from the argument
          upon which all the other arguments rest.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e263" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d17q3-d1e321">Saint Thomas sets it forth
            in Book IV of the <hi rend="italic">Sentences</hi>,
            distinction 17, q. 3, art. 1, question 5, in the body of the article.</ref>
          The argument is this.
          The Pope, the vicar of Christ,
          and the other ministers of the Church were established in the Church
          after the Church was divinely instituted.
          Hence it is certain that the building up, or institution, of the Church
          preceded and is presupposed by the ministries and acts of the Church's ministers;
          just as the works of creation preceded and are presupposed
          by the works of nature.
          Now this institution of the Church consists of faith and the sacraments.
          The sacraments necessarily presuppose that there must be
          certain persons capable and fitted to receive the sacraments —
          namely, those made capable through faith.
          But pagans and unbelievers,
          since they are entirely outside the Church
          and are not members of the Church
          because they lack faith,
          are incapable of the sacraments;
          and thus the institution of the Church
          does not in any way pertain to them.
          From this it follows that the works or acts of the Church's ministers
          do not extend to them,
          just as the operation of nature does not extend
          to things not yet created,
          or to things that do not yet exist in the natural order.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e320">
          But jurisdiction and the operations or judicial acts
          by which offenses are punished
          belong to the ministers of the Church
          by reason of faith and the sacraments,
          which must necessarily be presupposed to the acts of the ministers —
          just as the work of creation must be presupposed
          in order for nature to be able to act.
          Therefore, the ministers of the Church cannot, as a rule,
          exercise jurisdiction over pagans or unbelievers,
          since they are not capable subjects of such operations of the Church.
          From which it is inferred that if, by an impossible supposition,
          the Apostles had converted no one to the faith,
          they would have been entirely unable to exercise
          the jurisdiction granted to them by Christ,
          since, with no Church existing among them,
          <pb ed="#P" n="55-v"/>
          there would have been lacking a subject or matter
          upon which to exercise the acts of their jurisdiction.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e357">
          Therefore, the punishment of idolatry,
          or of any sin whatsoever of pagans or unbelievers,
          does not belong to the Church.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e364">
          ¶ Tenth: in the conversion of unbelievers
          who have never received the faith,
          to whom the faith has not been preached,
          and who have not resisted hearing the faith —
          with respect to whom this will be called the first preaching of the faith —
          one must not begin with the punishment of sins,
          but with the offer of clemency and forgiveness
          and with exhortation to repentance.
          This is proved because,
          if we begin by punishing their crimes,
          we overturn the express commandment and institution of Christ,
          and the form of preaching prescribed to preachers.
          For Christ, sending the Apostles to preach the Gospel to every creature,
          addressed them in the words recorded by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e405" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e407">Luke in the final chapter:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e407"
            source="http://scta.info/resource/lc24_46 http://scta.info/resource/lc24_47 http://scta.info/resource/lc24_48">"Thus it was written,
          and thus it was necessary for Christ to suffer
          and to rise from the dead on the third day,
          and that repentance and forgiveness of sins
          should be preached in his name to all nations,
          beginning from Jerusalem;
          and you are witnesses of these things"</quote> — namely,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e430" source="http://scta.info/resource/go-lc24-d1e115">"those things which are to be preached,"</quote>
          according to the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e423" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e430">interlinear gloss.</ref>
          And on the word
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e428" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc24_47@11-11">"all,"</quote>
          the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e439" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e432">same interlinear gloss</ref> says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e432" source="http://scta.info/resource/go-lc24-d1e91">"Not in one nation only, that of the Jews,
          nor in any one region of the earth."</quote>
          Thus the gloss.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e438">
          And on the phrase
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e443" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc24_47@13-15">"beginning from Jerusalem"</quote>
          and so forth,
          the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e441" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e449">Glossa Ordinaria</ref> says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e449" source="http://scta.info/resource/gom-lc24-d1e89">It was fitting that the ministers
          who were to preach repentance and forgiveness to all nations
          should begin from Jerusalem —
          not only because to them were entrusted the oracles of God,
          and because theirs is the adoption as children,
          and the glory,
          and the covenants,
          and the giving of the law;
          but also so that the nations,
          entangled in various errors and crimes,
          might be drawn to the hope of pardon
          by this supreme act of divine mercy:
          that pardon was granted even to those
          who had crucified the Son of God.</quote>
          Thus the gloss.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e476">
          ¶ From these words it is proved, first,
          that Christ commanded the Apostles to preach the Gospel
          by freely offering and promising forgiveness of sins.
          Likewise, that they should exhort those people to repentance.
          That this was indeed a command is proved from those words,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e491" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc24_46@4-6">"thus it was written,"</quote>
          that is, thus it was prophesied;
          therefore it was necessary
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e498" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc24_46@11-12">"for Christ to suffer."</quote>
          Given, therefore,
          the divine pre-ordination and the necessity of the end —
          which was to free and redeem the human race,
          concerning which
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e508">Saint Thomas, Part III, q. 46, a. 1</ref>
          and in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e510" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l3d20q1-d1e257">Book III of the <hi rend="italic">Sentences</hi>,
            distinction 20, a. 1, question 3</ref> —
          by the same manner and by the same necessity
          it was necessary to preach repentance and forgiveness of sins to all nations.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e521">
          For just as it was necessary for Christ to suffer
          and to rise from the dead for the redemption of the human race —
          both because it was thus prophesied,
          and because it had been pre-ordained by the Lord
          on account of the necessity of the end —
          so too it had been ordained by God
          and foretold by the prophets many years beforehand,
          and it was also necessary for the fulfillment of the counsel and will of God,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e540" source="http://scta.info/resource/Itim2_4@1-6">"who wills all people to be saved,"</quote>
          especially the predestined,
          that the evangelical truth should be announced —
          beginning with the exhortation of people to repentance
          and promising them, on behalf of God and Jesus Christ,
          pardon and forgiveness of all their sins.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e563">
          This was so necessary that,
          unless the Gospel had been announced in this manner
          to those who at that time were ignorant of the truth,
          the predestined would certainly not have attained salvation;
          and thus the fruit of Christ's passion would have been rendered
          void and null —
          in accordance with that verse of
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e577" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e579">the Psalmist in Psalm 29:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e579" source="http://scta.info/resource/ps29_10@2-9">"What profit is there in my blood,
          if I descend into corruption?"</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e585">
          But this — namely, that the predestined should fail to attain salvation —
          was impossible.
          Therefore, it was entirely and necessarily required
          that the Apostles should evangelize
          in accordance with the form,
          commandment,
          and institution given to them by Christ.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e598">
          This consequence is clear.
          For when God predestined those who would attain salvation,
          he also predestined the means by which salvation was to come to them.
          This is taught by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e608">Saint Thomas, Part I, q. 28, a. 8.</ref>
          Now the first and foremost means was the passion of the Son of God;
          and the second and foremost after the first,
          presupposing divine grace,
          was the announcement of the Gospel
          in accordance with the commandment,
          form,
          and institution of Christ —
          in keeping with that verse of the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e625" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e633">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Nd1e626">Apostle</name>
            in Romans 10:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e633" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom10_14@1-19">"How will they call upon him in whom they have not believed?
          Or how will they believe in him whom they have not heard?
          How will they hear without a preacher?"</quote>
          Therefore, the preaching of the Gospel was a necessary means
          for the salvation of those whom God predestined;
          and consequently, the Apostles were entirely and necessarily obliged
          to proclaim the law of Christ in that manner.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e651">
          Now the manner of evangelizing,
          in accordance with the institution and commandment of Christ,
          is to exhort people to repentance
          while offering them forgiveness of sins —
          as is clear from
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e660">the words of Luke cited above,</ref>
          and from many other passages of the Gospel and the prophets.
          In confirmation of this,
          when Christ began to disseminate his heavenly teaching,
          he addressed people in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e671" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt4_17@7-12">"Do penance,
          for the kingdom of heaven is at hand,"</quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e676" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e671">Matthew 4.</ref>
          That word of <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e681">Luke,</ref>
          <mentioned>it is necessary</mentioned> (<hi rend="italic">oportet</hi>),
          therefore implies a commandment and introduces necessity —
          as is also proved from those words of
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e689" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e691">John 3:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e691" source="http://scta.info/resource/io3_7@6-9">"You must be born again."</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e697">
          This word <mentioned>it is necessary</mentioned> (<hi rend="italic">oportet</hi>)
          entirely introduces necessity.
          For it is necessary for people to be reborn through the water of baptism
          in order to be saved —
          in accordance with that saying:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e707" source="http://scta.info/resource/io3_5@7-20">"Unless one is born again of water
          and the Holy Spirit,
          he cannot enter the kingdom of God,"</quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e714" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e707">John 3.</ref>
          So also in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e737" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e720">John 10,</ref>
          the word <mentioned>it is necessary</mentioned> (<hi rend="italic">oportet</hi>)
          introduces necessity:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e720" source="http://scta.info/resource/io10_16@2-15">"I have other sheep
          that are not of this fold;
          and I must bring them also."</quote>
          These sheep are pagans,
          who are to be brought to the sheepfold of Christ
          by the preaching of evangelical truth.
          Therefore,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e734" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e736">that verse of Luke,</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e736" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc24_46@4-6">"thus it was written"</quote> and so forth,
          and the word <mentioned>it is necessary</mentioned> (<hi rend="italic">oportet</hi>),
          which introduces necessity,
          signifies that preachers of the Gospel are necessarily obliged
          to exhort people to repentance,
          offering them forgiveness of sins.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e752">
          For just as there the word <mentioned>it is necessary</mentioned> (<hi rend="italic">oportet</hi>),
          referred to the passion and resurrection of Christ,
          signifies that these were necessary for the salvation of the predestined,
          so too it signifies that the Gospel must be preached
          with exhortation to repentance
          and with the offer of forgiveness of sins.
          No announcer of the Gospel,
          therefore,
          can begin with the punishment of the crimes of pagans —
          especially of those to whom the faith has not yet been preached.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e795">
          For the Apostles,
          sensing themselves bound by a strict commandment
          to announce the Gospel in the very manner
          that Christ taught and commanded,
          therefore observed most strictly,
          in both word and deed,
          the aforesaid form and manner in converting the world.
          Concerning them,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e810">Augustine in Letter 3 to Volusianus</ref>
          says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e815">filled with the Holy Spirit,
          they suddenly speak the languages of all nations;
          they faithfully refute errors;
          they preach most wholesome truth;
          they exhort to repentance;
          they promise, from divine grace,
          pardon for past blameworthy life;
          fitting signs and miracles follow upon the preaching of true and holy religion;
          fierce unbelief is stirred up against them;
          they endure what was foretold,
          they hope for what was promised;
          they teach what was commanded;
          few in number they are scattered throughout the world;
          they convert peoples with wondrous ease;
          they grow in the midst of enemies;
          they increase under persecutions;
          through the narrow straits of afflictions
          they spread to the very ends of the earth;</quote>
          and further:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e849">the temples and images of demons
          and sacrilegious rites
          are gradually and in turn overthrown,
          as the prophets had foretold.</quote>
          Thus Augustine.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e857">
          From these words of Augustine
          our position is abundantly confirmed —
          namely, that the Gospel must be announced to pagans
          with exhortation to repentance
          and with the offer of forgiveness of their sins.
          Furthermore, that word of Christ,
          <mentioned>it is necessary</mentioned> (<hi rend="italic">oportet</hi>),
          introduces necessity —
          as the canonists teach in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e908" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t2-d1e164">c. <hi rend="italic">Nam concupiscentiam</hi>,
            de constitutionibus</ref>
          and in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e913">c. 1 de libelli oblatione</ref>
          and in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e917" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e108-d1e122">c. 1 de rescriptis, Book VI,</ref>
          and in other parts;
          and it is also held by the civilians in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e923">l. 1 on the word <hi rend="italic">oportet</hi>,
            ff. de iustitia et iure</ref>
          and so forth.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e929">
          The rationale behind all of this is given by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e933" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e945">Augustine in <hi rend="italic">Against Petilianus</hi></ref>
          and is read in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e938" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q5-d1e609@41-54" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e945">C. 23, q. 5, c. <hi rend="italic">Ad fidem</hi>;</ref>
          he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e945">but the punishing discipline of evil living is preposterous —
          that is, disordered —
          unless the hard work of teaching good living precedes it;</quote>
          that is,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e955">unless the offender is first instructed in what is good,
          or unless the one who corrects first offers an example of good life,</quote>
          as <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e962" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e955">the gloss explains.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e965">
          You see that Augustine teaches
          that holy doctrine and the example of upright living
          must precede the punishment of a sinner.
          This holds all the more for sinners who sin in ignorance —
          such as those pagans who have never heard the words of Christ,
          concerning whom our present discourse has been established.
          Otherwise, punishment and discipline is preposterous and disordered,
          and devised by the spirit of the devil.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-d1e987">
          ¶ Second, it is to be noted from those words of our Savior —
          namely,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e993" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc24_46@4-7">"thus it was written"</quote>
          and so forth —
          that the form in which he commanded his Gospel to be announced
          must be observed for whatever nations of the world are evangelized,
          indiscriminately,
          whether they are pagans or weighed down by the most atrocious sins;
          for the words are general.
          For Christ says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e1007" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc24_47@10-12">"to all nations,"</quote>
          establishing no difference between one nation and another.
          Furthermore, we read in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Rd1e1014" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e1020">Acts 13:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e171-Qd1e1020" source="http://scta.info/resource/act13_46@23-26">"Behold, we turn to the Gentiles."</quote>
          But it is a maxim in human law that where the law has made no distinction,
          neither should we make one.
          Since, therefore, the words of Christ are general,
          they must be observed wherever the Gospel is preached —
          by announcing the truth in accordance with the institution,
          example,
          and commandment of Christ and his Apostles.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>