<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 37 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 37 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-09">May 09, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-09" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="164-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Hd1e97">Chapter 37</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e99">
          Chapter 37
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e104">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> All that has been deduced above seems to be confirmed,
          and thus it can be persuaded that it is not entirely abominable to sacrifice men to God,
          through that which God commanded Abraham,
          that he should sacrifice to Him his only son Isaac.
          Although from the words of sacred Scripture Genesis 22 chapter,
          and from the interpretation of the sacred doctors,
          it is established that God commanded this in order to show men the faith and obedience 
          of his servant Abraham,
          and to signify that mystery worthy of adoration by which God the Father offered 
          his only son Jesus in sacrifice to death for the salvation of men:
          nevertheless we can still say that God also wished to signify:
          that he would do no injury to anyone if he had commanded that he be offered to Him 
          in sacrifice.
          For God is the author of every creature,
          and all creatures are his possessions,
          as has been said.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Qd1e150">For the earth is the Lord's and the fullness thereof</quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Rd1e157">Psalm 23</ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Qd1e159">And you are the Lord of all things</quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Rd1e165">2 Maccabees 14</ref>,
          and consequently of death and life.
          Although the Lord only once requested that a human victim be offered to Him as a 
          holocaust (namely Isaac according to what Abraham understood),
          nor did He wish that very thing to be completed,
          nevertheless this was not because all things,
          even the lives of men,
          ought not to be offered to Him,
          but surely this proceeded from his immense charity toward the human race:
          and thus pitying Isaac he did not wish him to be sacrificed to Him on account of 
          the covenant which he had made with Abraham and his posterity,
          from which originates that which we have called in the second principle 
          condescending justice.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e200">
          Moreover,
          that all things ought to be owed and offered to God,
          even men in sacrifice,
          seems to be confirmed from another place of Scripture.
          For He commanded his people to sacrifice to Him every firstborn in these words:
          sanctify to me every firstborn that opens the womb among the children of Israel,
          both of men and of beasts:
          for they are all mine Exodus 13 and Numbers 8.
          Although afterwards He freed them from this precept:
          provided that they offer a pair of turtledoves or a yearling lamb,
          as is clear in Leviticus 12 and Luke 2.
          For when God commanded that all the firstborn be sacrificed to Him:
          and when He added they are all mine,
          He sufficiently showed that all things are justly owed to Him:
          and that He can without injury to anyone command that they be sacrificed to Him,
          or that they serve Him perpetually in the tabernacle of the covenant:
          in the ministry of divine worship.
          Just as today we see God sometimes snatch away the firstborn by death:
          as it pleases Him:
          which being done He inflicts injury on no one,
          as has been said.
          Thus also God wished certain ones to be bound to His service,
          namely the Tribe of Levi,
          as is clear in Numbers 3 and 8 chapter,
          and finally without injury to anyone He can at His pleasure either kill all men 
          or preserve them or assign them to any use.
          When indeed that precept sacrifice to me every firstborn wishes to be redeemed by 
          the offering of a pair of turtledoves or certain animals,
          He manifestly shows us His immense mercy,
          condescension,
          grace,
          and condescending justice.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e284">
          To these things agrees what we read in Judges 11 chapter,
          that Jephthah sacrificed his only daughter to God:
          perhaps led to believe that God had demanded a similar sacrifice from Abraham:
          and therefore thinking that it would be pleasing to Him,
          which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Rd1e302">Abulensis notes in questions 48 and 52</ref>.
          Since indeed the Israelite people was most famous and celebrated among all the nations 
          of the world on account of the admirable works and miracles performed by God among them,
          according to Eusebius in de preparatione evangelica book 11 and 12,
          where he asserts that the Greeks and Plato learned many things pertaining to religion 
          and government from the Hebrews:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Qd1e321">the wise men (he says) of the Greeks imitated 
            Jewish doctrine</quote>.
          And a little below:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Qd1e329">but no one will wonder that they stole everything 
            from the Jews and barbarians and spoke it more elegantly,
            who does not know that they were both speakers and thieves</quote>.
          Thus Eusebius.
          Therefore not absurdly might someone suspect that the custom of sacrificing men was 
          derived to all peoples:
          because they would hear that the greatest God of the Jews commanded his most beloved 
          servant Abraham to offer his own son to Him in sacrifice:
          and moreover that the most famous leader of that people,
          having obtained victory,
          sacrificed his only daughter to God:
          certainly not about to do this unless he thought it would be most pleasing to God.
          It is therefore not surprising if peoples destitute of Christian faith and instruction,
          acknowledging the immense majesty of God and His most abundant beneficence toward all,
          and that they were bound to offer sacrifice to Him from their most precious things 
          (which however how many and of what kind they are is left to their judgment),
          were persuaded to decree that from the whole people on certain days and for certain 
          necessities some,
          however innocent,
          should be sacrificed to the gods for the salvation of the entire republic.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e386">
          And thus it appears that it cannot be done briefly or in few words to make it evident 
          to infidels,
          especially our own,
          that sacrificing men to God is contrary to nature.
          And therefore it manifestly follows that it is not a just cause for waging war against 
          any kingdoms that the inhabitants sacrifice men to their gods or even eat human flesh.
          And moreover this custom inveterate among them cannot suddenly be uprooted:
          therefore the most innocent Indians are not to be blamed because at the first voice 
          of one preaching the Gospel they do not wake up.
          For they do not understand the speaker nor ought they immediately desert the religion 
          of their ancestors (not understanding what is better),
          nor is sacrificing men even innocent ones for the salvation of the entire republic 
          so contrary to natural reason that,
          as if a thing contrary to the dictate of nature,
          it should immediately be abominated.
          For this error can take its origin from probable natural reason.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e434">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> From the above it is proven that those who willingly suffer 
          themselves to be sacrificed,
          as commonly are the common people,
          and the ministers who sacrifice them to the gods at the command of princes or priests,
          have excusable and invincible ignorance,
          and their error must be pardoned even if we were to suppose there were some 
          competent judge who could punish these sins.
          But if in such sacrifices they offend God,
          He alone will punish this sin of sacrificing men.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e476">
          Nevertheless insofar as they offer sacrifices to idols,
          certainly they do not seem able to be excused by invincible ignorance according to 
          the common opinion of the doctors,
          who say that in those things which are necessary for attaining eternal salvation,
          no one has invincible ignorance.
          Since if men do what is in them,
          the Lord will give them light or the inspiration of the Holy Spirit,
          giving to each one knowledge of Himself,
          or opening the eyes of infidels through men or through angels.
          For in a similar case Saint Thomas in the questions de veritate q. 14 article 11 
          to the 1st,
          speaking of a man raised among groves,
          forests and wild beasts,
          says:
          for it pertains to divine providence to provide for each one concerning what is 
          necessary for salvation,
          provided that on his part he is not impeded.
          If indeed anyone is so nourished in the forests or among wolves,
          and follows the guidance of natural reason with an appetite for good and flight from evil,
          it is most certain to hold that God would reveal to him through internal inspiration 
          those things which are necessary for belief,
          or would direct some preacher of the faith,
          just as he sent Peter to Cornelius Acts 10.
          Thus Saint Thomas.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e538">
          He teaches the same thing on the epistle to the Romans chapter 10 lesson 3.
          That however as regards men they are excused is proven in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Rd1e546" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e1823-Dd1e201">
            l. regula, ff de iure et facti ignorantia</ref>,
          where probable error excuses from punishment.
          Which is also proven in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Rd1e557" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l4t15-d1e195">
            c. fraternitas. de frigidis et maleficis</ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Rd1e562">there Abbas teaches in the 2nd column prepositi)</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Rd1e567">the cardinal in clementinas 1. q. 39. 
            de privilegiis)</ref>.
          Moreover it is proven because the error of the people confirmed by the authority 
          of the prince makes law and excuses,
          as per the jurists in l. Barbarius Philippus ff de officio presidis,
          and in l. si arbiter. C. de sententiis et interlocutionibus omnium iudicum,
          and ff de suppellectile legata. l. 3 in finem,
          and C. de testamentis l. 3,
          and per the Canonists in c. nihil. de electione,
          and there at length Abbas 9 column and following.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-d1e592">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Since therefore among some regions of the new world either by 
          law or most ancient custom,
          and by the command of princes,
          confirmed by the authority of teachers and priests,
          and thus by public authority,
          it is held pious and holy to sacrifice men to the gods esteemed as the true God,
          it follows that this custom and common error among them makes law,
          and consequently will excuse those sacrificing:
          for he is not judged to err or be deceived who follows public law,
          as in l. nihil consensui ff de regulis iuris.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>