<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 29 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 29 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-02">May 02, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-02" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="132-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Hd1e97">Chapter 29 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e99">
          Chapter 29.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e104">
          ¶ It does not contradict the above that God killed the fathers and sons,
          both guilty and innocent,
          of Sodom and Gomorrah:
          and similarly on account of the sin of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e111"><seg>Achan</seg></name>:
          women and small infants were consumed by fire 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e121" target="http://scta.info/resource/ios7_24">Joshua 7</ref>.
          And the Tribe of Benjamin on account of the violence inflicted by a certain one of that Tribe
          upon the wife of a certain Levite:
          was utterly destroyed by the other eleven Tribes with no distinction made of age or sex.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e138">
          Nor does it contradict the above that when we pursue a just war,
          on account of the sin of a prince or leaders of a city:
          the innocent and guiltless are accustomed to be killed and plundered,
          who neither by deed nor by counsel gave cause for war or aided it.
          Since according to certain doctors:
          when a city is justly condemned to be destroyed or given over to plunder,
          we are not bound to investigate whether there are any innocents in it who merited no such thing:
          since all citizens are presumed to be enemies of the republic or prince waging just war.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e167">
          And thus soldiers in killing or plundering a city do not sin nor are they bound to make restitution:
          since killing the innocent happens (as they themselves say) per accidens and not by deliberate counsel,
          nor is the city directly captured so that they might be killed.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e181">
          ¶ But returning to the first argument,
          it truly does not contradict for a fourfold reason.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e188">
          <note type="marginal-note" place="margin-left" hand="F">
            Examples of the Old Testament are to be admired but not always to be imitated
          </note>
          First 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e193">
            because examples of the Old Testament (as was declared above in chapter <add place="margin-right" hand="AB">15.</add>
          </ref>
          are to be admired:
          but are not always to be imitated.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e205">
          ¶ Second,
          the judgments of God are inscrutable:
          therefore not because God commanded that thing to be done:
          can we also do that thing.
          For all the people of the world are God's:
          therefore He can dispose of them at will just as men dispose of their own possessions,
          and far better indeed as proper to the Creator.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e227">
          But for a human being toward his own possession,
          it is not just politically according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e233">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e234">the Philosopher</name> in book 5 of the <title>Ethics</title>
          </ref>,
          especially because human beings,
          however just they may be,
          are nevertheless going to die and are debtors of death. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e243">Hebrews 9</ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e248">It is appointed for men to die once</quote>.
          But among human beings political justice must be preserved:
          that is,
          equality of justice:
          therefore judges do not have human beings so subject to them:
          that they can punish them or kill them beyond law and right.
          For a human judge cannot judge otherwise than the law commands,
          especially the natural and divine law.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e267">
          ¶ Third,
          I respond that however much a human being may be innocent and most blameless before human beings:
          he is guilty before God by reason of original sin according to that saying 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e277">Exodus 34</ref>.
          No one is innocent before you in himself,
          that is,
          there is no one who is not obligated through his own or another's sin to you.
          Therefore God justly kills or commands to be killed whom He wishes and when He wishes.
          Just as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e290">Genesis 22</ref>.
          He commanded 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e294">Abraham</name> to sacrifice his son <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e296">Isaac</name>.
          And 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e300">He visits the sins of the parents upon the children unto the third and fourth generation</quote>:
          and He punishes the sins of children upon the fathers conversely,
          as we read 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e310">Exodus 34</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e313">
          Therefore it can never truly be said that God kills or punishes an innocent person:
          either in this life or in the future.
          But concerning a prince who punishes crimes committed against the republic,
          it is far different.
          For one innocent of a crime is guilty neither to the republic nor to the prince:
          therefore neither can princes inflict punishment on a father for a son nor a son for a father:
          nor ought a human being to be punished for a crime which he himself did not commit.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e338">
          ¶ Fourth,
          I respond that since God knows the most secret things of the heart 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e342" target="http://scta.info/resource/Isam16_7@28-33">1 Kings 16</ref>,
          and truly understands what is expedient for each one:
          sometimes He snatches away a human being because it is expedient for him to die then,
          lest he fall into sins according to what we read 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e357">Wisdom 4</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e363" source="http://scta.info/resource/sap4_11@1-12">
            He was snatched away lest wickedness change his understanding:
            or lest deceit deceive his soul
          </quote>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e370" source="http://scta.info/resource/sap4_14@1-14">
            For his soul was pleasing to God:
            therefore He hastened to lead him out from the midst of iniquities
          </quote>.
          And of this kind perhaps were the infants of Sodom,
          
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e387" target="http://scta.info/resource/num16_32">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e389">Dathan</name> and <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e391">Abiron</name>
          </ref>,
          and the children of the Canaanites whom God commanded to be killed.
          For perhaps if they had reached mature age they would have imitated their fathers' impiety.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e401">
          For children are accustomed to reproduce the vices of their parents:
          as it is said 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e407">Wisdom 12</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e409" source="http://scta.info/resource/sap12_10@10-26">
            Wicked is that nation and natural their malice:
            and because the thought of their heart could not be changed forever
          </quote>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e422" source="http://scta.info/resource/sap12_11@1-6">For it was a cursed seed from the beginning</quote>,
          and there he speaks literally of the Canaanites.
          Sometimes also the Lord does this so that those killed before mature age may suffer milder punishments:
          just as the sons of the Sodomites and Canaanites who had already reached the age of reason.
          For we ought to consider that the Lord uses mercy even toward infidels from whom He takes life in their first years:
          since by living they could turn out more wicked than their parents:
          and after death they would suffer more bitter punishments.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e479">
          Therefore whatever the Lord does concerning the state of human beings,
          even with untimely death,
          ought to be judged most righteous:
          since He ordains and disposes that thing either to something better or at least to something less evil.
          But because we are ignorant of the causes of these things:
          it seems to us that with certain ones it should be acted otherwise than it is done.
          
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e513">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e514">Boethius</name> in <title>De consolatione</title> book 4, prose 5
          </ref> condemns this ignorance in us.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e521">
            But you (he says) although you are ignorant of the cause of so great a disposition:
            nevertheless since a good ruler governs the world:
            you should not doubt that all things are done rightly
          </quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e533">
          And since none of the judges of the world has power insofar as by killing or torturing human beings,
          he might lead them to a better state:
          but rather to a worse state,
          because from being to non-being:
          indeed if death seizes such people in mortal sin:
          they are cast down to the most unhappy of all and eternal states:
          therefore it is not licit for any mere human being to punish anyone corporally (namely) with death or afflictive bodily punishment:
          for another's sin without most grave mortal offense.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e559">
          Therefore a human being killing an innocent person or punishing him corporally for another's sin acts impiously and commits a great sin:
          for we cannot suspect that a judge kills an innocent person so that it might be better for him.
          For what is better than life:
          by which we can reconcile the Lord,
          angered by our crimes,
          with tears and prayers?
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e579">
          Hence for human judges a law has been set forth in no way to be transgressed:
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e586">You shall not kill the innocent and just and fathers shall not be killed for sons</quote>,
          et cetera.
          Thus 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e592"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e593">Augustine</name> in question 8 on Joshua</ref> says 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e598">
            it is commanded to a human being to observe that a son shall not be killed for a father Deut. 24.
            But by a far more secret justice God judges,
            who is able even after death (which a human being cannot do) to liberate or to destroy
          </quote>.
          These are <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e612">Augustine's</name> words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e616">
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e618">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e619">St. Thomas</name> 2a 2ae. q. 108. article last, throughout, especially ad 3
          </ref> says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e626" source="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1830-d1e1150@25-71">
            But the hidden judgments of God by which He temporally punishes some without fault:
            human judgment cannot imitate:
            because a human being cannot comprehend the reasons of these judgments:
            so as to know what is expedient for each one:
            and therefore according to human judgment no one should ever be punished without fault with the punishment of the scourge,
            so as to be killed or mutilated or beaten
          </quote>,
          these are <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e646">St. Thomas's</name> words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e649">
          The same thing 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e651"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e652">Innocent</name> teaches in c. graue. de senten. excommunicationis</ref>.
          And thus the passages which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e659"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e660">Gratian</name> adduces in c. ecclesia</ref> and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e665">c. Turbatur. 1. q. 4</ref> and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e667">24. q. 3. in suma</ref> are to be understood.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e675">the gloss in suma there</ref>:
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e677">1. q. 4. in suma</ref>,
          where it is treated:
          whether God punishes a human being for the sin of another human being.
          What 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e686">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e687">St. Thomas</name> adduces 2a 2ae. q. 64: article 6. ad 1
          </ref> is consonant with these:
          
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e692">12. q. 100. article 8, ad 3</ref>.
          From these things it is clear how much weight the things have which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e699">jurists teach in l. aut facta ff. de penis</ref>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e704">c. dilectus filius. cl. 2º. de symonia</ref>,
          arguing against 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e709"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e710">Innocent</name> in the said c. Graue</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e717">
          That a whole community can be destroyed along with the guilty:
          from the fact that God,
          as we read in the Old Testament,
          sometimes commanded cities to be utterly destroyed and all children and women to be killed indiscriminately.
          They also adduce that Troy was destroyed:
          as if a military example proceeding from pagans ought to move Christian men.
          For to these things it is responded that the judgments of God are everywhere right and holy:
          but the judgments of human beings:
          do not always exist as just or good:
          unless they are known to accord with natural reason and divine law and equity.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e749">
          For not because princes or emperors publish or have published certain laws by which the innocent are punished corporally with the punishment of the scourge for the faults of others,
          is it therefore necessary that they not contain iniquity,
          since many unjust laws are found.
          And the will of a Prince is sometimes received as law,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e766">insti. de jure naturali. § sed et quod princi.</ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e772">
          Which will however is very changeable.
          And according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e776"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Nd1e778">the Philosopher</name> in <title>Politics</title> book 3</ref>,
          the human will is a very bad standard.
          Especially because the error of a prince makes law according to human laws,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e790">ff. de suppel. lega. l. 3. in fine</ref>.
          Therefore what we read in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Rd1e794">l. si quis. cum militibus. Cod. doctores, l. julia. Maiesta</ref> is not to be imitated,
          where it says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e803">
            but his sons,
            namely of one committing the crime of <unclear>lese</unclear> majesty,
            to whom we grant life by special imperial leniency (for they ought to perish by their father's punishment),
            in whom examples of this hereditary crime are feared
          </quote>:
          this law is truly unjust:
          as to that part 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-Qd1e821">they ought to perish by their father's punishment</quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e827">
          Therefore the words of the jurists must be attentively weighed,
          distinguished,
          and understood:
          that if the innocent are to be punished for the faults of others:
          this ought to be done with a punishment of loss,
          not of sense,
          so that a son may be rendered infamous on account of his father's crime by reason of lese majesty,
          divine or human,
          and be deprived by loss of goods:
          and by incapacity for dignities.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e421-d1e848">
          But never ought an innocent person to be punished by human judgment otherwise by reason of another's crime:
          and one acting otherwise is guilty of the gravest crime before God.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>