<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 24 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 24 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-17">Apr 17, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-17" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="109-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Hd1e97">Chapter 24 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e99">
          Chapter 24.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e104">
          Third, 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e108">Augustine of Ancona</name> 
          argues that infidels are judged and condemned by the Church. 
          Indeed if he understands that the crimes of infidels are punished by the Church with 
          contentious jurisdiction: 
          he is manifestly in error as is clear from what has been said above. 
          But if he understands that the Church judges and condemns pagans with Catholic judgment 
          insofar as it judges by the certainty of faith which it has that they are to be consigned 
          to eternal fire: 
          we do not deny this. 
          For outside the Church there is no salvation. 
          As <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e132">24. q. 1, c. alienus</ref>.
          For it does not judge or condemn them with the judgment of contentious jurisdiction, 
          so that it punishes them for crimes outside the six cases, 
          which we have already begun to enumerate. 
          We confess that if they should awaken, 
          they can be absolved from sins by the Church through the power of the keys.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e148">
          That Augustine adds that the Church has judicial power over infidels: 
          understood absolutely and generally this is false, 
          as has been proven very often above. 
          For it is necessary to distinguish whether infidels are subject to Christian princes, 
          and what crimes they commit: 
          and whether they are Jews: 
          or Saracens or heretics or schismatics or infidels, 
          who possess provinces which formerly belonged to the Christian Church. 
          Whether they harm the Christian people with incursions. 
          For these cases must be distinguished as is sufficiently clear from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e184"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e185">Augustine</name> 
            in his book <title>On the True Religion</title></ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e190">
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e192">This Catholic Church, 
            he says, 
            widely and broadly spread throughout the whole world uses all who err for her advancement 
            and for their correction when they have been willing to awaken. 
            For she uses the Gentiles as matter for her work: 
            heretics for the proof of her doctrine: 
            schismatics for the evidence of her stability: 
            Jews for comparison of her beauty. 
            Therefore she invites some: 
            she excludes some: 
            she shuts out others: 
            yet to all she gives the power of participating in the grace of God whether they are still 
            to be formed: 
            or to be reformed or to be gathered again, 
            or to be admitted, etc.</quote>
          Thus Augustine.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e227">
          By relating these words individually: 
          they comprehend all the cases touched upon above: 
          For those words <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e235">for the matter of her work</quote>: 
          refer to the Gentiles: 
          to whom the word of God is to be preached by the Church. 
          For this is the proper office of the Church. 
          Again that word "invites" more clearly signifies that the Church does not compel: 
          but rather allures and leads men to faith with holy examples and persuasive reasons. 
          Similarly those words <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e258">"to be formed"</quote> 
          still signify that they have not yet been formed nor instructed in the word of God and 
          Catholic doctrine: 
          which does not pertain to heretics, 
          but to those who have not yet received the faith.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e271">
          For concerning those (namely) heretics (he says) 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e273">"she excludes"</quote> 
          and <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e278">"to be reformed"</quote>. 
          By which words he signifies that heretics and also schismatics who do not repent, 
          are to be ejected from the Church by excommunication (namely) by spiritual penalty. 
          But if they persist contumaciously in error, 
          they are to be consumed by flames. 
          That word <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e299">"to be reformed"</quote> 
          signifies that Augustine is speaking of those, 
          who having been correctly formed were afterwards deformed by errors: 
          and the judgment by which they are to be reformed.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e312">
          Those words <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e314">"she excludes others"</quote> 
          can be understood of infidels, 
          who do not pertain to the jurisdiction of the pope, 
          nor does the pontiff punish their crimes as I taught above: 
          since they do not at all harm the Christian commonwealth. 
          But if they perpetrate even horrible sins: 
          they harm no one except themselves, 
          and therefore they have God alone as their avenger.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e337">
          But those words: 
          "she goes before others": 
          and "to be admitted": 
          demonstrate the benignity of the Church prepared namely to receive the Jews even if 
          they committed the horrible crime of killing Christ the Lord. 
          For if the Church receives in her bosom those guilty of so great a crime: 
          much more will she receive pagans whose sin is less.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e355">
          But also those words "to all she gives the power of participating in the grace of God." 
          The words are addressed to the pagan namely if he should receive the Christian faith: 
          to the heretic by compelling him to be reconciled to the Church: 
          to the schismatic if he should conform himself to the orthodox: 
          to the Jews if with opened eyes they have understood the truth of Christ and their own 
          ignorance. 
          And thus the Church presents to all a certain hope of their salvation.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e384">
          <add place="margin-left" hand="F">In what manner all the faithful look to the judgment of the Church</add>
          Therefore all infidels of whatever kind or species they may be look to the judgment 
          of the Church: 
          but very differently. 
          For infidels who have never heard the faith pertain to the Church with respect to 
          preaching and conversion procured by her ministers: 
          and because they can if they wish become her members.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e408">
          This is what 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e410">Saint Thomas in the 3rd part, q. 8, art. 3, ad 1</ref> 
          writes, that <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e415">although infidels are not actually of the Church: 
            they are nevertheless within ecclesiastical power. 
            Which indeed is founded on two things: 
            first and principally on the power of Christ which is sufficient for the salvation of the 
            whole human race. 
            Secondarily on the freedom of will: 
            by which any man with the help of divine grace can, 
            having heard the doctrine of Christ, 
            become his member</quote>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e438">
          And thus it is clear that not all infidels are under the judicial power of the Church; 
          as <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e444">Augustine of Ancona</name> 
          has opined.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e450">
          Nevertheless we concede that all infidels may be occasionally of fruitful utility to the Church, 
          for the reasons mentioned above from the words of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e458"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e459">Augustine</name> 
            in <title>On the True Religion</title></ref>: 
          as also 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e466">Ancona says in his fourth argument</ref>. 
          But in truth his teaching is quite confused in this part just as is the teaching of Innocent 
          from whom he received it almost formally, 
          and therefore his arguments are not to be much heeded. 
          And thus having satisfied as we believe the arguments of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e491">Augustine of Ancona</name> 
          together with those of Innocent, 
          we must pass on to the other cases in which the Church brings into act the contentious 
          jurisdiction which it has in habit against infidels.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e503">
          <add place="margin-left" hand="E">Third case</add>
          Therefore the third case is of this kind if they are blasphemers against Christ or against 
          the saints or against the Christian religion maliciously and knowingly and contemptuously: 
          speaking out of hatred and contempt of Christian truth. 
          For the Church ought neither to ignore nor to bear this as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e521">we taught above in chapters 15 and 16</ref>: 
          indeed rather it ought to take up arms against them.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e529">
          But if pagans should speak blasphemous things about the Christian religion not out of 
          contempt and hatred of the religion: 
          but in anger at Christians by whom they had been badly treated and affected with injuries 
          without legitimate cause as happened among the Indians in the province of Xalisci, 
          where in mockery of the priests and Christians the Indians raised up a small cake of dough 
          with both hands imitating the custom of Christian priests who when celebrating Mass 
          display the body of our Lord Jesus Christ to the people. 
          Such people are not blasphemers: 
          for they are ignorant of what they do nor do they know that what the Christian priests 
          display is to be adored as the body of Christ.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e582">
          Nor do they do this out of contempt, 
          but from desire for vengeance: 
          when they imitate with derision the action of those whom they had experienced as most 
          savage enemies. 
          For they believe that the religion accords with the life of most impious men: 
          from whom it is scarcely believable how much pitiable calamity they have received: 
          how much savage tyranny they have endured.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e605">
          Indeed even if the word of God had been announced and preached to them they would not be 
          called blasphemers, 
          if they spoke impiously about the Christian religion: 
          since two or three pious men preached the word of God to them: 
          but a thousand of the same profession, 
          with whom the preachers associated familiarly: 
          defamed the Christian religion by their impious life, 
          inhumanity, 
          savagery, 
          and pride. 
          These by the best right are to be called blasphemers according to that of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e631"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e632">Paul</name> 
            to the Romans chapter 2</ref>. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e638">Through you the name of the Lord is blasphemed 
            among the Gentiles</quote>. 
          Again <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e644">Peter 2, chapter 2</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e646">through you the way of truth is blasphemed</quote>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e652">
          Adversaries object that the worship of idols is blasphemy against God according to what is 
          noted by <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e658"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e659">Saint Thomas</name> 
            in 2a 2ae, q. 94, art. 3</ref>: 
          And that therefore idolaters can be attacked with war according to what is written by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e666"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e667">Saint Thomas</name> 
            in 2a 2ae, q. 10, art. 8</ref>. 
          But <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e675">in truth Saint</name> 
          Thomas does not mean to signify absolutely that blasphemy is a just cause of war against 
          idolaters. 
          For it has already been proven above, 
          that if idolatry is blasphemy: 
          nevertheless it does not pertain to the Church to punish idolaters. 
          He speaks only of those, 
          who knowingly and maliciously with deliberate counsel are blasphemers against Christ, 
          and impede the preaching of the Gospel: 
          and lest anyone should receive the faith. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e706">The words of Saint Thomas in the said article 8</ref> 
          I shall subjoin <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e713">They are to be compelled by the faithful, 
            he says, 
            if the faculty is present, 
            that they not impede the faith either by blasphemies or by evil persuasions or even by 
            open persecutions</quote>. 
          Thus he.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e725">
          But what sort of blasphemy this is he explains there 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e729">Cajetan in his commentaries</ref>. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Qd1e734">Consider carefully, 
            he says, 
            the just cause of war against infidels and of compelling them lest (namely) they impede 
            the faith in any of three ways, 
            namely either by blasphemies speaking evil of Christ Jesus: 
            or of his saints or of his Church. 
            Or by persuasions leading our people to infidelity or by persecutions</quote>. 
          Thus he.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e763">
          Whence it sufficiently appears concerning what blasphemy the 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e767">holy doctor</name> 
          speaks there which deserves to be avenged by war: 
          it is not idolatry: 
          but contumelious words against Christ our Lord maliciously uttered: 
          with such intention that the Catholic faith should not be received. 
          But truly for blasphemy, 
          which results against God from sacrilegious rites and ceremonies for the observance of the 
          law or sect of any infidels whatsoever even if they are idolaters (which is truly blasphemy) 
          as <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e792"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e793">Saint Thomas</name> 
            rightly says in the above q. 94, article 3</ref>. 
          they cannot be warred against.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e801">
          This is most clearly proven. 
          The Jews observing and exercising today the ceremonies of the law of Moses without doubt 
          commit blasphemy against God: 
          similarly the Saracens observing the law of the most filthy Mohammed and both hate the law 
          of Christ and the whole Catholic religion as execrable and evil and this is known to the 
          Catholic Church: 
          and yet the Church does not wage war on them nor punishes them even when they are subjects, 
          therefore not every blasphemy of infidels against God does the Church punish.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-d1e832">
          But certainly it would be otherwise if the Jews or Saracens in contempt of our religion 
          should crucify a man or perpetrate some similar deed: 
          it would be blasphemy which would impede the propagation of the faith and those similar 
          to these are to be pursued with war. 
          Which the most learned theologian 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Rd1e849"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e355-Nd1e850">Francis of Vitoria</name> 
            teaches most learnedly in his lucubrations on 2a 2ae, q. 10, article 8</ref>. 
          From which the error of the adversaries is sufficiently refuted.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>