<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 40 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 40 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-22">April 22, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
Published under a 
<ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-21" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="176-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-Hd1e97">Chapter 40</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#P" n="176-r"/>
          Chapter 40
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e106">
          And indeed since the word of God uproots idolatry and every vice,
          and softens the hearts of any nation,
          however savage,
          by its wondrous power:
          the word of God will be of much greater effect among the Indians than among any other peoples,
          since they are of teachable intellect and distinguished by excellent disposition for receiving the faith 
          above very many nations of the known world,
          gentle,
          meek,
          unarmed.
          Experience itself has taught this,
          and I,
          for the glory of Christ,
          what I have seen with my own eyes for fifty years,
          I hand down to posterity with sincere spirit.
          The Spanish penetrated with truly immense daring into this new world of lands unheard of in previous centuries.
          Where,
          contrary to the intention of the prince,
          they perpetrated enormous and unprecedented crimes:
          they killed innumerable myriads of people;
          they burned villages;
          they drove away herds;
          they plundered cities;
          and without any even seemingly probable cause,
          they committed abominable outrages with savage cruelty against the wretched people,
          cruel,
          rapacious,
          seditious.
          Could they have knowledge of the true God to whose worship the religious exhorted the Indians?
          Nevertheless,
          behold the power of the word of God and the teachableness of the Indian people;
          hear the mercy of Christ whose adorable name the most impious men defamed by their crimes.
          The Indians received Christian truth most willingly,
          which the truly religious receive as a great miracle.
          They followed,
          however,
          the sacred men and religious monks announcing to them evangelical truth.
          Woe is me,
          what if those most gentle sheep had that great teacher Paul,
          or someone who wished to imitate Paul's divine virtue:
          how great and what sort of obedience would they render to their Lord?
          How abundant would be the spiritual harvest and the fruit of divine rejoicing?
          If they do not spurn the gospel which the preachers themselves,
          which is lamentable,
          sometimes defame by their morals:
          what if men,
          emulators of apostolic virtue,
          penetrated alone into those provinces whose inhabitants received the faith of Christ despite the worst examples 
          and the crimes of savage cruelty which the Spanish perpetrated against them?
          Whatever I shall say about the faith of the Indians,
          I have seen with my own eyes,
          not in one place only or in only one nation,
          but indeed in many.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e273">
          They venerate the holy sacraments of the Catholic Church and receive them with great signification of piety;
          if,
          because of a shortage of priests,
          they cannot be aided by the sacraments,
          these most sincere people grow pale,
          weep,
          grieve,
          lament.
          Again,
          at the time of death,
          you see in them wondrous care for their salvation and soul,
          and a manifest sign in them of eternal predestination,
          which is characteristic of Christians.
          And would that there were more among us who were troubled by such cares.
          Finally,
          they seek the sacraments with great solicitude of spirit both for themselves and for their children.
          Concerning which matter I shall discuss more broadly in the second part of this apology.
          From which we can gather that if probable hope can be had concerning all idolaters 
          who labor only from ignorance of divine things,
          that having heard the proclamation of Christ,
          they will awake from those and similar vices,
          we ought doubtless to conceive more probable hope concerning the conversion of those nations of the world,
          since experience has taught us so many and such great things about the goodness and teachableness of their intellect.
          Therefore,
          in recalling our brothers from this error,
          let us follow the examples of the apostles and apostolic men;
          let us uproot idolatry and the worship of demons 
          and other sins by the word of God and evangelical doctrine in that manner in which Christ commanded it to be manifested,
          with the example of life,
          not however by war,
          for malice does not remove but propagates malice.
          Therefore the sixth case is clear,
          concerning whose matter we began to treat above in chapter 24,
          in which we said the Church can reduce the habit of coercive jurisdiction 
          which it has in potency to act with respect to any infidels—namely,
          that it might free the innocent from unjust oppression.
          The truth and definition of this matter stands in these terms—namely,
          that although it pertains to the Church,
          on account of the fullest power conferred upon it by God,
          to impede the aforesaid injuries committed against the innocent jurisdictionally,
          and in the case where those committing them pertinaciously resist,
          to punish them also:
          nevertheless,
          if,
          having first tried any lawful and honest human means,
          such inconveniences to the innocent cannot be obviated except through war,
          one must utterly cease from it,
          and dissimulate with both those doing and suffering such things.
          First,
          because of two evils,
          if both cannot be avoided,
          the lesser must be chosen according to right reason.
          Second,
          because it is manifest that more innocent persons will perish than those who are proposed to be freed,
          and yet we are forbidden by the strictest negative precept to kill the innocent in any case.
          Third,
          because in war the innocent cannot be distinguished from the guilty.
          Fourth,
          because such a remedy has already lost the nature of justice or virtue.
          Fifth,
          on account of the common utility which is concerned with avoiding the temporal overthrow of the entire republic,
          and especially the spiritual loss.
          Sixth,
          on account of the probable hope and vehement presumption which is had concerning their conversion 
          through the preaching of the faith,
          as the longest experience has taught,
          as is now clear.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e455">
          To which we add this universal reason—namely,
          lest God and his holy Church,
          without which he wishes men to be saved and to come to the knowledge of truth,
          remain frustrated.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e467">
          And thus we conclude that six cases are possible in which the Church and its head,
          the supreme vicar of Christ,
          by right of his apostolate,
          can place in practical act the contentious jurisdiction which it has habitually—that is,
          exercise it with respect to any infidels according to what has been declared above.
          And this is the second mode of that distinction by which we said in chapter 15 
          that the Church can exercise temporal jurisdiction concerning infidels.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e492">
          There is a third mode of the aforesaid distinction of the Church exercising temporal jurisdiction 
          in or concerning infidels,
          not however just any kind,
          but that which among jurists is called voluntary.
          Jurists call voluntary jurisdiction that which cannot be exercised against an unwilling person,
          but only against a willing one;
          therefore it is called voluntary jurisdiction.
          The text enumerates the acts of voluntary jurisdiction in l. actus ff de feriis,
          namely:
          to emancipate,
          to adopt,
          etc.
          And it extends even to foreigners who are not subjects,
          and concerning it is treated in l. omnes ff. de officio proconsulis 
          and in capitulo ultimo de feriis.
          The pope has jurisdiction of this kind concerning all infidels of the entire world 
          as the universal vicar of Jesus Christ,
          to whom it pertains to send the gospel to all nations of the entire world through his ministers and apostolic legates.
          This jurisdiction is called voluntary or similar to voluntary because infidels 
          who have never professed the faith are not to be compelled by the Roman Pontiff,
          but are to be exhorted and peacefully and graciously invited;
          if they are unwilling to receive,
          they have God alone as judge,
          for those who have not believed are reserved for divine judgment,
          according to that passage in Mark at the end:
          "but whoever does not believe will be condemned."
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e569">
          If,
          however,
          through baptism and faith they enter the sheepfold of Christ,
          then the Roman Pontiff has contentious jurisdiction over them in habit only,
          according to what is read in capitulo nouit de iudiciis,
          and we have treated above at length.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e582">
          Therefore I call this jurisdiction voluntary or similar to voluntary.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e589">
          First,
          because although the duty of preaching the gospel pertains to the pope,
          the infidels to whom it is preached are not compelled to receive it,
          but it is left to their free will,
          since to believe is an act of the will,
          as was said above.
          Since,
          therefore,
          that power of preaching the gospel which the Church has must be adapted and suited to the voluntary reception of the faith 
          as means to end—for the same right and disposition is in one of connected things as in the other,
          as 1 quaestione 3 c. si quis obiecerit and 3 q. 6 c. hoc quippe,
          and "the accessory follows the nature of its principal,"
          by the rule accessorium de regulis iuris libro 6—it follows that such power can be called voluntary power or jurisdiction,
          or similar to voluntary,
          according to the manner of jurists,
          who,
          with respect to those over whom they have it to exercise,
          because they must be not unwilling but voluntary,
          call it voluntary.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e641">
          Second,
          and this is a juridical reason quite adaptable to the proposition:
          since one of the acts of voluntary jurisdiction is assigned to be adopting someone as a son who is not a son,
          as if art imitates nature,
          as in institutis de adoptionibus § foeminae in the gloss,
          and 
<ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-Rd1e661">Saint Thomas 4 sententiarum distinctio 42 quaestione 2 articulo 1</ref> 
and 
<ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-Rd1e667">3 sententiarum distinctio 10 quaestione 2 articulo 1 quaestiuncula 1a</ref> 
and 
<ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-Rd1e670">3 pars quaestione 3 articulo 5 ad 2m</ref>,
          and this indeed is a certain voluntary acceptance of some foreign person who is not in the power of the adopter as a son,
          by which the adopted one is admitted to share in the inheritance of the adopting father,
          which indeed must be voluntary on the part of the adopted one,
          l. Neque. ff de adoptionibus.
          Infidels are also foreign and outside persons,
          since they exist entirely outside the doors of the Church,
          and thus are not of its forum as to coercive jurisdiction,
          as has been proved at length above;
          it follows that if the Church wishes to adopt them as sons of God,
          this must be with their voluntary consent,
          according to that passage in John 1:
          "He gave them power to become sons of God,"
          that is,
          he left it in their power of free will that,
          if they wish,
          they may become sons of God.
          Whence Ambrose says:
          "Christ chose a voluntary soldier,"
          15, q. 1, c. Non est.
          Whence,
          by voluntarily receiving the sacrament of baptism,
          they are made adoptive sons of God,
          according to that passage in Romans 8:
          "You have received the spirit of adoption of sons of God,
          in which we cry Abba Father."
          Since,
          however,
          this power which is in the Church of preaching the gospel throughout the world,
          which is nothing other than by the teaching of faith to persuade and invite foreign nations—namely,
          infidels—that it may please them to be adopted as sons of God,
          is known to be founded,
          after the virtue and grace of Christ,
          only upon the voluntary acceptance of the infidels themselves,
          according to Saint Thomas 3 pars q. 8 articulo 3 ad 1m,
          and besides this and the six cases related above,
          nothing pertains to the Church concerning judging those who are outside,
          as was most fully proved in the preceding matters,
          it follows that such power or jurisdiction or right of preaching can be called voluntary 
          in likeness to that which jurists call voluntary,
          although on the part of the Church and the supreme vicar of Christ it is preceptive and necessary,
          as appeared above in a certain place.
          And with respect to this necessity imposed on the supreme pontiff by Christ,
          because he has a precept to take care that the gospel be preached throughout the entire world,
          the whole world is assigned to him as a parish,
          with Chrysostom as authority,
          super ioanem homilia 87:
          "For when Christ had communicated great things to Peter,
          he entrusted to him the care of the world."
          These are his words.
          And thus the supreme pontiff is curator of the entire world.
          Whence Bernard in libro 2o de consideratione ad Eugenium says there:
          "A sign indeed of singular power and of the pontificate of Peter,
          through which he received to be governed not one ship as each of the others his own,
          but the very world itself,"
          etc. These are Bernard's words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e828">
          And concerning this voluntary jurisdiction,
          which is founded in the preaching of the faith and the voluntary conversion of nations,
          Pope Leo speaks more expressly in sermon 3 of his ordination,
          among other excellences of Peter,
          thus:
          "From the whole world one Peter is chosen,
          who is placed before both the calling of all nations and all the apostles and all the fathers of the Church,"
          etc. These are his words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e848">
          And thus the Roman Pontiff is the first of all heralds of evangelical truth and the prince of the calling of all infidel nations,
          and also the prince of the entire universal Christian Church and of all who are counted as members of the Church.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e865">
          To these accords what Bernard says in the aforesaid book 2 de consideratione ad eugenium:
          "Go forth into the field of your Lord,
          go forth into the world,
          for the field is the world,
          and that has been entrusted to you.
          Go forth into it not as lord but as steward to see and approve whence you must render an account.
          Go forth,
          I say,
          with certain steps of your intent solicitude and solicitous intention,"
          etc. These are his words.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e894">
          And thus the supreme pontiff is not lord of the world but steward of the supreme prince and universal lord of the entire world,
          insofar as in his field,
          that is,
          in the entire world,
          that is,
          in all nations,
          he may plant and build with the cultivation of his apostolic doctrine virtues and uproot vices,
          according to the prophecy of Jeremiah 1.
          To which also pertains what Bernard in book 4 of the same work calls the Roman Pontiff teacher of the nations,
          thus saying:
          "Henceforth it is fitting that you be the form of justice,
          the mirror of sanctity,
          the example of piety,
          the assertor of truth,
          the defender of the faith,
          the teacher of nations,
          the leader of Christians,"
          etc.
          Therefore the vicar of Christ is the primary and par excellence teacher of all men,
          to whose definition,
          pertaining both to morals and to faith,
          one must stand,
          according to the words of Jerome to Pope Damasus,
          which are read in c. haec est fides 24 q. 1.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e942">
          From this obligation,
          therefore,
          by which the supreme pontiff must go forth into the field of his Lord,
          that is,
          into the world,
          to teach through his suitable ministers,
          fit preachers of the faith,
          all nations,
          he is known to be head,
          curate,
          and pastor of all men of the world,
          whether faithful or infidels,
          and as to this,
          all men are his subjects:
          the faithful indeed absolutely as to spiritual matters;
          the infidels,
          however,
          concerning whom there is now discussion,
          according to the nature or hope of voluntary jurisdiction in the manner in which we have spoken,
          and no more,
          because he is the form of justice and established in truth,
          as is now clear from what has been said,
          and we have shown more copiously elsewhere.
          And these things are gathered from the mind of blessed Chrysostom,
          expounding that passage,
          "I will give you the keys,"
          etc.,
          Matthew 16,
          homilia 51 in opere inperfecto:
          "But this Peter,
          Christ placed over the entire world so that he might sow everywhere on earth the revelation both of his teacher and of his son."
          These are his words.
          To these also accord those words which the Church sings in the feast of blessed Peter:
          "You are the shepherd of the sheep,
          prince of the apostles;
          to you God has handed over all the kingdoms of the world."
          From which it appears that the supreme pontiff is prelate,
          king,
          and pastor not only of those sheep which have already entered the sheepfold of Christ through holy baptism,
          that is,
          of Christians,
          and over their kingdoms as to spiritual matters,
          but also of all those which are outside and have not yet touched the doors of the Church,
          that is,
          of infidels,
          who nevertheless are to be allured and led by blandishments through the proclamation of Christ 
          that they may enter the sheepfold of the Church,
          according to that passage in John 10:
          "I have other sheep which are not of this fold,
          and I must bring them also."
          Which indeed are all infidels,
          especially those who have never heard anything of the faith of Christ 
          and who have not maliciously imposed impediments to preaching on account of hatred of the faith,
          as was said above in chapters 5 and 3.
          Moreover,
          over these sheep the supreme pontiff only and precisely is accustomed to use,
          and ought to use,
          jurisdiction or authority entirely voluntary,
          not however contentious or coercive,
          as has been said;
          but over those others,
          both—namely,
          voluntary and contentious,
          even to judging concerning temporal matters in the case where it is expedient for the promotion,
          direction,
          and conservation of spiritual matters,
          according as is the common opinion of theologians and jurists,
          and according to the truth.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e566-d1e1072">
          Thus,
          therefore,
          it is clear that to the pastoral office,
          principate,
          prelacy,
          governance,
          and kingdom of the vicar of Jesus Christ,
          God and man,
          good shepherd,
          king of kings,
          and lord of lords,
          pertain all the kingdoms of the world and all men of the entire world,
          with the aforesaid distinction,
          just as in our probative treatise concerning the right of principate of our kings of Spain 
          over that Indian world we have proved at length,
          and still more broadly in our other works.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>