<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 15 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] — English Translation</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 15 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] — English Translation</title>
          <date when="2024-11-14">Nov 14, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-11-14" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="74-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Hd1e97">Chapter 15 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e99">
          Chapter 15.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e104">
          ¶ Up to this point we have taught that neither the Church nor Christian princes
          can punish pagans,
          even if they are liable for the most serious crimes.
          Now, for a complete understanding of this treatise,
          I will set forth six cases in which the Church can punish pagans,
          and I will also respond in passing to the things that Sepúlveda teaches
          near the end of his second argument.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e132">
          Before all else, it must be supposed that the Church can exercise temporal
          jurisdiction over unbelievers in three ways.
          The third member may be seen
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e142">below in chapter 37.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e146">
          First, when unbelievers are subjects of the Church —
          both in disposition and in act —
          or of some member of the Church,
          such as a Christian prince.
          Unbelievers of this kind are heretics,
          concerning whom we have argued
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e156">above in chapter 7</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e161">will argue below.</ref>
          For these, having once received the Catholic truth,
          must be compelled to return to the fold of Christ.
          Unbelievers of this kind are also Jews and Moors
          who are subjects of Christian kings.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e173">
          Over these, since they are subject in both law and fact,
          the Church can enact laws —
          which is sufficiently proven from the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e179">title on Jews and Saracens</ref>
          and from the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e184">title on heretics</ref>
          in the book of the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e189">Decretals,</ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e191">the Sixth,</ref>
          and the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e193">Clementines;</ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e197">c. de iudaeis, paganis et templis eorum;</ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e202">c. de hereticis et apostatis.</ref>
          And in the Spanish language we have very many laws
          promulgated by the Castilian kings concerning Jews and Moors.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e211">
          And thus contentious jurisdiction can be exercised over these
          — that is, even against their will —
          as explained by the doctors in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e218" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e4101-d1e1235">l. inter stipulantem. §. 1. ff. de verborum
          obligatione.</ref>
          For the Church does this legitimately,
          since they are subject in both act and disposition
          to Christian princes, that is, to members of the Church.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e233">
          ¶ Second, the Church holds only in disposition contentious jurisdiction
          over other unbelievers,
          so that it may bring this into act when the occasion arises
          or while the cause subsists —
          but not otherwise,
          on account of the ten reasons adduced above,
          and especially
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e248">according to that word of Paul:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e250">"What business is it of mine to judge those
          who are outside?"</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e256">
          Now these unbelievers are those who have never professed the faith of Christ
          through baptism —
          of whatever religion, worship, rite, or sect they may be —
          provided they are not Jews,
          and have their own kingdoms separate from Christian kingdoms,
          so that they are not subjects of the Church
          or of any of its members.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e274">
          We said
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e276">"provided they are not Jews,"</quote>
          because Jews, on account of the crime committed by them —
          killing Jesus Christ our Lord —
          are by right servants of the Church,
          as stated in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e287">c. etsi iudaeos: de iudaeis 161.</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e291">"Those whom their own fault has consigned to perpetual
          servitude, let Christian piety receive and sustain"</quote>
          and so forth.
          But in fact it was
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e300">Constantine who subjected them to servitude,
          according to the gloss in c. consuluit de iudeis.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e306">
          Nevertheless, they are not properly slaves,
          nor can works be imposed on them against their will,
          nor should they be oppressed contrary to justice and right,
          as stated in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e314">c. qui sincera. 45. distinctio</ref>
          and in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e319">c. sicut iudaei. de iudicii.</ref>
          We also said that unbelievers are not subjects of the Church
          but have separate kingdoms —
          because in this respect one and the same reasoning applies
          to all unbelievers of whatever region or rite they may be,
          on the basis of the reasons set forth above.
          For no one will be able to assign any rational basis for a distinction.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e344">
          ¶ Over all unbelievers, therefore,
          the Church can exercise contentious jurisdiction
          in six cases.
          <note place="margint-right" hand="E">
            Six cases in which the Church can exercise contentious jurisdiction
            over all unbelievers.
          </note>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e356">
          ¶ First, if they unjustly possess kingdoms
          from which they have unjustly despoiled the Christian people —
          especially if Christians live among them.
          Of this kind are the Byzantine Empire,
          Rhodes, Hungary, Belgrade, and Africa,
          all of which once worshipped Christ.
          For since by holding those kingdoms
          they inflict upon us a continuous injury,
          the Church can bring into act
          the jurisdiction it holds in disposition over them,
          in order to recover through the compulsion of war
          what is its own.
          For no other remedy remains.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e390">
          And it is about unbelievers of this kind that
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e394">Hostiensis speaks in c. quod super his.
          de voto,</ref>
          and the other doctors there.
          And
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e399">Oldradus in consilium 72.</ref>
          And
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e404">Albericus on the Rubric of c.
          de paganis et eorum templis.</ref>
          Where Hostiensis and his followers say that unbelievers,
          if they do not acknowledge the lordship of the Church,
          are unworthy of all lordship and jurisdiction.
          And
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e418">Hostiensis understands this of the jurisdiction
          and empire</ref>
          that infidel princes hold over lands that were once Christian,
          and over the Christians dwelling among them —
          or where the whole people or some part of the people
          has converted to Christ,
          while the prince persists still in his blindness and unbelief.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e438">
          So interprets
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e440">Antonius Butrius in his commentary on c. quod super
          of the Decretals,</ref>
          reconciling the opinion of
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e447">Hostiensis and Innocent IV</ref>
          in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e452">"This conclusion of Innocent is confirmed by Hostiensis,
          who moderates it: so that unbelievers could have
          jurisdiction over Christians
          when the unbelievers acknowledge the jurisdiction
          of the Church.
          For such persons can have,
          and by the Church's tolerance can hold,
          lordships and rights"</quote>
          and so forth.
          From which it is clearly and plainly evident
          that Hostiensis understood the matter to concern
          infidel lords who have under their power certain Christians —
          that they must acknowledge the lordship and jurisdiction of the Church
          in order to be worthy of such principality or lordship
          (that is) over the faithful.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e484">
          And these things accord with the teaching of
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e488">the holy doctor, the divine Thomas,
          Secunda Secundae q. 10. art. 10,</ref>
          that the Church,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e493" source="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1324-d1e2304@65-225">"although it could by its own right remove through sentence or decree
          the right of lordship or rule
          that infidel princes hold over Christians —
          because by reason of their unbelief they deserve to lose
          power over the faithful who are transferred
          into the children of God —
          nevertheless tolerates them
          in order to avoid scandal."</quote>
          These are the words of Saint Thomas.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e512">
          And so the opinion of Hostiensis is to be understood
          not indiscriminately of all unbelievers,
          but of those who were of his time —
          namely when an infidel prince holds Christians under his dominion,
          or has usurped Christian kingdoms.
          For these seem to be bound to acknowledge
          the lordship of the Church.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e531">
          But concerning others —
          such as our Indians,
          who have neither usurped Christian kingdoms
          nor rule over Christians,
          nor had ever before our age heard the name of this our world —
          it is absurd that they should be bound
          to acknowledge the lordship of the Church,
          or else be deprived of their principality,
          since they have no way to divine this
          without the teaching of the faith.
          For if the opinion of Hostiensis were understood otherwise,
          it would itself be heretical —
          as we will prove at length elsewhere —
          and great dangers in the world
          and intolerable absurdities would follow.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e560">
          ¶ Second, the Church actually exercises jurisdiction over pagans
          when in provinces that were once under Christian rule
          they practice idolatry,
          or infect a region with abominable and unspeakable vices against nature.
          For since in those places the true sacrifice
          of the body and blood of Christ has been consecrated,
          and pure worship has been offered to the true God,
          and the sacred sacraments have been administered —
          concerning which see
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e583">Saint Thomas, Tertia Pars, q. 63, art. 2, 3, 4,
          6, in c.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e589">
          Whose end it is that human beings,
          rendering glory and honor to the true God,
          should subject themselves entirely to him in body and soul —
          according to
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e597">Thomas, Secunda Secundae, q. 93, art. 27, c.,</ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e599">Book 3, c. 119, Contra Gentiles —</ref>
          it is by no means reasonable that the Church,
          if it has the power,
          should tolerate such things,
          since they redound to the reproach and dishonor
          of the Christian name.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e619">
          And this no Christian ought to dissemble,
          as stated in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e623">c. in nonnullis. de iudaeis,</ref>
          where it says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e628">"we ought not to dissemble the reproach
          of him who has blotted out our reproaches for us,"</quote>
          and in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e635" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e640">l. Manichaeos c. de hereticis,</ref>
          it is said:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e640" source="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e104-d1e151@6-17">"we desire that a public crime
          be what is committed against the divine religion:
          it is an injury inflicted upon all"</quote>
          and so forth.
          And
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qggj111" source="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e59-d1e116@30-38">"public law consists in sacred matters and in priests,"</quote>
          as stated in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e656" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e236-Qggj111">l. 1. ius publicum, ff. de iustitia et iure.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e659">
          This case together with the preceding one is specifically stated by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e663">Innocent in c. maiores. de baptismo,
          at the end,</ref>
          where, speaking of the Saracens, he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e669">"that they are not to be attacked by war by the Church,
          if they neither defile the land of Christians with their filth
          nor assail the persons of Christians"</quote>
          and so forth.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e679">
          Innocent took that word "filth" from sacred scripture,
          where it chiefly signifies idolatry
          or another unclean abomination,
          especially against nature.
          For so we read in 3 Kings 15
          of King Asa,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e692">"that he removed the effeminate men from the land
          and cleansed all the filth of the idols
          which his fathers had made."</quote>
          And in Apocalypse, chapter 22:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e701">"he who does harm, let him do harm still:
          and he who is in filth, let him be made filthy still."</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e710">
          And thus must be understood what the same Innocent holds
          in c. quod super his de voto, 1st column,
          <note place="margin-right" hand="F">How Innocent is to be understood.</note>
          where he believes that
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e721">"if a gentile who has no law except that of nature
          acts against the law of nature,
          he can lawfully be punished by the pope."</quote>
          And a little further on he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e731">"I say the same (he states) if they worship idols.
          For it is natural to worship one sole God the Creator
          and not creatures."</quote>
          So far he.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e741">
          This must be supplemented and understood as follows:
          if the provinces where those sins are committed
          were once inhabited by a Christian people —
          otherwise more absurdities would follow than from the teaching of Hostiensis —
          if Innocent were to understand this absolutely
          of all parts of the world
          whose inhabitants had not yet received the faith
          nor had the Church been founded among them.
          First, because that would be contrary to what we proved above
          by ten effective arguments.
          Second, because Innocent does not prove his assertion
          but merely cites the fact that the Sodomites,
          who sinned against the law of nature,
          were punished by God —
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e773">Genesis 14.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e776">
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e778">"Since the judgments of God (Innocent says) are examples for us,
          I do not see why the pope, who is the vicar of Christ,
          cannot do this —
          provided the power is available."</quote>
          So Innocent.
          Certainly, if all the judgments of God were to be imitated by us,
          it would follow that on account of the sin of idolatry
          and the sin against nature,
          the innocent children of those who committed such sins
          ought to be killed —
          on the grounds that God had done so.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e805">
          ¶ Similarly, on account of rebellion
          or schism against the Church,
          not only the rebels and schismatics would have to be killed,
          but also their children and wives,
          and all their possessions would have to be destroyed —
          on the grounds that in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e819">Numbers, chapter 16,</ref>
          we read that Korah, Dathan, and Abiron,
          <add place="margin-left" hand="?">together with their tents and all their substance,</add>
          were swallowed up by the earth
          on account of their disobedience toward Moses and Aaron.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e830">
          ¶ Similarly, that on account of serious theft,
          not only would the thief have to be stoned,
          but also his children, wife, oxen, sheep, beasts of burden,
          and all his possessions would have to be consumed by fire —
          on the grounds that the Lord commanded this to be done
          to <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e840">Achan</name>
          in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e844">Joshua, chapter 7,</ref>
          because he had hidden a scarlet mantle
          and two hundred shekels taken from the plunder of the enemies
          which God had commanded to be burned.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e853">
          ¶ Similarly it would follow
          that if children insulted a prelate —
          even the supreme one —
          they should be thrown to the lions,
          since we read in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e861">4 Kings, chapter 2,</ref>
          that forty-two children were torn apart by bears
          because they mocked
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e868">the prophet Elisha</name>
          as he was coming into the city of Bethel,
          taunting him with these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e875">"Go up, bald-head! Go up, bald-head!"</quote> —
          for which cause they were cursed by
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e880">Elisha</name>
          and torn apart by bears that came out of the forest.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e886">
          And other terrible judgments of God
          which we omit for the sake of brevity —
          which, if they were to be imitated by us,
          would undoubtedly cause us to commit
          a great many and very serious unjust acts and gravest sins,
          and a thousand thousand absurdities would follow.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e907">
          ¶ Therefore not all the judgments of God
          are examples for us to imitate.
          Nor will anyone be able to assign any reason —
          except a frivolous one —
          why we should not imitate the judgments of God
          in these cases just as in that one.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e920">
          To which we respond as follows.
          First, because examples and deeds of this kind from the Old Testament
          are to be marveled at rather than imitated,
          as was said above and will be said again.
          Second, because when God saw that certain sins had begun to be committed,
          he was accustomed to punish them very severely at the outset,
          so that people, frightened by that most severe example,
          might be deterred from similar sins.
          Of this kind was the destruction or submersion of Sodom.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e948">
          At the beginning of the bans
          at the entry into the Promised Land
          was the punishment of <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e954">Achan</name>
          and the transgression of the first ban.
          Similarly, the punishment for the first exercise of simony
          was harshly inflicted upon
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e961">Simony's</name> first practitioner:
          it was severely punished in the case of
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e965">Gehazi,</name>
          who received silver and garments from
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e970">Naaman</name>
          in return for communicating spiritual grace to him.
          For <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e977">Gehazi</name>
          and all his offspring were struck with leprosy by God.
          Thus also, when the evangelical light first arose in the East,
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e983">Ananias</name>
          and <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Nd1e988">Sapphira,</name>
          for one lie alone —
          in that they concealed a certain part of their possessions —
          were suddenly deprived of this light,
          as recorded in Acts, chapter 5.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e1000">
          This reason is given by the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e1004">ordinary gloss</ref>
          in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e1006">"the beginnings of laws are always commended by punishments:
          the two sons of Aaron, offering strange fire, are consumed.
          Oza, supporting the ark, fell dead.
          He fell so that other transgressors might be terrified by his example.
          It was not the cause of gain that gave so severe a sentence of transgression:
          but one who foresaw the future tares
          that would corrupt the simplicity of the Church with depraved morals —
          seeing that no penitence could cure the guilty —
          cut out the harmful root
          in order to instill fear in posterity"</quote>
          and so forth.
          And the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e1037">interlinear gloss:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Qd1e1039">"at the beginning,
          this swift punishment instilled great fear."</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-d1e1047">
          Certainly, greater abuses of simony
          and greater sins and unspeakable crimes
          were afterwards committed by human beings
          of the kinds mentioned above —
          yet God never punished them so severely.
          This matter is treated by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e1058">the Master of Histories on Acts, chapter 22
          of his History,</ref>
          and by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e236-Rd1e1064">Tostado on Joshua,
          chapter 7, question 59.</ref>
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>