<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 12 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] [English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 12 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] [English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-09-18">September 18, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
              4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-09-18" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="62-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Hd1e97">Chapter 12 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e99">
          Chapter 12.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e104">
          ¶ All that has been said above,
          and the ten arguments previously set forth,
          are effectively confirmed by the praiseworthy constitution
          and holy custom of the Church.
          For the custom of the Church is to be imitated and emulated in all things,
          according to
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e117" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1324-d1e2787@4-39">Thomas,
            Secunda Secundae, q. 10, a. 12. c</ref>.
          And
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e122" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e125">Quodlibet 2, a. 7,
            in the body</ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e125">For whatever sacred men have written
            holds authority only from the Church;
            therefore the customs of the Church are to be praised and followed
            and set before the teaching of Jerome and Augustine,
            and of any other sacred doctor.</quote>
          So teaches Saint Thomas.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e139">
          This being granted,
          never from the ascension of Christ to the heavenly realm
          did the Church begin with the punishment of the sins
          by which pagans offend God,
          in order to plant evangelical truth;
          rather, by gentleness, acts of service, meekness,
          and charity she drew them to the faith,
          offering them in the name of Christ the remission of all sins
          (<ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e156">as will be shown below, ch. 39 and the following chapters,</ref>
          more clearly than light itself).
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e161">
          For the Church, illuminated by the Holy Spirit,
          understands that Christ reserved to himself the judgment of those crimes,
          and did not commit it to her,
          and that he willed his Church to lead unbelievers to the truth of the faith
          by gentleness and charity,
          not by force or arms.
          And therefore among the
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e179" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e184">decrees of the pontiffs
            we read: 45 dist. c.</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e184" source="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d45-d1e142@4-61">Those
            who with sincere intention desire to lead
            those outside the Christian religion to the right faith
            ought to strive by means of persuasion,
            not harshness,
            lest those whose minds sound reasoning might have called back from error
            be driven further away by hostility.
            For whoever acts otherwise
            and under this pretext wishes to remove them from the accustomed practice of their rite,
            is shown to be pursuing his own interests there rather than God's.</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e206">
          And further on:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e208">For what profit is there
            when, even if they have been forbidden against long-standing custom,
            it avails nothing for their conversion to the faith?
            Or how do we lay down rules for them
            if by this we cannot win them over?
            For the effort must be made
            that, rather, provoked by reason and gentleness,
            they should wish to follow us,
            not flee from us,</quote>
          and so forth.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e225">
          The same view is held by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e227">Gregory in Book 11 of the Letters</ref>,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e232">Letter 15</ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e234">Letter 34</ref>,
          where he speaks in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e239">Those who are at variance with the Christian religion
            must be gathered into the unity of the faith
            by gentleness, kindness, admonishment, and persuasion,
            lest those whom the sweetness of preaching
            and the fear of the coming judgment's dread
            might have invited to belief
            should be driven away by threats and terrors.
            It is therefore fitting that they come together willingly
            to hear the word of God from you,
            rather than shrinking from a harshness
            that is extended beyond all measure.</quote>
          Thus Gregory.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e262">
          By these words Gregory sufficiently signifies
          what we have at length urged above,
          and what will be seen more fully below.
          <del rend="crosshatch" hand="B">What inconveniences, evils, and harms would follow
            if the Church were to begin the preaching of the Gospel
            from the punishment of sins.
            For war and force, injuries, slaughters, and plundering
            turn pagans away from religion —
            those who, admonished by gentleness and reason,
            might perhaps be healed by that which is the charity of God toward humankind.</del>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e286">
          The same song is sung by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e290">Saint Cyril in Book 6, Against Julian</ref>,
          who speaks thus:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e295">Since the Maker of all things willed man to be his own master
            and to be governed in his deeds by his own will,
            for this reason it seemed very rightly good
            to Christ, the Savior of all,
            that men should be freed from shameful deeds
            by persuasion rather than by the compulsion of necessity,
            so that they might choose what is better
            and be made better by those means
            by which it is most plausible they would be so.
            For if, adorned with royal glory and holding invincible power,
            he had commanded men to believe in him,
            faith would no longer have been the fruit of knowledge,
            but rather of necessary and unavoidable commands,
            and he might perhaps have been like one
            who is honored with the glory of divinity unworthily,
            according to human opinions.
            But because he comported himself as one of us,
            with modest and humble bearing,
            and abstained from human glory,
            partly by his most wise teachings,
            partly by his ineffable divine miracles,
            he leads the willing — and those who truly know —
            to better things,</quote>
          and so forth.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e343">
          See how far removed from the decrees of the Fathers
          and from the teaching of Christ
          is the desire to bring pagans to the faith
          by the terror of arms,
          military force,
          and empty arrogance.
          But whoever acts otherwise,
          or teaches that this should be done,
          shows that both parties are intent upon plunder,
          as
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e356">Gregory in the place cited above</ref>
          shows:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e361">they are shown to be pursuing their own interests there
            rather than God's.</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e367">
          Finally, that
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Nd1e369">Sepúlveda</name>
          has gone wholly astray here,
          and that those who abuse the authority of that otherwise most learned man
          for the confirmation of an impious cause
          are instruments of the devil,
          the enemy of human salvation,
          of the glory of Christ,
          and of the propagation of the Gospel —
          this was declared by
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Rd1e382">the Roman Pontiff Paul III,
            Vicar of Christ,
            in the year 1537,
            by means of a bull he issued,</ref>
          which confirms and renews the ancient custom of the Church
          in the preaching of the Gospel
          and the subjugation of pagans to the true religion.
          It has pleased us to append here the text of the bull.
          ¶
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e399">The sublime God so loved the human race
            that he created man of such a nature
            that he might not only share in the good,
            as other creatures do,
            but might also attain the highest good —
            the inaccessible good —
            and see it face to face.</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e414">
          And further on:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e416">Thereupon, the Truth itself,
            which can neither deceive nor be deceived,
            is known to have said,
            when it appointed preachers of the faith
            to the office of preaching:
            "Going, teach all nations" —
            it said "all," without any distinction,
            since all are capable of receiving the discipline of the faith.
            Seeing and envying this,
            that rival of the human race
            who always opposes all good things lest they be saved,
            devised a hitherto unheard-of means
            of hindering the word of God
            from being preached to the nations so that they might be saved,
            and stirred up certain of his satellites
            who, desiring to satisfy their own greed,
            presume everywhere to assert
            that the western and southern Indians,
            and other peoples who have in these times come to our notice,
            should be reduced to our service like brute animals,
            on the pretext that they are without the Catholic faith;
            and they reduce them to slavery,
            pressing them with such afflictions
            as those by which scarcely brute animals serving them would be pressed.</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e463">
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e465">We, therefore,
            who, though unworthy,
            exercise on earth the functions of the same our Lord,
            and seek with all our effort
            to bring to his sheepfold those sheep of his flock
            that are outside it,
            and that have been entrusted to us —
            taking note that the Indians themselves,
            as true human beings,
            are not only capable of the Christian faith
            but, as has come to our attention,
            eagerly hasten toward that faith —
            and wishing to provide suitable remedies for these matters,
            we determine and declare by apostolic authority,
            by these presents,
            that the aforesaid Indians
            and all other peoples
            that shall hereafter come to the knowledge of Christians,
            even though they be outside the faith of Christ,
            are nonetheless not to be deprived or to be deprived
            of their liberty or dominion over their things;
            rather, they may freely and lawfully use,
            possess, and enjoy such liberty and dominion;
            nor ought they to be reduced to slavery;
            and whatever has been done contrary to this
            is void and of no force or effect.
            And we decree and declare by the said apostolic authority
            that the said Indians
            and all other peoples
            are to be invited to the said faith of Christ
            by the preaching of the word of God
            and the example of a good life,
            notwithstanding the foregoing
            and whatever else may be to the contrary.
            Given at Rome,</quote>
          and so forth. These are its formal words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e518">
          The designated executor and commissioner of this bull
          by apostolic authority
          was the Archbishop of Toledo,
          with the fullest power,
          speaking as follows.
          ¶
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e524">Our beloved son,
            greeting and apostolic blessing.
            Exercising with diligent care the pastoral office
            toward the sheep entrusted to us from on high,
            as we are afflicted by their perdition,
            so we rejoice in their advancement.
            And we not only praise their good works,
            but we extend more widely
            the concerns of our apostolic consideration
            so that they may enjoy the outcomes they have prayed for.
            Indeed it has come to our hearing
            that our most dear son in Christ,
            Charles,
            ever august Emperor of the Romans,
            who is also King of Castile and León,
            has by public edict
            forbidden all his subjects,
            in order to restrain those who,
            burning with greed,
            bear an inhuman disposition toward humankind,
            from presuming to reduce the western or southern Indians to slavery
            or to deprive them of their goods.</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e564">
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e566">We therefore,
            taking note that the Indians themselves,
            even though they exist outside the bosom of the Church,
            are nonetheless not deprived nor to be deprived
            of their liberty or dominion over their things —
            and since they are human beings
            and therefore capable of faith and salvation,
            they are not to be destroyed by servitude
            but are to be invited to life by preachings and examples —
            and therefore also desiring to restrain for our part
            the wicked audacity of such impious men,
            and to provide lest,
            embittered by injuries and harms,
            they become more hardened against embracing the faith of Christ,
            we have special confidence in the Lord
            in your circumspection,
            rectitude, prudence, piety,
            and experience in these and other matters.</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e598">
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Qd1e600">By these presents we commit and command
            that by yourself or through one or more others
            you stand as a shield of effective defense
            for all the aforesaid Indians in the matters set forth above,
            and that you strictly forbid,
            under pain of excommunication
            already incurred by the act itself
            if they do otherwise —
            from which they cannot be absolved
            except by us
            or by the Roman Pontiff who is in office at the time,
            except for those in the moment of death,
            and with prior satisfaction —
            forbid all and singular,
            of whatever dignity, estate, condition, rank,
            and excellence they may be,
            from in any way presuming to reduce the aforesaid Indians to slavery
            or to despoil them of their goods in any manner;
            and that you proceed against those who do not comply
            to the declaration of the incurrence of this excommunication
            and to further measures,
            and that in the aforesaid matters and those related
            you establish, order, and dispose
            what is necessary or in any way fitting,
            as shall seem expedient to your prudence,
            probity, and religious sense.
            In which matters we grant you full power,
            and let nothing contrary to it stand,
            whatever it may be.
            Given at Rome,</quote>
          and so forth. These are its formal words.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e647">
          ¶ Do you see, reader,
          that the Roman Pontiff expressly asserts and teaches
          that all those things which these enemies
          of the propagation of the Gospel affirm are false?
          First, he teaches that the method used by these men
          was the invention of the devil,
          to impede the salvation of humankind
          and the propagation of the true religion.
          And in truth what these men have done must be called by that name —
          portraying the Indians as similar to wild and brute animals
          so as to make use of their labor,
          as though they were beasts of burden.
          <del rend="strikethrough" hand="B">And would that they had treated them
            no less savagely and conveniently than beasts of burden.</del>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e679">
          Second,
          the Roman Pontiff asserts
          that the Indians,
          inasmuch as they are human beings,
          are capable of blessedness
          and of the means by which one arrives at it,
          namely Christian teaching;
          and so he calls them sheep of the flock of Christ
          committed to his pastoral care,
          so that he may lead them to the sheepfold of Christ,
          outside of which they have hitherto been.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e697">
          ¶ Third, he teaches that even if they have not embraced the faith of Christ,
          they are not therefore to be deprived of liberty,
          possession,
          and dominion over the things
          which nature has granted them —
          indeed, that they may lawfully use and enjoy them.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e708">
          Fourth, he teaches that they are not to be extirpated
          from the face of the earth
          by violence, tyranny, and the atrocity of arms,
          lest, goaded by these hardships,
          they vomit forth blasphemies against the law of Christ.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e719">
          ¶ Fifth, he teaches that those
          who carried out atrocious and savage acts against them
          in violation of the commands and prohibitions of the Kings of Castile
          were satellites of Satan
          and of the most relentless enemy of humankind.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e730">
          ¶ Sixth, he teaches that the western and southern Indians
          who have not heard the Gospel of Christ
          are to be invited and led to the faith
          by gentleness,
          meekness,
          kind inducements,
          and Christian charity.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e741">
          You see the Supreme Pontiff,
          regarding the drawing of unbelievers to the faith,
          decreeing the same thing
          that natural reason itself dictates,
          that Christ taught and commanded by word and example,
          that his apostles,
          always following his footsteps in all things,
          took care to fulfill diligently,
          that the sacred doctors taught in their writings,
          and that the Church has used
          through its traditions and customs
          from the earliest age,
          and which it shows preachers of the faith ought to employ.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e766">
          Therefore they are not to be harassed,
          despoiled,
          and persecuted —
          which is what the satellites of Satan have done
          and continue to do,
          raging against a wretched people
          with incredible savagery —
          nor are they even to be punished
          for any sins,
          however grave,
          in which they may be entangled,
          committed within the bounds of their own territories
          or in their unbelief,
          as the good doctor
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-Nd1e784">Sepúlveda</name>
          rashly and presumptuously affirms.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e787">
          ¶ Seventh, the bull declares and,
          making a new decree,
          ordains
          that acts done contrary to this are void
          and of no effect.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e197-d1e794">
          By these eleven arguments
          our truthful judgment is proven
          to be most true and beyond doubt —
          namely, that it does not belong to the Church,
          nor to any Christian prince,
          to punish the crimes of unbelievers
          of which our discourse treats,
          by reason of defect of authority and jurisdiction,
          and so forth.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
