<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 13 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] — English Translation</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 13 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] — English Translation</title>
          <date when="2024-10-09">Oct 09, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-10-09" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="66-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Hd1e97">Chapter 13 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e99">
          Chapter 13.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e104">
          ¶ It remains to respond to the example that Sepúlveda brings forward
          from the sacred books — namely,
          from <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e110" target="http://scta.info/resource/deut7_1">Deuteronomy ch. 7</ref>
          and from <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e112" target="http://scta.info/resource/io8_24 http://scta.info/resource/io8_25 http://scta.info/resource/io8_26 http://scta.info/resource/io8_27 http://scta.info/resource/io8_28 http://scta.info/resource/io8_29">the book of Joshua</ref>:
          where we read that God, on account of certain crimes,
          destroyed the seven nations who were inhabitants of the promised land.
          He contends moreover that this should be carried out against the Indians,
          citing also <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e123">Saint Cyprian,</ref>
          whose meaning he inverts and adulterates,
          as he is accustomed to do with many other things.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e130">
          First, therefore, most distinguished doctor
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e132">Sepúlveda,</name>
          I would like to know from you why God did not command the destruction
          of very many other idolaters who were living at that time.
          For with the exception of the Jewish people
          and the lineage that extended from
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e144">Adam</name>
          all the way to Christ,
          the whole world was given over to the worship of idols.
          Except for a few men noble in piety —
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e150">Job,</name>
          namely,
          and <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e154">Melchizedek,</name>
          and others whom God deigned to grant knowledge of the truth
          while living among the nations —
          as is evident from <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e161">Genesis,</ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e163">Deuteronomy,</ref>
          and nearly all the books of the Old Testament.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e168">
          And <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e172">Paul</name>
          and <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e174">Barnabas</name>
          bear witness in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e18x" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e178">Acts ch. 14,</ref>
          saying:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e178" source="http://scta.info/resource/act14_15@1-11">that God, namely, in past generations
            allowed all the nations to walk in their own ways</quote> —
          that is, their various rites and ceremonies of idols.
          This <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e188">Ambrose treats at length
          in his two books on the calling of all nations,</ref>
          and all the histories of the pagans sufficiently attest to it.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e199">
          Although, therefore, the whole world worshipped idols,
          God did not command that the Edomites or the Egyptians
          be destroyed by war —
          peoples who surpassed the other nations of the world
          in their foul worship of idols and in other crimes.
          On the contrary, God said:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e209" source="http://scta.info/resource/deut23_7@1-15">You shall not abhor the Edomite,
            for he is your brother.
            Nor Egypt, for you were a stranger in his land.</quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e217" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e209">Deuteronomy 27.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e220">
          And so God by no means commanded the killing of any idolaters
          except those who inhabited the promised land,
          unless there happened to be some new cause apart from idolatry.
          This is proven from <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e230">chapter 20 of that book,</ref>
          where God, instructing his people how they ought to conduct war
          against the pagans who dwelt outside the promised land —
          if perchance they should receive harm or injury from them,
          as <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e246"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e247">Lyranus</name> notes there</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e250"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e251">Abulensis</name> in question 1
          and 2 Chronicles ch. 8, q. 5</ref> —
          admonished them with these words, saying:
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e259">
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e261" source="http://scta.info/resource/deut20_10@1-10">If at any time you approach a city to besiege it,
          you shall first offer it peace.</quote>
          And further on:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e268" source="http://scta.info/resource/deut20_15@1-21 http://scta.info/resource/deut20_16@1-11 http://scta.info/resource/deut20_17@1-5">Thus you shall do to all the cities that are very far from you,
            and that are not among those cities which you are about to receive
            as your possession.
            But of those cities that shall be given to you,
            you shall permit no one at all to live,
            but shall put them to death by the edge of the sword</quote>
          and so forth.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e286">
          And so against the Canaanites inhabiting the promised land,
          sufficient cause for war was simply that they were inhabitants of that land;
          therefore the Jews were bound by divine command to kill them,
          sparing neither great nor small,
          nor even the animals themselves at times.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e299">
          Yet against other nations,
          even if they were impious and idolatrous,
          the Jews could not take up arms without some other legitimate cause;
          and in such cases they were bound first to offer them peace.
          If the others did not refuse it and therefore opened their gates,
          the Jews could afflict them with no other hardship
          than the imposition of tribute as a penalty
          for harm or injury inflicted upon themselves;
          and once tribute had been imposed,
          the others were left unharmed and free to inhabit their own cities.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e321">
          But if they obstinately refused peace,
          persisting in that resolve,
          the Jews could, after taking the city,
          kill those who were fit for battle;
          yet they were bound to spare the women, children, and animals.
          Indeed they could even spare the men,
          for they were not bound by divine command to kill them,
          as <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e336">Cajetan notes there.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e343">
          <add place="inline" hand="B">And</add> although this was indeed a general rule —
          namely, that no nation, however idolatrous,
          among those dwelling outside the promised land
          could be subjected to war or any other hardship
          unless some legitimate cause intervened —
          the Lord had, however, made two exceptions from all the others:
          namely the Midianites and the Amalekites,
          whom the Jews were bound by divine command to attack and destroy —
          not indeed because they were idolaters.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e382">
          For, as has been said,
          they could not wage war against idolaters without a just cause,
          even if they were most impious;
          rather, it was because those peoples had inflicted certain particular wrongs
          upon the children of Israel.
          The Midianites were indeed the cause
          by which the children of Israel committed fornication
          with the women of that region and worshipped idols,
          and thereby the wrath of God came upon them;
          for which reason the Lord commanded them:
          let the Midianites feel that you are their enemies,
          and strike them,
          for they acted in a hostile manner against you.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e410">Numbers ch. 16.</ref>
          <note place="rm" hand="F">
            <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e403">The children of Israel could make war
              upon the Midianites and Amalekites.</quote>
          </note>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e413">
          The Amalekites, moreover, twice fought against the Jews
          in an unjust and impious manner in the desert:
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e419">Exodus 17</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e421">Numbers 14.</ref>
          Therefore God commanded them not to forget that injury,
          but to blot out the name of Amalek from the face of the earth
          as soon as they had first settled in their own land.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e433">Deuteronomy 26.</ref>
          And because Saul spared their king, he sinned gravely;
          for which reason the Lord did not permit his sons to succeed him in the kingdom.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e439">1 Kings 15.</ref>
          The Lord, therefore, did not will that all idolaters be killed
          or subjected indiscriminately by war,
          unless some particular and just cause were present.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e452">
          For a case that is admitted for a special reason
          does not make a general rule;
          on the contrary, it teaches that the common law is to the contrary,
          by the argument from the special provision —
          concerning which argument see <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e462" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e81-d1e254">l. quod vero contra</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e468" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e81-d1e275">l. ius singulare. ff de legibus</ref>,
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e470" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e4980-d1e108">l. 1. ff ad municipia</ref>,
          and in the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e475" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1612-d1e301">rule which is iure de regulis iuris,
          Book 69, with similar passages.</ref>
          These men therefore err,
          knowing neither the scriptures nor the power of God.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e483">
          Nor does what they adduce from <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e491">Lyranus
          on Numbers ch. 31</ref> carry any more weight —
          where, teaching that certain just causes
          for which war was undertaken are found in the sacred books,
          he adds that a just cause for war is if the nation of some province
          blasphemes God by worshipping idols,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e511">Deuteronomy ch. 13.</ref>
          This indeed we do not deny,
          as it is read there.
          But that is understood to be true when they worship idols
          after having received the faith.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e520">
          For if, having been warned and required to abstain
          from those impure sacrifices and sacrilegious worship,
          they refuse to do penance and to acknowledge the truth,
          war can justly be waged against them.
          This the Lord commanded through
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e530">Moses,</name>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e533">Deuteronomy 13.</ref>
          Although even those who had not been heard were bound to be destroyed at that time —
          concerning which see what is said in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e539">the following chapter.</ref>
          In this age of grace, however,
          something altogether different is to be thought and done
          (as I will demonstrate shortly).
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e547">
          The passages that Sepúlveda hammers in by constant repetition,
          so as to induce a lethargic sleep in those who pay no attention —
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e554">Deuteronomy 12,</ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e556">9,</ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e558">18,</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e561">Leviticus 13,</ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e563">18,</ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e565">20</ref> —
          speak of idolaters inhabiting the promised land,
          whose idols the Jews were bound to utterly demolish to their foundations.
          But to argue from idolaters inhabiting the promised land
          to other idolaters,
          especially after the coming of Christ,
          is absurd (as I have shown above);
          otherwise, if they press us with the authority of those passages,
          they will also teach that the Spaniards must necessarily kill
          the great and the small,
          the guilty and the innocent,
          even down to the beasts of burden,
          dogs, and cats —
          just as is commanded in some of those passages —
          which is most absurd.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e596">
          But if they deny this —
          claiming that children, women, dogs, and beasts of burden
          ought to be spared —
          I will ask by what right they admit those passages
          with respect to men,
          yet reject them with respect to children,
          beasts of burden, and the other things commanded to be killed there?
          Is it for the sole reason that so it seems to
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e609">Sepúlveda?</name>
          He brings forward a sufficiently weak argument
          to deserve belief on this point.
          In sum, those passages speak of pagans inhabiting the promised land;
          against all others the Jews could not wage war
          without some other legitimate cause
          (as has been proven above many times).
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e625">
          I marvel, however, that this Christian man
          does not rather admit those passages
          which speak of pagans outside the promised land,
          so that we might use their analogy against all the nations of the world
          found to be given over to idolatry —
          since those passages are more closely in accord
          with the mildness of the evangelical teaching
          and the meekness and charity of Christ
          than those which rested upon that special and rigorous command.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e645">
          ¶ But so that the pernicious error
          and the ignorance — or certainly the malice —
          of certain adversaries, now exposed,
          may henceforth be more clearly manifest to all,
          as a further confirmation of what has been said,
          we wish to prove more fully
          that that rigorous command against the Canaanite nations
          was most special in character,
          and hence that those passages commanding idolaters to be killed
          are to be admitted only against the inhabitants of the promised land.
          This we prove by assigning certain reasons for this special character,
          drawn from the sacred scriptures.
          <pb ed="#P" n="69-v"/>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e671">
          Two of these reasons
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e675">Saint Thomas assigns in book 4 of the Sentences,
          distinction 29, art. 1, ad 1m.</ref>
          First, because the wickedness of those nations was already complete,
          and therefore the Lord was unwilling to tolerate them any longer,
          given that they persisted in their sins with stubborn minds.
          For we read in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e689">Genesis 15</ref>
          that God said to Abraham:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e698">to your seed I will give this land.</quote>
          And again, as if Abraham were asking the Lord
          why he would not give it to him at once,
          it is added:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e705">for the iniquities of the Amorites
            are not yet complete up to the present time.</quote>
          The iniquity of that nation, therefore,
          is believed to have been complete at the time
          when the children of Israel went out from the servitude of the Egyptians,
          at which point that command was imposed upon them to exterminate those peoples.
          This <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e721">Gratian notes in c. remittuntur, 23 q. 5, § praescientes.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e727">
          This obstinacy of the nation is expressly reported in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e731">the book of Joshua ch. 11:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e733">For it was the sentence of the Lord
            that their hearts should be hardened,
            and that they should not deserve any clemency.</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e742">
          And so the Lord, on account of the crimes of that nation,
          had condemned it to death
          and had made the Hebrews the executors of his will;
          therefore he expressly commanded them to kill and exterminate those peoples;
          and if the Hebrews had not done so they would have sinned mortally.
          But other idolaters they could not kill.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e758">
          ¶ The second reason for which the Lord commanded the Hebrews
          in particular to kill those nations
          was on account of the danger that threatened the Hebrews themselves.
          For the Hebrews, as is clear from many passages of sacred scripture,
          were especially prone to idolatry.
          Lest therefore the proximity of the Canaanites,
          Amorites, and the other nations of that region
          draw them into the worship of idols,
          the Lord commanded those nations to be utterly exterminated:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e778">lest perhaps (he says) they teach you to do
            all the abominations which they have practiced for their gods,
            and you sin against the Lord your God.</quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e787">Deuteronomy 20</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e792">7.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e795">
          For the same reason also the Lord commanded
          that they should not contract friendship or marriage
          with any of those nations.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e801">Deuteronomy 7.</ref>
          This <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e803">Saint Thomas notes in the same place
          and in Ia IIae q. 105, art. 4, ad 6m.</ref>
          With the other idolatrous nations, however,
          the Jews were not prohibited from contracting friendship —
          especially if there was no danger present
          of their being drawn into their worship.
          Thus we see that it was permissible for the Hebrews
          to form marriage alliances with those peoples.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e820">
          For Joseph took as wife the daughter of Potiphera,
          who was a priest of the idols of Egypt.
          Moses had an Ethiopian wife.
          Esther married King Ahasuerus.
          Solomon celebrated nuptials with the daughter of the king of Egypt.
          Indeed, even with idolaters very close to the promised land
          it was permissible to contract marriage.
          For we read in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e837">Ruth ch. 4</ref>
          that Ruth the Moabite,
          born in the land of Moab which is very close to the land of Canaan,
          married Boaz.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e852">
          Likewise in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e854">Deuteronomy ch. 21,</ref>
          the Lord permitted the Hebrews that if they should ever wage war
          against other enemies —
          that is, those not inhabiting the promised land —
          and conquer them,
          and among the captives should see a beautiful woman
          who appealed to them,
          they could, after performing certain rites,
          take her as a wife.
          Indeed they could even take as wives
          the daughters of pagans inhabiting the promised land,
          by dispensation.
          For Salmon, prince of the tribe of Judah,
          son of Nahshon, took as wife
          Rahab the harlot, who was born in the city of Jericho,
          which is in the inland region of Canaan —
          as we read in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e885">Numbers 12</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e887">71</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e889">Matthew 1.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e895">
          <add place="lm" hand="F">Third reason.</add>
          ¶ In the Conferences of the Fathers,
          the conference of <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e901">the holy Abbot Serapion, ch. 24,</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e903">Saint Epiphanius in the book entitled the Ancoratus,</ref>
          and <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e909">Saint Augustine in sermon 105 de tempore</ref>
          offer another reason for this special command.
          Namely, because that region which the Canaanites possessed
          had fallen by lot to Shem,
          the eldest son of Noah,
          when Noah divided the world among his three sons.
          And an oath was exacted from them by their father
          that none of them should invade the lot of a brother,
          and that whoever transgressed this sworn precept
          should be exterminated by oath —
          he and his entire seed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e933">
          But after the sons of Shem had long possessed that region,
          the sons of Ham — whom Noah their father cursed
          (who are called Canaanites) —
          descending into that region,
          violently expelled the sons of Shem
          and took possession of their territory.
          Therefore the Lord, who is long-suffering,
          gave them time for repentance
          so that those born of Ham might repent
          and restore to the sons of Shem their proper inheritance;
          but they did not repent.
          Then God, being just after many generations,
          avenged those who had been wronged by the sons of Ham,
          exterminating the offspring of Ham in accordance with their oath,
          and the seed of Shem — that is, the children of Israel —
          received their own region.
          For thus it was necessary that the measure of the Amorites be fulfilled —
          that is, the wickedness of the Canaanites —
          both so that the kingdom might be restored to its lawful owners,
          and also so that the crimes of that nation might be punished.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e978">
          ¶ From this it clearly appears
          that the command of the Lord
          to exterminate the seven nations inhabiting the promised land
          had a particular cause,
          and that from it one cannot infer in general
          that pagan idolaters are to be killed —
          which we have proven from the passages of the Old Testament.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e991">
          And since this was the case even in the time of the old law,
          which was harsh and severe,
          all the more is this to be understood today,
          when through the coming of Christ the Lord has poured out
          the treasures of his mercy over all the earth and over every nation.
          For this reason this time is called the time of grace,
          the time of love,
          the year of favor,
          the day of salvation and joy,
          the good news sent freely —
          as the prophets and both the Old and New Testaments
          are full of testimonies of this kind.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e1015">
          The venerable
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e1017">Doctor Sepúlveda</name>
          therefore errs,
          who in this matter by no means carefully examined
          — or certainly did not understand well enough —
          the scriptures,
          wishing in this age of grace and mercy to put into practice
          the rigorous commands of the old law that were issued for a special reason,
          and thereby to open the way for tyrants and plunderers,
          under the pretext of religion,
          to cruelly invade, oppress, plunder,
          and reduce to bitter slavery innocent nations
          that have neither heard the faith
          nor could have suspected that the faith of Christ
          or the Christian religion existed in the nature of things.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e1044">
          What then? The examples of things that God at that time
          commanded to be done we admire,
          yet we ought not to imitate them —
          as is stated in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1050">c. nos si incompetenter,
          § his ita respondetur, 2 q. 7.</ref>
          For <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e1056">Samuel</name>
          in one of those wars cut to pieces
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e1061">Agag, king of the Amalekites,</name>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1063">1 Kings 15;</ref>
          but now consecrated men abstain from all shedding of blood.
          Likewise <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Nd1e1069">Phinehas the priest</name>
          killed a Jew who was lying with a Midianite woman;
          but now it would be judged impious
          for a priest to defile his hands with blood.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e1079">
          Furthermore the Hebrews then despoiled
          the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1083">Egyptians</ref> by a kind of stratagem,
          and the prophet <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1085">Hosea</ref>
          took up with a harlot wishing to have children of fornication.
          But today, according to the evangelical law,
          if anyone did something similar
          he would be guilty of theft and licentiousness
          and would commit mortal sin.
          It was then permitted to have many wives;
          today one who did the same would be an adulterer.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e1103">
          Therefore <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1105">Gregory in the Moralia,
          book 18, ch. 3,</ref>
          cited also in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1110">the Decretals, 22 q. 2,
          c. si quis,</ref> says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e1115">If anyone through the Old Testament wishes to defend his falsehood,
            because it perhaps harmed some people less there,
            let him say that the seizure of another's property
            and the requiting of injury —
            conceded to the weak there —
            cannot harm him.
            All of which, it is evident with what great correction
            truth pursues them,
            truth which now, having cast aside the shadow of its signification,
            is declared to us in true flesh.</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e1136">
          And again <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1138">at the end of ch. 2, Gregory says:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e1143">For in the New Testament,
            with higher precepts,
            truth having been made manifest through the flesh,
            we make progress;
            and it is just that we abandon certain deeds
            which in that people served as a shadow of the truth.</quote>
          Thus Gregory.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e1161">
          Again, <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1164">Augustine in his Questions on Exodus,
          read in 14 q. 5, c. dixit dominus,</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Qd1e1169">The Lord said (he writes) to Moses:
            let every man ask of his neighbor
            and every woman of her neighbor,
            vessels of silver and of gold and clothing —
            no one from this ought to think an example is being given
            for despoiling one's neighbor in this manner.
            For the Lord commanded this,
            who knew what each person ought to suffer,
            and the Israelites did not commit theft,
            but performed a service at God's command.</quote>
          Thus Augustine.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-d1e1190">
          Those, therefore, who from those passages strive to prove
          that all unbelievers or idolaters in general
          are to be consumed by the sword of war —
          where of necessity so many homicides,
          so many plunderings, rapines, scandals,
          and infinitely many other irreparable evils and hardships intervene —
          on the grounds that God commanded the children of Israel
          to do such things to the Egyptians and Canaanites:
          must necessarily also confess
          that it is permissible to steal others' property,
          to avenge one's own injuries;
          they must also acknowledge what I have said above —
          that this would be nothing other than the practice of Judaism.
          But by the words of the Savior we are taught
          that we cannot attain salvation
          unless we surpass the justice of the Jews.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e210-Rd1e1218">Matthew 6.</ref>
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>