<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 62 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 62 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-06-20">June 20, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-06-20" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="250-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855">
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-d1e97">
          Chapter 62
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-d1e102">
          Therefore that word contained in the bull "to subject" 
          must be understood civilly and christianly:
          which beyond the above is proven from the common principles of law that any law or 
          constitution ought to be extended or restricted:
          to the limits of the expressed reason:
          even if the words do not allow it as in L. adigere. §. quamuis. ff. de Iure patio 
          and in l. cum pater, 
          § dulcissimis. ff. de legatis 2o and in L. pater. §. fundum. ff. de lega. 3o 
          and in c. cum dilecta de confir. utili. And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e138">regula fi. de regulis Iuris. lib. 6</ref> 
          where it is said: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Qd1e143" source="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1612-d1e735">
            it is certain that he commits against the law:
            who embracing the words of the law:
            strives against the intention of the law</quote>.
          And always the mind of the prince must be examined,
          observed and followed even if it does not agree with the propriety of the words in the 
          said § dulcissimis. For always the mind of the speaker must be considered rather than 
          the voice. ff. de suppellecti. lega. L. labeo. Nor should the word be examined more 
          than the will of the speaker. c. quae res pigno. obliga. possunt. l. ultima And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e169" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c22q5-d1e297">
            22. q. 5 c. humanae aures.</ref>
          and in l. scire leges: 
          cum duabus sequen. ff. de legi. and it is noted in l. quamuis and there the gloss. 
          finalis. ff. de in ius vocando 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Nd1e179">Panormitanus</name> 
          and others in c. quia insulis de regularibus after 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Nd1e183">John of Legnano</name> 
          in c. audientiam. de decimis. For words ought to serve the intention and not the 
          intention serve the words:
          as has been proven above. And 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Nd1e192">John of Legnano</name> 
          in c. ad audientiam de decimis And generally in the letters of the prince the mind 
          must be considered:
          and the reason upon which his commands rest as in c. si propter tua debita and there 
          the doctors. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e209">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Nd1e210">Ancharanus</name> 
            in the repetition of the same chapter de Rescriptis libro 6.</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e215">in c. 2, eo titulo</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e220">c. ultimo de concessione praebendae libro 6</ref>, 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e225">c. ex multiplici de decimis.</ref> 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e230">Archidiaconnus. 25. q. 2. c. Seruatis.</ref> 
          says,
          that where it is evident concerning the intention of the pope that intention must be 
          followed entirely. Likewise,
          that the words of the pope enunciating the intention from of old determine and prove. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e241" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c25q2-d1e106">25. q. 2. § quod autem</ref> 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Nd1e247">Baldus</name> 
          reports and confirms these things in the proem of the book of feuds § aliqua in 
          principio.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-d1e253">
          Now the mind of the pontiff was that those peoples should be led to Christ. 
          But this can in no way be done by war which rather generates hatred than love of our 
          religion. Therefore by gentleness,
          charity,
          holy customs and the word of God the Indians must be led to the faith not by war 
          concerning which the pontiff never dreamed (as we have often said) 
          and the kings themselves understood that those peoples were to be subjected not by war 
          but by the word of God as commanded to them by the pontiff as has been most clearly 
          proven above. With these agrees that in odious matters words are to be strictly 
          interpreted while favorable matters are to be extended and expanded. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Qd1e285" 
            source="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1612-d1e213">
            Hatreds should be restricted and favors should be amplified</quote> 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e290">c. odia de regulis juris lib. 6.</ref> 
          But war which 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Nd1e299">Homer</name> 
          writes is sent from hell is the most miserable and pestilential of all things that are 
          under heaven:
          and completely incompatible with the life and teaching of Christ unless when 
          unavoidable necessity compels it. But to invite pagans to the faith by the word of God 
          and evangelical customs is most holy and truly Christian and suitable for extending and 
          exalting the glory of Christ.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-d1e317">
          Let us therefore restrict war,
          the pestilence of body and soul:
          and let us embrace evangelical preaching and the sword of the divine word more 
          efficacious than all human arms. To these is added that even those things which 
          regularly ought to be restricted such as penalties:
          are extended / If it concerns public utility according to Bartolus in l. quemadmodum. 
          C. de agricol. et censib. but these things pertain to the public salvation of those 
          peoples:
          that they should be led to the faith not by war deadly to mortals:
          but by the word of God and to the rule of the kings of Spain. For by war it will 
          rather happen that they hate the faith than that they embrace it. Then I believe no 
          utility to be more public:
          than that which besides the tranquility of so many provinces / generates the salvation 
          of so many myriads of mortals. For the soul must be preferred to all things. as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e368" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t38-d1e301">
            c. cum infirmitas. de penitentiis et remissionibus</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-Rd1e374" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c12q1-d1e494">c. praecipimus. 12. q. 1</ref>
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e855-d1e380">
          Let us therefore restrict that word "to subject":
          so that it is understood concerning the subjection which will be born from the 
          preaching of the divine word:
          Gentle and mild:
          in which sense that word must be accepted even if its proper signification were 
          opposed. Especially since there exists the bull of Paul III,
          Roman pontiff which expressly prohibits these detestable wars which are waged against 
          the Indians under the pretext of religion:
          commanding:
          that they should be led to the faith not by warlike terror but by the word of God and 
          holy customs. The content of this bull given in the year 1537 I have recounted above 
          in the chapter.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>