<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 27 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 27 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-27">Apr 27, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-27" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>
            Created file for the first time.
          </p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="123-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Hd1e97">
          Chapter 27 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]
        </head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e99">
          <pb ed="#P" n="123-r"/>
          Chapter 27.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e104">
          ¶ With these things agrees what we proved above,
          that no one can be compelled to provide a good which he never promised. 
          To this is similar that also by human law a benefit is not conferred upon an unwilling person 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e114">l. inuito. ff. de regulis juris</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e119">l. hoc jure. §. non potest, ff. de donatio</ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e124">l. si quis in inconcedendo, C. de pactis</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e130">
          ¶ Returning to the princes of the infidels,
          who would maliciously impede the propagation of the gospel:
          that the Church can move war against them is proven by this manifest reasoning. 
          Since Christ the Lord is king and lord of every creature inhabiting whatever part of the world:
          to impede that men recognize and worship him,
          the fountain of all good,
          through the reception of the Catholic faith:
          an injury is done to him which the Church cannot in the least tolerate.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e154">
          For this sin is not similar to that which they commit among themselves and against God:
          rather it directly removes the honor owed to God,
          and directly does injury to him,
          and is true and formal blasphemy against the Christian religion maliciously committed:
          wherefore it is carried into the injury of all,
          what is committed against the divine majesty,
          as we taught above.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e175">
          Whence it is clear from the reasons introduced above,
          that against those infidels only who would maliciously impede the propagation of the faith:
          or in those who had already received it,
          trying that they might abandon it:
          or placing obstacles to those who would probably believe:
          the Church can justly move war. 
          Of these speaks 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e194">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e195">
              Albertus Pius,
              Count of Carpi,
            </name>
            who 
            <title>
              writing against Erasmus
            </title>
          </ref>
          asserts and wishes to prove it is lawful to wage war against the Turks,
          either that we might recover kingdoms taken away from Christian dominion:
          or because they impede or would impede the propagation of the faith.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e215">
          Whence 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e217">
            Pius
          </name>
          thus speaks. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Qd1e218">
            Therefore,
            whoever opposes Christ the Lord and resists his glory:
            impeding the propagation of the gospel:
            certainly they are to be cast down from all power,
            since they abuse it against the dignity and greatness of the supreme Prince. 
            For with them ruling things,
            it is not permitted to the peoples subject to their tyranny:
            to receive the evangelical law,
            nor is it allowed that it be preached:
            for which reason,
            to promulgate it and to amplify the glory of Christ:
            it is lawful and expedient according to place and time to invade them,
            and to subject them to the sweet yoke of Christ:
            even if they do not provoke us in the least,
            nor hold our lands,
            which were ever possessed by us. 
            For they are of the right of Christ:
            which it is lawful for the servants of Christ to vindicate:
            therefore,
            in this manner with this purpose,
            namely,
            of propagating the gospel and amplifying the glory of Christ:
            if war is undertaken,
            it will be pious and just,
          </quote>
          these things 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e266">
            the Count of Carpi
          </name>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e272">
          Whoever reads those words:
          even if they do not provoke us in the least:
          and those,
          for they are of the right of Christ. 
          Perhaps they will think that 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e280">
            Pius
          </name>
          teaches:
          it is lawful to wage war against infidels even peaceful ones:
          even if no other cause is present,
          than the propagation of the gospel and amplification of the glory of Christ,
          but truly it is not so. 
          For 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e291">
            Albertus
          </name>
          speaks when they maliciously resist the preaching and propagation of the gospel,
          as is clear 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e300">
            there
          </ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Qd1e302">
            therefore whoever opposes Christ the Lord,
            and resists his glory,
            impeding the propagation of the gospel
          </quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e310">
          Likewise he speaks of the Turks and Moors,
          who are not ignorant of our teachings,
          and most effectively oppose the propagation of our religion. 
          Thus also it is proven from those words of his,
          where treating that war is lawful even if no other cause is present than the amplification of the glory of Christ,
          according to place and time it is lawful and expedient,
          namely,
          to invade such infidels opposing the expansion of the faith,
          and to subject them to the sweet yoke of Christ. 
          Whence whatever he treats there:
          this is presupposing malicious resistance and impediments of the infidels lest the faith be propagated,
          and not indeed of infidels 
          <del rend="strikethrough" hand="B">
            the faith is not propagated and not indeed of infidels
          </del>
          absolutely:
          but only of Saracens and Turks,
          concerning whom is established the most inveterate hatred which they bear against the name of Christ.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e356">
          Therefore it is not always lawful to move war,
          even only for the sake of the expansion of the faith,
          since he says:
          according to place and time it is lawful and expedient:
          but when they maliciously impede the propagation of the gospel:
          and when without scandal and hatred of our religion and blasphemies against Christ,
          they could be subjected to his sweet yoke,
          as we proved above. 
          Otherwise I do not know how it would redound to the glory of Christ,
          and the increase of religion:
          nor how the souls of such infidels,
          if the matter is dealt with by the sword,
          would obtain salvation. 
          To me it rather seems that by such means the blood of Christ is rendered useless to them:
          therefore not only is it not expedient,
          but indeed it is not lawful.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e391">
          <add place="margin-left" hand="E">
            Fifth case
          </add>
          ¶ The fifth case in which the Church can bring into act the jurisdiction which it has over infidels only in habit:
          is when infidels with warlike apparatus burst into our provinces,
          or infest our shores. 
          Either in general,
          as the Turks daily with terrible armies molest,
          attack,
          and afflict Christianity:
          or in particular,
          as we more frequently suffer from the Saracens.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e423">
          And the reason which makes for the Church is clear. 
          For by the law of nature,
          the arms of all peoples of the world are stirred up against public enemies. 
          Thus we also,
          that we may crush the insolence of such:
          recover captives:
          and by inflicting equal disasters,
          teach men to fear ours and abstain from injuries:
          so that they may make amends for the disasters inflicted upon us.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e444">
          And an act of this kind is called natural defense,
          and is contained under that maxim of natural law 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Qd1e451">
            it is lawful to repel force with force
          </quote>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e453">
            l. ut vim ff. de justi et jur
          </ref>.
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e458">
            c. olim. t. de restitu. spoliatorum
          </ref>.
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e464">
            c. dilecto: de senten. excomuni. lib. 6
          </ref>.
          And in other places of both laws.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e472">
          These three last cases,
          the 3rd,
          4th,
          and 5th,
          are comprehended by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e476">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e477">
              St. Thomas
            </name>
            2a 2ae,
            q. 10,
            art. 8
          </ref>
          in these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Qd1e482">
            they are to be compelled by the faithful,
            namely,
            the infidels,
            if the faculty is present:
            that they not impede the faith:
            either by blasphemies,
            or by evil persuasions,
            or by open persecutions:
            and on account of this,
            the faithful of Christ frequently move war against the infidels,
            that they may compel them not to impede the faith
          </quote>.
          This he says.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e501">
          These causes set forth are interpreted by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e510">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e511">
              Cajetan
            </name>
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e515">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e516">
              Carpensis
            </name>
            in the place cited above
          </ref>,
          although 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e521">
            Erasmus
          </name>
          never dreamed that which 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e524">
            Carpensis
          </name>
          objects to him;
          rather he most openly teaches the Catholic position 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e528">
            expounding the psalm Bring to the Lord,
            O sons of God
          </ref>,
          and in many other places:
          But Carpensis perhaps was seeking glory from the denunciation of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e537">
            Erasmus
          </name>:
          to whom our 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e541">
            Sepúlveda
          </name>
          by forging that little book performed strenuous service,
          as fame reports.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e555">
          ¶ The reason of the doctrine of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e558">
            St. Thomas
          </name>
          is:
          since in those three cases,
          the pagans by reason of offense:
          are made of our jurisdiction,
          and we can punish them,
          even if otherwise they are not subject to us,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e566">
            c. fi. de foro compe.
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e572">
            c. 1º. de raptori.
          </ref>
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e576">
            c. vbi de criminibus agi oportet.
          </ref>
          in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e579">
            auten. qua in prouincia
          </ref>,
          and in very many other laws:
          where it is held that by reason of offense,
          someone is made of the jurisdiction of another:
          of whom the judge otherwise was not his.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-d1e589">
          Because no other remedy is found,
          and therefore natural reason itself supplies and dictates:
          when,
          namely,
          there is no superior to whom recourse can be had,
          et cetera. 
          And concerning such infidels,
          who offend us,
          says 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e604">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Nd1e605">
              Baldus
            </name>
            in 
            <title>
              the proem on the Decretals of Gregory
            </title>,
            3rd col.
          </ref>,
          that by temporal judges they can well be punished,
          all infidels near the territory of the one judging:
          nor are they distinguished whence they may be,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e394-Rd1e619">
            l. 3. ff. de offi. presi.
          </ref>,
          where it is said:
          that the governor of the province sometimes has authority also against foreigners,
          if they have committed any evil,
          et cetera.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>