<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 53 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 53 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-05-23">May 23, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-05-23" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="226-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Hd1e90">Chapter 53 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-d1e94">
          Chapter 53
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-d1e99">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> As for the slanderers of the Indians: 
          they also bring forward what 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Rd1e109" target="http://scta.info/resource/jb2v19-d111866-d1e326@114-285">
            John Major wrote on this matter in the second book of Sentences, chapter 44, question 3
          </ref> 
          who truly, with all due respect, 
          spoke very confusedly partly about all unbelievers: 
          partly he thinks erroneously and against natural reason and divine law, 
          to the scandal and impediment of the faith: 
          he said certain things in the present business of the Indians. 
          However, 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Rd1e129" target="http://scta.info/resource/jsnvu6-e146938">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Nd1e130">Durandus</name>, 
            a theologian of greater authority, 
            disapproves of his doctrine in that Book of Sentences in the same distinction
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-d1e136">
          But so that the errors of this man ignorant of law and fact may appear more clearly, 
          I will set forth his words: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Qcyaa8a" source="http://scta.info/resource/jb2v19-d111866-d1e326@114-285">
            Since, he says, the Indians did not understand the Spanish language: 
            nor would they admit preachers of the divine word without a great army, 
            it was necessary to build fortified strongholds here and there, 
            so that with the passage of time the unbridled people might become accustomed to the ways 
            of Christians, understanding each other mutually. 
            And because great expenses are required in all these things, 
            which no other king provides, 
            it is therefore lawful to seize them, 
            because another ought reasonably to wish this. 
            And then when the people will have become Christian, 
            either the ancient king receives the faith or not. 
            If the latter, since he can turn to the harm of the faith, 
            he is to be deposed for the liberty of the orthodox faith, 
            and also deserves to be deposed: 
            and this the people wishes if they properly receive Christianity. 
            But if you suppose the people still wish to have that ancient king, 
            although he remains a pagan, 
            it is a great indication that the faith is not yet sincerely received: 
            and then the kingdom is not to be left to him, 
            nor is it fitting that an infidel king have a Christian people, 
            since through gifts and honors he can turn them away from the faith. 
            But if the same one will wish to receive it along with the others, 
            paying for the expenses assumed, 
            I do not see that he should be deposed. 
            And this if he will be prudent, 
            unless a lapse into infidelity is feared
          </quote> 
          etc. These are 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Rccyxxy" corresp="lca8s8-d1e737-Qcyaa8a">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Nd1e208">John Major's</name>
          </ref> 
          words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-d1e212">
          First, while he supposes the Indians would not receive preachers without a great army, 
          he clearly stumbles, 
          ignorant of how the matter stands. 
          For the Indians are most gentle, 
          and where the Spanish first penetrated into those provinces, 
          a great number of them, with sincere spirit, 
          eagerly entered the ships of the Christians, 
          and entertaining the Spanish in their houses as divine men and sent from heaven, 
          they honored them most devotedly. 
          From which it is clearly evident that they would receive and almost worship the preachers 
          if they reflect the example of Christ and the apostles in their conduct, 
          and are such as the announcers of evangelical truth ought to be.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-d1e249">
          Moreover, when 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Nd1e251">John Major</name> 
          asserts that kings can be despoiled of their kingdoms 
          until they pay the expenses incurred by the kings of Spain in sending soldiers and preachers, 
          certainly he errs. 
          Shall we seize a kingdom in the name of a pledge, 
          just as a cloak which is easily returned when the debt is paid? 
          Furthermore, so that a king may be despoiled of his kingdom under this tyrannical pretense, 
          how many slaughters, how many fires, 
          how many pitiable calamities must necessarily precede? 
          Where has this theologian read of such pledges which bring about the destruction of so many souls? 
          What moreover will the Indian kings think 
          when they see the Spanish, a bearded, fierce, strong, and formidable people, 
          erecting fortresses and building stone houses without royal permission? 
          These things will make the name of Christ hateful to worship, 
          and from them will follow the innumerable evils related above. 
          Did Paul accept such pledges from those to whom he preached the gospel? 
          Or rather did he labor with his hands lest an offense be presented to the gospel? 
          All things, he says, we endure, 
          lest we give an obstacle to the gospel of Christ, 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Rd1e311" target="http://scta.info/resource/Icor9_12">
            1 Corinthians 9
          </ref>. 
          Did he say this for himself alone, as if he alone were bound to give the gospel freely, 
          and not rather say this for all, 
          which is narrated in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Rd1e320" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e737-Qd1e344">
            the Acts of the Apostles chapter 20
          </ref> 
          that he said to the bishop and prelates at Miletus: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Qd1e344" source="http://scta.info/resource/act20_33-35">
            I have coveted no one's silver or gold or clothing, as you yourselves know: 
            because these hands have ministered to my needs and to those who were with me. 
            I have shown you all things, that laboring thus you ought to support the weak, 
            and to remember the word of the Lord Jesus, because he himself said: 
            it is more blessed to give than to receive
          </quote>? 
          Why do we not imitate this man of generous mind?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-d1e349">
          Why, by reason of money or expenses which he pretends, 
          do we give occasion for the Indians to think that the law of the gospel is troublesome and burdensome? 
          Let us follow the footsteps of Paul saying that thus it is necessary to support the weak. 
          That word "necessary" is prescriptive and introduces necessity, as I said above. 
          Therefore 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Nd1e366">John Major</name> errs, 
          who, granting that the kingdoms of the Indians exist, 
          asserts that kings ought to be despoiled of their kingdoms in the name of a pledge, 
          so that when the expenses are paid they may receive them back if they have accepted the faith of Christ. 
          Which is most vain. 
          For let us suppose that they are unwilling to accept the faith of Christ nor to pay the expenses: 
          I ask by what title can they be despoiled of their kingdom? 
          Certainly not by the title of action for business conducted usefully. 
          For it cannot be said that their business was conducted usefully, 
          since from the arrival of the Spanish they are despoiled of their own kingdoms, 
          and innumerable evils arise from the war which it is necessary to wage 
          so that the Indian king may be despoiled of his dominion. 
          Since therefore the business was not conducted usefully, 
          they need not pay the expenses, as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Rd1e407">
            L. sed si ideo, ff soluto matrimonio
          </ref>. 
          Since therefore from the doctrine of Christ no one is to be punished 
          for the reason that he does not wish to receive the Christian faith, 
          nor is he to be compelled to the faith, 
          what kind of example is it to despoil a prince of his kingdom because he does not wish to accept the faith, 
          especially preached by impious men whom you would rather call demons and ministers of Satan 
          and enemies of the glory of Christ than angels of peace and announcers of truth?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-d1e432">
          Therefore let 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Nd1e434">John Major</name> go away with his dreams. 
          For he is ignorant of law and fact. 
          But it is laughable that this theologian says that the Indian king, 
          even before he understands the Spanish language, 
          and even before he understands with what plan the Spanish erect fortified strongholds, 
          ought to be despoiled of his kingdom if he does not accept the faith, 
          by reason of expenses. 
          If the wretched king does not understand the Spanish language, 
          how will he perceive or believe the truth of Christ, 
          and depart from his religion approved by the consensus of so many centuries? 
          Would not one who did this be insane? 
          Are Christian dogmas similar to principles which nature itself teaches and demonstrates 
          to each man, gentile and infidel, by a peculiar light inserted in him? 
          Who is so blind that he does not see these to be the arts of Satan: 
          to despoil an innocent prince completely ignorant, 
          and to lead him into captivity stripped of his goods, under the pretext of expenses? 
          What does this have in common with the charity of Christ or with common reason? 
          The Indian who has never heard the name of Christ believes, 
          at least in a human way, that his religion is true no less than a Christian believes Christianity is. 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Nd1e495">John Major</name> adds 
          that the Indian king ought reasonably to endure this. 
          I by no means think that 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Nd1e504">John Major</name> himself would tolerate these things so impious and crude, 
          even if he were an Indian, 
          if Hungarians or Bohemians whose language he did not understand, 
          even if they were moved only for his good, 
          should despoil him, that is, at their first entrance, of his dignity or kingdom if he were king: 
          all provinces overturned, shaken by warlike tumult. 
          Would he receive graciously with joy that good thing and willingly pay the expenses 
          when already with the passage of time they understood each other's language? 
          I think not. 
          What is it to compel to the faith if this is not? 
          And it is not simple coercion, 
          but with deaths and warlike terror than which there is nothing greater. 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e737-Nd1e546">Gregory</name> says in the place cited above: 
          this is a new and unheard-of preaching which demands faith by blows.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>