<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 42 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 42 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-19">April 19, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-19" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="184-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Hd1e97">Chapter 42</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e99">
          Chapter 42
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e104">
          Here we shall refute the fourth argument or cause of Sepulveda.
          For he says that war can be waged against the Indians so that the Christian religion may be spread 
          and the whole path opened to the preachers of the gospel.
          Indeed I cannot sufficiently marvel at Sepulveda.
          For by what spirit is this man,
          a theologian,
          old,
          and polished in humanistic literature,
          inspired to offer these poisons to the world:
          so that the Indian empires,
          extending very widely,
          might be prey to the most savage robbers contrary to the law of Christ.
          Just as they have been until now,
          to the great envy of the Spanish people,
          who have perpetrated such crimes among those peoples as no nation however wild 
          (as literature records)
          has ever perpetrated.
          Sepulveda indeed strives with all his might to expand these crimes:
          so that the remaining nations of that entire world might finally be destroyed:
          and the just and upright God,
          perhaps more quickly than he had decreed,
          being stirred up by these things,
          might pour out the fury of his wrath and seize all of Spain.
          Therefore Sepulveda first brings forth what Augustine writes in his letter to Donatus the heretic.
          For Sepulveda asserts that Augustine teaches that the nations in the beginnings of the nascent church 
          were to be led gently and mildly to the faith of Christ:
          But afterward,
          with the strength of the church increased,
          they could be compelled to enter into the fold of Christ in the parable of the wedding feast.
          Certainly Sepulveda speaks impiously and errs in many things to the prejudice of his own soul:
          especially in three matters.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e180">
          First,
          saying that the decrees of the church,
          of the pontiff,
          and of the Caesars issued against heretics should be observed even against unbelievers,
          not distinguishing the species of unbelievers,
          which are four:
          Some unbelievers are Moors and Jews living under the yoke of Christians.
          Others are apostates and heretics.
          Others are Turks and Moors persecuting us by war.
          Others are unbelieving idolaters inhabiting very remote provinces.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e204">
          Second,
          Sepulveda impiously interprets that parable of the wedding feast in Luke 14 and Matthew 22.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e216">
          Third,
          he errs in not distinguishing unbelievers subject to the church or to princes who are its members 
          from other unbelievers not subject:
          attributing to the church jurisdiction where it has none.
          This last point I proved false in chapter 6 and following by the most clear reasons above.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e234">
          But as to what pertains to the principal question,
          certainly that evangelical parable in no way proves what Sepulveda brings it forward to prove.
          For he strives to prove that Christ wanted the church,
          strengthened by forces and princes,
          to compel men to receive evangelical truth,
          not indeed by baptizing them with violence inflicted,
          but by overturning the worship of idols and crushing their strength:
          so that they cannot impede the preaching of the gospel.
          Before all else I would gladly be instructed by Sepulveda why God would have preferred violence 
          to be inflicted on unbelievers by the church and Christian princes rather than by angels,
          by whose ministry God often leads unbelievers to knowledge of himself,
          according to what has been handed down by the great Dionysius in the Celestial Hierarchy chapter 9?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e278">
          Again I ask whether that compulsion of which the parable makes mention:
          should be corporeal or material,
          inflicted by angels or by God himself?
          Indeed if Sepulveda with his associates has nothing to bring forth except his own inventions:
          I will oppose that saying of blessed Jerome to Paulinus in these words:
          who if they should happen to come to the holy scriptures after secular letters,
          and should charm the ears of the people with polished speech,
          they think that whatever they say is the law of God.
          Nor do they deign to know what the prophets,
          what the apostles thought,
          but they adapt incongruous testimonies to their own meaning:
          as if it were a great and not most vicious manner of teaching to corrupt sentences 
          and to drag scripture to their own will though it resists.
          These are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e315">
          Indeed,
          venerable doctor Sepulveda,
          it would have been fitting for you to consider:
          that a parable is a certain obscure sentence or similitude:
          according to the opinion of Saint Thomas 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e333" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e842-d1e269@6-18">1st part: question 1 article 10 ad 3</ref>
          and on Isaiah.
          Since moreover parables can be expounded in many ways and receive multiple interpretations,
          and the same thing can be attributed to different things according to different similitudes,
          by the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e337" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l1d3q2-d1e134@4-26 http://scta.info/resource/ta-l1d3q3-d1e202@11-39">Saint Thomas 1a 2ae question 33, article 1 ad 1 and 1st Sentences distinction 17 question 1 article 1 question 3 in the body</ref>.
          Nor is the literal sense,
          on which other senses are founded and under which there cannot be falsehood:
          that which anyone wishes:
          but that which the author of Sacred Scripture intends,
          namely the Holy Spirit.
          But to assign who or what this is:
          is not for just anyone:
          but for sacred doctors who have excelled other mortals in morals and doctrine.
          But of all these,
          none has existed up to now:
          who has expounded that evangelical parable in the way Sepulveda expounds it:
          namely that unbelievers,
          especially gentiles who have never heard the faith,
          are to be compelled by military force by princes to abandon the worship of idols 
          and enter the fold of Christ,
          namely the church.
          And thus concerning exterior and corporeal compulsion.
          Therefore it is great temerity:
          to presume to prove by the said parable:
          that Christ commanded his church,
          when it had been strengthened,
          that it ought to use corporeal compulsion concerning unbelievers before the preaching of the faith.
          Moreover,
          all theologians teach that nothing pertaining to faith or to the salvation of men 
          is found in the sacred letters proposed under a parable or spiritual sense:
          which scripture does not somewhere manifestly hand down through the literal sense.
          So teaches 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e402">Augustine in the book On Christian Doctrine</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e407">Saint Thomas in the first part question 1 article 9 ad 2</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e412">article 10 ad 1</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e417">Quodlibet 7 article 14 ad 3</ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e420">
          Here I would wish Sepulveda with his associates to bring forth from the sacred letters some place 
          where that evangelical parable is expounded:
          as he himself expounds it,
          that the gospel (that is,
          the good and joyful announcement)
          and the remission of sins:
          ought to be announced by arms and bombardments:
          by subduing with armed soldiers and pursuing a people by the force of war.
          What has joyful announcement to do with wounds,
          captivities,
          slaughters,
          fires,
          and the destruction of cities and the common evils of war?
          Surely they will descend to hell before they feel the benefit of the gospel.
          What will those tell who flee to foreign provinces seeking refuge from the Spaniards,
          with split heads,
          amputated hands,
          ruptured intestines?
          What will they think about the God of the Christians?
          Surely they will think them to be sons of the devil,
          not sons of God and angels of peace.
          Would those who interpret that parable thus want,
          if perhaps they were pagans,
          to have the truth announced to them with their house first destroyed:
          and their children led into captivity,
          their wife ravished:
          their cities laid waste,
          women deflowered,
          and provinces desolated?
          Would they want,
          with so many evils:
          so many tears,
          so many horrible disasters:
          such savage fear and pitiable calamity,
          to come to the fold of Christ?
          Does not Paul say:
          receive one another as Christ also received you?
          And a little above:
          Whatever things were written were written for our instruction.
          Romans 15.
          Therefore,
          just as they themselves would not want to be led thus to the fold of Christ:
          so also let them abstain from all violence toward their brothers.
          Just as blessed James and his disciples used this evangelical moderation with their fathers:
          who perhaps were contaminated by worse crimes:
          and were more devoted to the dregs of idolatry and abounded more in barbaric customs 
          than other nations,
          as can be seen in the great difficulty with which Spain was converted to Christ.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e529">
          Let them abstain (I say)
          from exercising such immoderation on other nations,
          the Spaniards:
          and let them use that sweetness by which they themselves were called:
          whether they be barbarians or idolaters:
          or infected with whatever other vices.
          The evident reason for this is:
          because there is not male and female,
          gentile and Jew:
          circumcision and foreskin,
          barbarian and Scythian:
          slave and free:
          but all things and in all things is Christ.
          To the Colossians 3.
          There is no distinction between Jew and Greek,
          for the same Lord of all is rich toward all who call upon him.
          Romans 10.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e556">
          The same says Chrysostom in the Imperfect Work on Matthew chapter 22,
          homily 41,
          in these words:
          Just as there is no distance in the nature of the creation of men,
          no difference is made in the calling to salvation of all of them,
          whether barbarians or wise men,
          since the grace of God is powerful to correct the minds of barbarians to reasonable understanding:
          who changed the heart of Nebuchadnezzar to a bestial sense and again reduced his bestial sense 
          to human understanding.
          It is powerful,
          I say,
          to change all,
          whether good or evil,
          the good lest they perish,
          the evil that they may be made inexcusable.
          These are the words of Chrysostom.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e591">
          Since therefore the nature of men is the same and all are called by Christ in the same way,
          nor would they themselves have wanted to be called in a different manner,
          they ought not to persuade that the Indians should be led to the church in another way 
          than other men.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e604">
          Again it is argued against the distinguished doctor and his obstinacy thus:
          the literal sense of any passage of scripture,
          from which alone an argument can be drawn according to Augustine and Saint Thomas,
          is that which the author of it,
          the Holy Spirit,
          intends and wishes us to understand.
          But Christ by those words of the parable "compel them to enter":
          signifies that he himself,
          immediately through himself or through angels or through men,
          is accustomed to move intellectually and draw and as it were compel to himself by a visible 
          or invisible miracle:
          those who do not know his truth:
          yet with no coercion of the will applied.
          Therefore that is the literal sense.
          Therefore Christ did not wish to signify exterior violence:
          but persuasive force through the said parable,
          which is sufficiently clear from the words of Chrysostom related above and from Saint Thomas 
          in the question On Truth question 22 article 9 ad 7,
          where speaking of this parable he says:
          that compulsion of which Saint Luke 14 makes mention there:
          is not of coercion:
          but of efficacious persuasion,
          through harsh and gentle means.
          These are his words.
          This is to move the hearts of men by infusing into the powers of the soul either fear 
          or sorrow or by afflicting the body exteriorly with diseases or pains:
          or by illuminating the soul itself with the light of the Holy Spirit.
          But God does these things either through himself or through angels or through men:
          representing before their eyes the torments of hell:
          the eternal damnation of the soul:
          and other inconveniences of present and future life.
          In these ways that saying is fulfilled:
          "compel them to enter":
          that is,
          urgently persuade and instigate them to convert through comminations of this kind,
          according to that saying of the Apostle 2 Timothy 4:
          preach the word,
          be urgent in season and out of season,
          reprove,
          entreat,
          rebuke,
          and to Titus 2:
          rebuke with all authority,
          and chapter 1:
          for which cause rebuke them sharply:
          that they may be sound in the faith.
          Thus Hugh of St. Cher interprets that parable.
          And 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Nd1e701">Dionysius the Carthusian</name>.
          For God,
          to impart light and salvation to men,
          uses the ministry of angels and commands them to compel men in these ways:
          by the authority of Dionysius in the Celestial Hierarchy chapter 9,
          who relates that God has drawn very many pagans to knowledge of himself through the ministry 
          of angels in these words:
          but they led back the one principle of all things and to him,
          following according to each nation the angels who function as priests,
          etc.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-d1e727">
          The Lord instructs men through prelates and preachers with the same words:
          whom he selects for a similar ministry,
          just as he instructed Peter whom he was sending to Cornelius in Acts 10,
          and Paul when he sent him to Macedonia in Acts 16,
          and Philip whom he sent to meet the eunuch of Queen Candace,
          upon whom then already lies the duty from the office enjoined to make such exhortations:
          and not to omit rebukes and urgent and opportune insistences.
          And in this way it can be said that very many unbelievers come to knowledge of the true God 
          as if compelled.
          Therefore unbelievers are compelled to know the truth by poverty,
          hunger,
          diseases,
          pains,
          terrors.
          They are also compelled by the Word of God,
          which is most efficacious,
          according to what we read in Jeremiah chapter 24:
          Are not my words like fire and like a hammer shattering rocks?
          Or because,
          convinced by miracles or reasons,
          they are moved to believe.
          Just as we also say demons have faith as if coerced.
          For their intellect,
          even unwilling,
          is convinced by the most efficacious arguments of things which they see and understand.
          For they see many manifest indications from which they perceive that the doctrine of the church 
          is from God:
          who can neither be deceived nor deceive,
          although they themselves do not see the very things which the church teaches.
          For instance,
          that God is three and one,
          or something of this kind,
          and thus they are forced to believe from the perspicacity of their intellect,
          by the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e814">Thomas 2a 2ae question 5 article 2 in the body</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e819">ad 2</ref>.
          Thus 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e821">Aristotle in the book of the Posterior Analytics</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e592-Rd1e826">Metaphysics 4</ref>
          writes about the ancient philosophers that although they denied the first principles with their mouth,
          they were nevertheless forced to confess them,
          convinced by evident and necessary reasons which he himself hands down in Metaphysics 11,
          chapter 4.
          Concerning such interior and persuasive compulsion Augustine says:
          happy is the necessity which compels to better things.
          And Seneca:
          I give thanks to my weakness:
          which compels me not to be able to do what I ought not to will.
          These are his words.
          And this is the compulsion which Christ intends to teach through that parable in the literal sense.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>