<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 32 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 32 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-04">May 04, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-04" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="141-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Hd1e97">Chapter 32 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e99">
          Chapter 32.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e104">
          The third reason why this crime of sacrificing the innocent should be overlooked when it cannot be cured except by war:
          and when some innocents cannot be freed without harm to other innocents,
          is this:
          namely when the guilty cannot be distinguished from the innocent,
          which manifestly happens in wars:
          on account of the confusion and disorder with which they are filled.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e138">
          These things are proven from the words of the 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e142">Lord</name> 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e144">
            Matthew 13
          </ref>,
          when he forbids the weeds to be pulled up lest perhaps the wheat also be pulled up at the same time.
          Do you wish (the apostles say) that we go and gather them?
          And he said:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e165">
            No,
            lest gathering the weeds you uproot the wheat at the same time.
            Let both grow together until the harvest
          </quote>
          and so on.
          Lest wanting to pull up the weeds you pull up the wheat also.
          Wheat signifies the innocent and pious,
          or those who can return to a mindset worthy of God.
          However,
          lest harm be done to these innocents:
          the Lord forbids the wicked to be uprooted,
          but defers their punishment to the day of judgment and this for no other reason than that the pious or innocent not perish with the impious and guilty.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e232">
          Wherefore the Lord explains thus.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e236">
            He who sows the good seed,
            these are the children of the kingdom:
            but the weeds are the children of wickedness.
            The enemy who sowed them is the devil.
            The harvest truly is the end of the age.
            And the harvesters are the angels
          </quote>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e263">
            Therefore the Son of Man will send his angels,
            and they will gather from his kingdom all scandals,
            and those who do iniquity.
            And they will cast them into the furnace of fire
          </quote>.
          Therefore Christ does not want but prohibits the guilty to be judged / punished or pulled up by men:
          as often as they cannot be distinguished from the innocent and thus without danger to them.
          And this is another case in which the Lord has reserved to himself the judgment of sinners.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e287">
          Which the gloss teaches,
          explaining those words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e291">
            Lord,
            do you wish us?
            It consults (he says) the justice of God whether he should do it,
            and whether God wishes this to be the office of men.
            But the truth responded:
            man cannot know in this life what sort of person he who now errs will be:
            and what his error may confer on the good:
            and therefore they are not to be removed:
            lest perhaps those who are going to be good be killed:
            or lest it stand in the way of the good,
            whom they benefit
          </quote>.
          And below:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e315">
            Then truly it will be done opportunely:
            when there is no longer time for changing life and profiting others:
            and then he says it will be done not by men but by angels
          </quote>.
          This is the gloss.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e325">
          From which it is manifestly gathered,
          that those who in the proposed case kill the guilty with loss and harm to the innocents whom the storm of war will necessarily involve in destruction:
          they act impiously,
          usurping the office which the Lord reserved to himself and the angels.
          Thus teaches 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e353">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e354">Chrysostom</name> 
            <title>on Matthew</title> chapter 1, homily 1
          </ref>.
          not in the imperfect work 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e361">
            see (he says) how illicit it is to usurp a work that has not been entrusted by God
          </quote>
          and so on.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e369">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e370">Saint Thomas</name> 
            2a 2ae,
            q. 108,
            art. 1,
            ad 1m
          </ref>.
          where it is said:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e376">
            that if anyone exercises vengeance outside the order of divine institution,
            he usurps to himself what belongs to God and sins against God
          </quote>.
          This is what he says.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e384">
          The same asserts 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e386">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e388">Saint Thomas</name> in various places
          </ref>
          discussing the same parable:
          namely:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e393">
            that the Lord commanded to abstain from the uprooting of weeds in order to spare the wheat,
            that is,
            the good:
            which indeed happens because the wicked cannot be killed without the good being killed at the same time:
            either because they lie hidden among the good:
            or because they have many followers so that they cannot be killed without danger to the good,
            as 
            <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e412">
              <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e413">Augustine</name> says 
              <title>against Parmenianus</title>
            </ref>.
            Whence the Lord teaches that it is better to allow the wicked to live:
            and vengeance to be reserved:
            until the final judgment:
            than that the good be killed at the same time.
            But when from the killing of the wicked no danger threatens the good,
            but rather protection and safety:
            then the wicked can be killed lawfully
          </quote>.
          These are his words exactly.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e437">
            2a 2ae,
            q. 10,
            art. 8,
            ad 1m
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e442">
            q. 11,
            art. 3,
            ad 3m
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e444">
            q. 64,
            art. 2,
            ad 1m
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e448">
            q. 108,
            art. 1,
            ad 5m
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e450">
            art. 3,
            ad 1m
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e455">
            4th Sentences,
            dist. 13,
            q. 2,
            art. 3,
            ad 3m
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e460">
            book 3,
            c. 146,
            at the end,
            against the Gentiles
          </ref>.
          And quodlibet 10,
          art. 5,
          ad 2m.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e470">
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e472">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e473">The same</name> teaches 
            <title>on Matthew</title>
          </ref>
          expounding that parable of the Lord,
          where he gives four reasons for this precept,
          namely that the wicked should not be pulled up lest the pious be endangered.
          First,
          for the exercise of the patience of the good.
          Second,
          because those who are wicked will perhaps be converted from weeds into wheat:
          and detesting their impious life they will be converted to the Lord:
          and from wolves they will become lambs just as we have seen in 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e499">Paul</name>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e502">The gloss also gave these two reasons</ref>.
          Third,
          because many seem impious and yet their mind lacks impiety.
          Fourth,
          because if some impious person is very powerful:
          he cannot be punished without disturbance of all divine and human affairs.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e520">
          An example of this most holy teaching was provided by 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e524">Saint Ambrose</name>,
          who inveighed most bitterly against the Emperor Theodosius,
          otherwise pious,
          because in an angry spirit,
          he ordered the people of Thessalonica to be gathered in the forum under a sought pretext:
          and because they had killed a judge sent by him,
          he ordered both guilty and innocent to be indiscriminately slaughtered,
          which we read 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e544">
            in the 
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e545">ecclesiastical history</name>,
            book 11,
            chapter 13
          </ref>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e556">
            More extensively in book 9,
            chapter 30
          </ref>.
          in 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e563">
            the tripartite history:
            Thessalonica (it says) is a great and populous city in which when there was sedition,
            certain judges were stoned and killed.
            Hence Theodosius,
            indignant,
            did not restrain the weakness of his anger:
            but ordered unjust swords to be drawn against all,
            and innocents to be killed along with the guilty;
            seven thousand men are reported to have been killed thus
          </quote>
          and so on.
          This is what it says.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e586">
          But in our case not seven thousand but seventy thousand:
          indeed seven hundred myriads of men,
          it is necessary to kill:
          among whom perhaps nearly all are most innocent before God,
          at least of those crimes on account of which we judge the war to be just (namely) the sacrificing of infants and the eating of human flesh.
          Again,
          this truth is proven from the decrees of jurists.
          For we read in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e607">
            the law "absentem",
            ff de penis where it says
          </ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e616">
            It is better (some say holier) for the crime of a guilty person to go unpunished:
            than for an innocent person to be condemned
          </quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e633">
          Where 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e635">Bartolus</ref> says that if it is clear to the judge that someone did not commit the crime,
          or that he did not commit the crime,
          or that he is not culpable:
          the judge cannot condemn him even from his own true confession,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e650">
            l. inde Neratius at the end
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e655">
            the following law ff. ad l. aquil
          </ref>.
          And this is what is said,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e659">
            that the judge should seek the defense of the accused
          </quote>,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e664">
            ff. de quaestio.,
            l. 9 at the end
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e674">
            l. si non defendatur,
            ff. de poenis
          </ref>.
          The same is understood when there is doubt about guilt.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e682">
          So also says 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e684">
            Chrysostom on Matthew,
            chapter 1,
            homily 1,
            in the imperfect work
          </ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e693">
            In an uncertain matter (he says) it is better that a prostitute,
            once established,
            escape:
            than that an innocent die.
            For it is more just that an unjust person justly escape:
            than that a just person unjustly perish.
            Because even if a guilty person once escapes he can perish again:
            but an innocent,
            if he once perishes:
            can no longer be recalled
          </quote>.
          This is Chrysostom.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e710">
          From these words of Chrysostom you see that our opinion is most true,
          and that it is a sin worthy of eternal death:
          to afflict and kill innocents so that the guilty may be punished,
          which is against justice.
          Likewise,
          the greatest care must be taken lest under the pretext of punishing the guilty,
          the innocent be punished,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e727">
            l. 2 at the end,
            c. de his qui latro occul
          </ref>.
          Where 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e733">Baldus</ref> says:
          that innocents should neither be seized nor burdened with expenses nor in any other thing.
          He cites 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e740">
            l. 1,
            § tribuni in that title
          </ref>.
          The same one says that whoever causes someone to be seized who afterward appears innocent,
          should then be punished with a similar punishment:
          and thus he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e751">
            on account of this a certain man in Perugia was beheaded,
            which note
          </quote>.
          This is Baldus.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e757">
          It also applies because an unjust condition should not be imposed on one person by another.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e761">
            ff. de regul. jur.,
            l. nemo debet
          </ref>.
          And punishment should hold only its authors.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e768">
            l. sancimus,
            C. de penis,
            l. si pena,
            ff. eo titulo,
            l. ab maritorum,
            C. ne vxor pro marito
          </ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e778">
            c. illud,
            11,
            q. 3
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e784">
            c. Romana,
            de sen. excommunicationis,
            lib. 6
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e789">c. Placuit</ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e791">c. crimen</ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e793">c. nullius</ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e798">
            c. judaei,
            1,
            q. 4
          </ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e800">
            c. peruenit,
            de his quae fi. Maiore par. cap
          </ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-d1e810">
          The same is proven from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e814">
            the canonical decrees in c. denique,
            14,
            q. 5
          </ref>.
          where 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e819">Ambrose</name> says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e821">
            finally,
            if one person cannot be helped unless another is harmed:
            it is more fitting that neither be helped than that one be burdened
          </quote>,
          and so on.
          Where 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e830">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Nd1e831">the Archdeacon</name>
          </ref> says.
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e838">
            c. ipsa pietas,
            23,
            q. 4
          </ref>.
          that no one should grant aid to another from which directly and necessarily follows harm to another:
          and rightly,
          because no one should be provided for with another's loss or injury,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e851">c. primum</ref> there 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e854">
            one must not lie in the third manner
          </quote>
          and so on 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e859">22, q. 2</ref>.
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e862">11, q. 3, si quis vero</ref>.
          And in the rule 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e864">
            no one should be enriched with another's
          </ref>
          and so on.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Rd1e872">l. jure nature, ff. de regu. jur</ref>.
          where the text says 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e460-Qd1e876">
            by natural law it is equitable that no one be made richer with another's detriment and injury
          </quote>.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>