<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 49 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 49 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-30">July 30, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-30" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="210-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Hd1e97">Chapter 49 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e99">
          Chapter 49
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e104">
          It does not stand against the previously stated arguments that the blessed Augustine expounds that evangelical parable in his letters 
          and other works concerning bodily and violent compulsion.
          For his exposition is true but only regarding heretics.
          Their condition and case differs vastly from that of the gentiles who have never received the faith,
          as was shown extensively above in chapter 6 and in what follows.
          For the abundance of divine scripture is so great that each word has many literal senses that are pious 
          (according to Thomas),
          who gives the reason for this 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e137" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e51-d1e2072">in part 1, question 1, article 10 in the body at the end.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e144">
          But that heretics are compelled by the application of force to return to the fold of Christ is proven.
          Since he who has promised nothing,
          like a pagan,
          is forced to render nothing.
          But a heretic,
          since in baptism he has devoted himself to Christ,
          can be compelled to return to his fold.
          For the law of nature dictates that each person must fulfill what he has promised according to that statement of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e163">the Apostle to the Romans 13</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e165" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_7@1-3">render to all their dues</quote> 
          and 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e170" source="http://scta.info/resource/rom13_8@1-3">owe nothing to anyone</quote>.
          And by natural law a simple promise obliges,
          which he who does not fulfill sins mortally as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e180" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c22q5-d1e315">c. Iuramenti 22. q. 5</ref>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e185" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t35-d1e119">c. 1. de pactis</ref> 
          and there the glosses and doctors;
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e191" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1840-d1e1141@5-40">Saint Thomas 2a 2ae, q. 10, article 3 ad 5</ref> 
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e199" target="http://scta.info/resource/ta-l4d27q2-d1e142">4 Sentences distinction 27 q. 2, article 1 ad 2</ref>.
          But a heretic is obliged not only to Christ but also to the Church.
          Therefore he must be compelled to fulfill his promise just as one who has made a vow is compelled to fulfill the vow as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e214">Psalm 75</ref> 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e216" source="http://scta.info/resource/ps75_12@1-6">make vows and render them to the Lord your God</quote>,
          for although making a vow is voluntary,
          nevertheless after the vow has been made,
          it must be fulfilled necessarily as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e227" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t34-d1e210">c. magnae</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e231" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t34-d1e195">c. liceat: devoto</ref>.
          So a free man and free cities can subject themselves to a king or prince,
          and after they have once subjected themselves they can in no way repent.
          For a free man can subject himself to another as is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e246" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e218-d1e159">c. grandi de supplenda negligentia praelatorum in 6</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e251">l. cum scimus de agricolis et censitis</ref> 
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e256">l. 1: § 1</ref>,
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e258">L. iuris gentium, § pretor, ff. de pactis</ref>.
          Therefore heretics who do not fulfill the vow made in baptism can by right be compelled to fulfill it.
          For he who is a heretic offends Christ and commits the crime of treason,
          whose offense is avenged by the Church,
          of which the heretic is a subject and to its head the Roman Pontiff.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e277">
          The root and foundation of this subjection is threefold
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e285">
          The first is the vow solemnly given and the spontaneous confession and promise of faith made in the reception of baptism.
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e295" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p3d4-d1e1193">c. prima</ref>,
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e299" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p3d4-d1e1018">c. postquam</ref>.
          And the following de consecratione distinctio 4
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e305">
          The second foundation is that the baptized person is obliged through stipulation by those words "do you believe in God" etc.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e313">gloss in the said c. prima</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e316">
          The third is the obedience which the baptized person tacitly and implicitly promises to Christ and the Church in baptism.
          Moreover,
          through baptism each person hands himself over to the Lord and the dominion of Christ and becomes his subject and debtor,
          fleeing and alienating himself through renunciation from the service and possession of his former lord and possessor the devil.
          And therefore he professes that henceforth he will live according to the divine evangelical law.
          He is also counted among the assembly of the faithful and the Christian republic.
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e344" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p3d4-d1e1018">c. postquam</ref>,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e349" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p3d4-d1e912">c. ante baptismum at the end</ref> 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e352" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p3d4-d1e766">c. ab antiqua de consecratione distinctio 4</ref> 
          therefore rightly the heretic is compelled by the Church to hold the faith and render obedience 
          and to live according to the law of Christ which he vowed to hold and spontaneously promised.
          For any subject of any prince or member of a republic is bound to obey its laws and to live according to them 
          and to conform himself to the other good citizens 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e373" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d8-d1e149">8 dist. c. quae contra</ref>,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e378" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t2-d1e119">c. 1, de constitutionibus</ref>,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e381">C. de summa trinitate l. cunctos populos</ref>.
          And this is what 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e388">Augustine means when expounding that parable "compel them to enter"</ref> 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e393" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1324-d1e1741">Saint Thomas 2a 2ae q. 10 article 3 in the body</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e399" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1324-d1e1856@5-32">ad 3</ref>.
          And the Council of Toledo expresses this difference between heretics and pagans in canon 56,
          determining that those who have never received the faith are not to be compelled to receive it,
          but otherwise with those who have received it and who depart by heresy from the unity of the Church,
          that is,
          from the body of Christ.
          For these must be compelled to return to the faith,
          which is also read in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e422" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d45-d1e179">c. de iudaeis 45 distinctio</ref> 
          since however ecclesiastical compulsion which is done by holy admonitions and the word of God 
          was not sufficient to compel heretics because the Church in its early days lacked the faculty and power 
          since it did not have any Christian princes who would help and defend it,
          Augustine writing to Donatus the heretic who complained that the Church,
          contrary to the example of Christ and the apostles,
          uses arms and the bodily forces of secular princes to compel to the faith.
          Augustine,
          explaining more fully the aforesaid difference,
          responds that in the Church two times are to be considered:
          the first when it was sprouting with new growth,
          for then it only invited to the faith.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e460">
            That prophecy had not yet been fulfilled:
            and all the kings of the earth shall worship him,
            all nations shall serve him from Psalm 71.
            The second time is when the prophecy has been fulfilled.
            Which indeed,
            the more it is fulfilled,
            the more power the Church uses,
            so that it not only invites,
            but also acts for the good.
            The Lord wanted to signify this because someone would have great power,
            but he first chose to commend humility.
            This is also shown quite evidently in that similitude of the feast</quote> 
          etc 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e489">thus Augustine</ref> 
          and it is found in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e495" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e711">23. q. 4,. c. displicet</ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e498" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q4-d1e711">c. non invenitur.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e502">
          Therefore in the second time the prophecy was fulfilled.
          Therefore in the time when the Church had kings and princes whose arms it could use,
          it compresses those unwilling to persevere in the faith already received.
          But the reasoning is different for pagans,
          especially Indians,
          who not only have not received the faith of Christ but have not even heard of it,
          and thus since they have promised nothing nor are subjects of the Church,
          there is no reason that they should be compelled like heretics about whom alone the blessed Augustine speaks.
          For it is manifest that all such infidels who have not received the faith belong to the first time of the Church,
          when (namely) for converting infidels it used reasons and persuasions,
          and the Church has always used this,
          not arms or violence,
          even if it had faithful princes,
          because the reason for using such means ceases.
          But heretics,
          on the contrary,
          must be compelled to hold what they promised and to pay to God the due obedience and to the Church their allegiance,
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e553">
          but because in the beginning,
          although there were heretics,
          nevertheless it lacked the garrisons of faithful princes,
          therefore it patiently endured the impious attacks of heretics.
          But after,
          by divine gift,
          the kings of the age were converted to Christ,
          and thus it began to have sons and subject faithful princes,
          then using their ministry and laws and arms it punishes and compels heretics.
          And this is the second state or time of the Church to which heretics,
          apostates,
          and schismatics are said to belong.
          And thus it is clear what is the mind of Augustine expounding the oft-mentioned parable "compel them to enter" 
          concerning exterior and bodily violence.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e584">
          And he still expounding nominally those words "compel them to enter" 
          in epistle 50 to Boniface the Count teaches that one should judge differently about heretics,
          but another thing about pagans,
          who are to be gently and sweetly attracted and invited to the faith,
          but not compelled.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e601">
          Whence Augustine says thus:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e605">
            does it not pertain to the diligence of the shepherd also to recall those sheep which not violently 
            but gently and softly seduced have wandered from the flock and have begun to be possessed by strangers,
            when found to the Lord's fold,
            if they wish to resist,
            with the terrors of scourges or even pains?
            Especially if among the fugitives and robber slaves they multiply by fecundity,
            does not that have more right in which the Lord's character is recognized?
            For thus the error of the sheep is to be corrected so that in it the seal of the redeemer is not corrupted.
            And below:
            therefore let the Church imitate in compelling these her Lord,
            who first waited that she would compel no one so that from the faith of kings and nations the prophetic preaching might be fulfilled.
            From this also not absurdly is understood that apostolic sentence where blessed Paul says:
            Ready to avenge all disobedience when your obedience shall be fulfilled.
            Whence also the Lord himself concerning his great supper first ordered the guests to be led,
            then to be compelled.
            For when his servants responded:
            Lord,
            it is done as you commanded,
            and still there is room,
            he said:
            Go out into the ways and hedges and whomever you find compel to enter.
            In those therefore who were gently led at first the obedience was fulfilled;
            but in those who are compelled the disobedience is coerced.
            For what is "compel to enter" when first it was said "lead" 
            and it was responded "it is done as you commanded and still there is room"?
            If he had wanted to be understood that they were to be compelled by the terrors of miracles,
            rather to those who were first called many divine miracles were done,
            especially to those about whom it is said:
            the Jews seek signs,
            to those same gentiles such miracles in the times of the apostles commended the gospel,
            so that if they were ordered to be compelled by such,
            the former guests,
            as I said,
            would more rightly be believed to have been compelled.
            Wherefore if by the power which through religion and faith of kings,
            in the time when it was due,
            the Church received by divine gift,
            those who are found in the ways and in the hedges,
            that is,
            in heresies and schisms,
            are compelled to enter,
            let them not attend because they are compelled.</quote>
          And a little below:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e714">
            but truly before those laws by which they are compelled to enter the holy feast were sent to Africa,
            it seemed to some of the brothers,
            among whom I also was,
            although the rage of the Donatists raged everywhere,
            that it should not be sought from the emperors that they order that heresy itself not be at all,
            by establishing a punishment for those who wished to be in it,
            but rather that they establish this:
            that they not permit their furious violences against those who would either preach or read the Catholic truth by speaking.
            We thought this could be done in some measure if the law of pious memory Theodosius,
            which he promulgated generally against all heretics</quote> 
          etc. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e751" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e605 #lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e714">all these things Augustine</ref> 
          in form
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-d1e759">
          You see,
          reader,
          the blessed Augustine thinking differently about heretics,
          differently about those who have not yet received the faith,
          namely that the former should be compelled by the arms of kings,
          the latter should be attracted by reasons,
          there so that by the faith of kings and nations the evangelical preaching might be fulfilled etc.
          And there the sheep seduced from the flock (that is) the Church or assembly of the faithful have wandered,
          and have begun to be possessed by strangers,
          that is,
          heretics,
          lest in them the seal (that is) the character of the redeemer which the soul receives indelibly in baptism be corrupted.
          When found,
          to recall to the Lord's fold with the terrors of scourges.
          Likewise for the Church to imitate her Lord,
          what else is it than first to wait that each infidel receive the faith voluntarily,
          which if afterward he abandons,
          he must be compelled to return to it?
          All of which the blessed Augustine confirms by the authority of the apostle:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e802" source="http://scta.info/resource/IIcor10_6@5-12">
            ready to avenge all disobedience when your first obedience shall be fulfilled</quote> 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e684-Rd1e809" corresp="#lca8s8-d1e684-Qd1e802">2 Corinthians 10</ref>
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>