<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 45 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 45 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-05">April 5, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-05" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="197-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Hd1e97">Chapter 45</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-d1e99">
          Chapter 45
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-d1e104">
          To these things it is fitting what 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Rd1e109">Augustine writes in the Book On the Christian Life</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Qd1e114">God wished His people to be holy and alien from every contagion of 
            injustice and iniquity,
            He wished them to be such,
            so just,
            so pure,
            so immaculate,
            so simple:
            that the nations would find nothing in them to reproach,
            but what they would admire and say,
            Blessed is the nation whose Lord is God,
            the people whom He has chosen for His inheritance.
            It is fitting that the worshippers and servants of God be such,
            meek,
            serious,
            prudent,
            pious,
            irreproachable,
            immaculate:
            so that whoever sees them may be astonished and marvel and say,
            These are men of God whose conduct is such.
            Thus a man of God ought to conduct himself and act so that there is no one who does not desire 
            to hear him,
            and who does not wish to see him,
            no one who having seen him does not believe him to be a son of God,
            <pb ed="#P" n="198-r"/>
            so that truly in him that prophetic saying is fulfilled,
            His mouth is full of sweetness and he is altogether desirable.
            For if the Christian conducts himself in such a way,
            if the servant of God conducts himself in such a way,
            or if by associating with those who serve demons and idols he becomes their equal,
            God will begin to be blasphemed through him and it will be said:
            O Christian,
            O servant of God whose conduct is so wicked,
            whose acts are so evil,
            whose works are so shameful,
            whose life is so impious,
            so criminal,
            so luxurious,
            so sordid,
            and he will be guilty of that prophecy:
            for the name of God is blasphemed among the nations because of you.
            But woe to those through whom it has been blasphemed.
            God also desires and requires nothing more from us than that through our acts His name be 
            magnified by all,
            as it is written,
            The sacrifice of praise will glorify me.
            This is the sacrifice which God above all sacrifices seeks and loves:
            that through the works of our justice His name be praised everywhere,
            and that God be proved to be the true God by the act and work of His servants.
            But those truly love God who exercise nothing else than that from which the name of God is 
            glorified</quote>.
          All these things are from 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Nd1e241">Augustine</name>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-d1e244">
          From these words of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Nd1e246">Chrysostom</name>
          and 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Nd1e250">Augustine</name>
          it is sufficiently clear how great an opportunity is provided to pagans for blaspheming Christ 
          if war is brought upon them,
          and how much hatred of the Christian religion war inserts into the hearts of pagans,
          who believing that they have a severe opinion about the Gods will think that war is impiously 
          brought upon them by the professors of Christian truth.
          And they will be indignant far more reasonably against the Christian religion and its professors 
          when they come to know that they suffer these things on account of the worship of their Gods.
          For when by such a war,
          which they think they suffer innocently,
          they see fathers deprived of sons and husbands of wives,
          <pb ed="#P" n="198-v"/>
          masters of servants or subjects and vice versa,
          led into servitude,
          most cruelly slaughtered by the Christian people who have not deserved ill from them:
          from such works of Christians,
          what I ask will they judge about these men and their teaching?
          For according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Rd1e295">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Nd1e296">Chrysostom</name>
            in homily 4 on the epistle to Titus chapter 2</ref>,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Qd1e301">For not from words but from actual deeds and from life are the gentiles 
            accustomed to judge doctrines,
            and a little above,
            His speech and teaching is not irreproachable who plots many losses even for the infidels</quote>,
          these are his words.
          But if the religion of anyone is judged from works and life,
          what will the pagans think the religion of Christians to be?
          What opinion will they conceive about Christ the Son of God,
          the true God of Christians?
          Surely what the Indians have conceived up to now,
          especially in provinces where religious do not dwell:
          that Christ (namely) is the most impious of all the Gods.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-d1e332">
          What is the cause that the name of Christ which should be adored is torn apart by these 
          blasphemies?
          The life of Christians and atrocious wars surpassing all barbaric ferocity are the cause.
          Therefore since by such wars and hellish expeditions the name of Christ which should be adored 
          is blasphemed,
          all Christians are bound to flee them,
          since according to Paul 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-Rd1e352">in I Corinthians 10</ref>,
          Whether you eat or drink or do anything else,
          do all things for the glory of God.
          Be without offense to Jews and gentiles and to the church of God,
          as I also please all in all things,
          not seeking what is useful to me but to many,
          that they may be saved.
          Be imitators of me as I also am of Christ.
          And in chapter 11 at the beginning.
          This most holy teaching of blessed Paul is to be observed at all times and in every age,
          as appears from those words,
          <pb ed="#P" n="199-r"/>
          Be imitators of me as I also am of Christ.
          And from II Thessalonians 3:
          For you yourselves know how you ought to imitate us,
          for we were not disorderly among you,
          nor did we eat anyone's bread without paying,
          but in labor and toil we worked night and day so as not to burden any of you.
          Not because we do not have the authority,
          but so that we might give ourselves as a model for you to imitate us, etc.
          Here Paul speaks about the preaching of the gospel,
          and his words refer not only to the apostles at that time but to all preachers and to all times,
          and ought to be observed at all times.
          But as is clear from his words,
          the Apostle by no means said that this model should not be observed with idolaters or other 
          pagans subject to horrible sins.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-d1e414">
          For the Apostle made no exception.
          For if in preaching the faith we ought not to imitate him,
          <pb ed="#P" n="199-v"/>
          now that the church has grown,
          what reason will adversaries assign why we should rather be bound to imitate him in humility 
          and other virtues?
          Since although the church now flourishes with the greatest power,
          nevertheless it is bound to show modesty and gentleness toward all,
          according to that saying of John 13:
          For I have given you an example,
          that as I have done,
          so you also should do.
          And that of Matthew 11:
          Learn from me,
          for I am meek and humble of heart.
          And John 15:
          This is my commandment,
          that you love one another as I have loved you, etc.
          Then Paul in Romans 13:
          Love does no evil.
          And to the Galatians 6:
          While we have time let us work good toward all,
          especially toward the household of the faith,
          that is,
          the faithful.
          Therefore pagans are to be treated most gently and with all charity,
          and in our actions nothing evil should be seen,
          according to 
          <ref>that in Philippians 2</ref>:
          Be without reproach in the midst of a perverse and depraved nation, etc.
          And in chapter 4 of the same epistle,
          Let your modesty be known to all men.
          And 
          <ref>in Titus 2</ref>,
          In all things show yourself an example of good works,
          in teaching and integrity.
          And Peter the pontiff of all,
          <ref>in I Peter 2</ref>:
          Having your conduct good among the gentiles,
          that in what they speak against you as evildoers,
          from your good works considering you,
          they may glorify God in the day of visitation.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-d1e490">
          But if Christians mix everything with wars,
          fires,
          fury,
          rashness,
          <pb ed="#P" n="200-r"/>
          savagery,
          sedition,
          plunder,
          tumults,
          where is meekness?
          Where is modesty?
          Where are the holy works which excite the hearts of pagans to glorify God?
          Where is irreproachable life and without offense?
          Where is humanity?
          Finally where is the meek and gentle spirit of Christ?
          Where is the imitation of Christ and Paul?
          Indeed the thought of this miserable calamity of our brothers so torments me that I cannot 
          sufficiently wonder that a learned man,
          a priest,
          an old man and a theologian,
          with shameless brow offers such deadly poisons to the world.
          And I judge that there is no one truly Christian and free from the crime of avarice who does not 
          recognize that these things are clearer than the noonday light.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-d1e556">
          Then when Christ sent His own to preach the gospel,
          with what weapons,
          with what cannons did He equip them?
          Let us hear 
          <add place="above-line">Christ</add>
          in Luke chapters 9 and 10 and likewise in Matthew chapter 10 commanding them and saying,
          Going preach saying:
          <seg type="correction">The kingdom of heaven has drawn near</seg>:
          cure the sick,
          raise the dead,
          cleanse lepers,
          cast out demons.
          Freely you have received,
          freely give.
          But our preachers,
          surrounded by a band of soldiers or rather of robbers,
          with what mouth will they say to the Indians:
          The kingdom of heaven has drawn near?
          Let them rather say 
          <seg type="correction">the kingdom of hell has drawn near</seg>,
          both to us who will kill you and plunder your houses,
          <pb ed="#P" n="200-v"/>
          and also to you who will breathe out your soul without faith and the grace of the sacraments.
          Will they cure the sick who with most bloody battles slaughter and savagely destroy a multitude 
          of unarmed people?
          Will they raise the dead who,
          having made terrible slaughters,
          corrupt and infect the pure air with corpses?
          Will they cast out demons or rather do they themselves give souls to demons?
          Or by this way do we fulfill the precept of Christ:
          Freely you have received,
          freely give?
          Is to lay waste provinces and having deleted or put to flight the inhabitants to destruction,
          to communicate the faith freely?
          O blind minds of men!
          O calamity truly to be deplored!
          When Christ sent His own to preach the gospel He commanded gentleness to them.
          Behold (He says),
          I send you as sheep among wolves or in the midst of wolves,
          which words Chrysostom explaining in homily 34 in the perfect work on chapter 10 of Matthew says:
          He commands them to have all gentleness,
          and not only that but also the simplicity of a dove, etc.
          And below:
          It is certainly more and more wonderful to change the mind and soul of adversaries than to 
          overcome them by the sword,
          especially since they were twelve in number there against all other men who surpassed wolves 
          in ferocity.
          Therefore let those be ashamed who acting to the contrary pursue their adversaries like wolves,
          <pb ed="#P" n="201-r"/>
          when they see innumerable wolves conquered by very few sheep.
          And certainly as long as we are sheep we easily conquer enemies,
          but when we pass into the nature of wolves,
          then we are overcome.
          For no protection from the shepherd is present to us who feeds not wolves but sheep.
          These are the words of Chrysostom.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e631-d1e698">
          Let them be ashamed,
          let them be ashamed who against the law of Christ,
          like most rapacious and savage wolves and robbers under the pretext of preaching the gospel,
          most greedily plunder the Indian kingdoms filled with most innocent men.
          But the Lord lives whose hand they will not escape.
          Therefore it is not very likely nor probable that the most blessed prelate Sylvester suggested 
          to Constantine to bring war,
          nor that the Caesar himself brought war upon the infidels who did not receive the faith or 
          attack him,
          for that reason alone that they worshipped idols,
          or for the sake of spreading the religion of Christ and removing impediments to such spreading.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>