<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 58 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 58 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2026-01-06">January 06, 2026</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2026-01-06" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="240-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803">
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-d1e97">
          Chapter 58
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-d1e102">
          It is not surprising if 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e107">Oviedo</name> 
          slanders the race of the Indians with so many criminal lies,
          which happens to him for two reasons. 
          For first,
          he was one of those bandits who in the time 
          <add place="margin-left">otherwise of Pedro Arias</add> 
          of Pedrarias penetrated into the continent in the year 1513. 
          For they,
          beginning before all others from the province of Darien which pertains to the Gulf of Uraba,
          devastated the entire continent with most savage cruelty,
          not only not sparing infants,
          women or the elderly,
          but indeed even burning men alive so that they might plunder their gold 
          and divide them among themselves,
          that is,
          drag them into slavery. 
          At that time 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e143">Oviedo</name> 
          was the inspector of the king's accounts. 
          For this is the office of him who is commonly called veedor. 
          And to him pertained a part of the plunder collected from these abominable raids. 
          The wretched Indians were sleeping,
          thinking nothing of the sort,
          and behold at dawn these most savage thieves,
          rather than soldiers,
          having made an assault attacked their houses constructed from straw,
          and having applied fire,
          they burned both houses and living men;
          and when the flames were extinguished,
          they sought the gold melted by fire. 
          Nor content with these things,
          they tore apart with most savage torments the Indians whom they captured alive,
          so that they might indicate where a greater quantity of gold lay hidden.
          <pb ed="#P" n="241-r"/>
          But all these things were done from the counsel and with the consent of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e182">Oviedo</name> 
          himself and the other officials of the king,
          so that they might have as many parts of the plunder as they had sent servants and ministers 
          to perpetrate the impious deed with the others. 
          It would be better for 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e195">Oviedo</name> 
          to repair these abominable crimes with restitution than to defame with criminal slanders 
          and shameless lies a most gentle race,
          most modest and redeemed by the blood of Christ. 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e196">Oviedo</name> 
          himself knows how many Indians marked unjustly on the forehead with iron they dragged 
          into slavery,
          of whom a part fell to him. 
          How many chiefs and principal men they savagely tore apart? 
          And how tyrannically they divided peoples or Indians among themselves,
          so that the Indians might serve not one but several tyrants. 
          He remembers how hard and unjust labors they imposed upon them even unto the expiration 
          of the soul,
          not sparing tender children,
          not women,
          not the elderly broken by age,
          that they might extract gold from the bowels of the earth. 
          He is not ignorant of the most unfortunate end of this impiety. 
          For what might he be ignorant of that is most well known to the whole world? 
          Those regions most cultivated with an almost immense multitude of inhabitants,
          through twelve hundred miles all the way to Nicaragua laid waste,
          devastated,
          and utterly deserted of inhabitants,
          have offered a pitiable testimony to the most savage cruelty of these thieves;
          here 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e197">Oviedo</name> 
          played his part. 
          Indeed he was one of those
          <pb ed="#P" n="241-v"/>
          impious bandits,
          which he himself does not wish to be kept secret. 
          For thus he says in the preface of the first part of his most trifling history: 
          "Thus I occupied myself for your majesty's service in inspecting accounts when and how it 
          was necessary,
          so that I did not fail in war and in the pacification of those regions with arms." 
          These are his words. 
          The sycophant calls it "pacification" to have killed God's rational creatures with Turkish 
          savagery without any or the slightest cause,
          and to have sent to hell countless souls who perhaps would have known Christ,
          with marvelous infamy to the Christian name. 
          Someone will perhaps marvel at the enormity of the crimes,
          but so may Christ be merciful to me and impart to these men a spirit of repentance to His glory,
          that if these things are reported truly,
          they can seem light and human,
          so to speak,
          in respect of those things which the multitude and immensity and gravity of cruelties 
          perpetrated by them compels me to keep silent about.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-d1e317">
          Furthermore 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e319">Oviedo</name> 
          writes in book 6 chapter 8 these words,
          narrating the manner in which gold is extracted in those regions: 
          "I," he says,
          "had gold extracted by my Indian slaves." 
          You see that he was one of those who used Indians as slaves,
          was a leader,
          and he himself glories in that diabolical war. 
          Moreover,
          in the desolation and plundering of those provinces which were called del Darien. 
          Therefore whoever reads 
          <name>Oviedo's</name> 
          history,
          let him know this for certain:
          <pb ed="#P" n="242-r"/>
          that so many and such enormous crimes were committed in that expedition that if the Indians 
          were cattle,
          they could have moved not only good mortals but even iron-hearted men to mercy. 
          But if 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e357">Oviedo</name> 
          was a companion of this impious expedition,
          what will he not say about the Indians? 
          With what vices will he not write that they are contaminated? 
          But what faith is to be given to an enemy and to one who wove that entire history from the 
          most shameless lies? 
          Whose eyes God blinded because of these savage crimes,
          together with the other bandits who were infamous for pride,
          greed,
          cruelty,
          lust for domination and ambition,
          lest he be worthy that God should grant to him to recognize that that naked,
          modest,
          simple and gentle race was prey they had,
          not understanding with what talent and with what teachableness they were endowed,
          how fit and ready they were to receive the Christian religion. 
          And this was the second reason why 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e413">Oviedo</name> 
          wrote so many pernicious lies against innocent peoples.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-d1e418">
          Why did he not imitate blessed Gregory,
          who seeing certain Angles dragged into slavery,
          asked what the province from which they were taken was called;
          it was answered that it was called Dei. 
          Most rightly did the most holy man say it is called Dei,
          for they are led from wrath to the mercy of Christ. 
          He asked what their king was called;
          it was answered
          <pb ed="#P" n="242-v"/>
          that he was called Adelle;
          rightly indeed did 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e444">Gregory</name> 
          say,
          "For he will sing alleluia to the Lord." 
          Thus should 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e448">Oviedo</name> 
          have done,
          namely to think that although the Indians were naked,
          they could be clothed with the garment of faith,
          hope and charity. 
          And it would be fitting for a man who seems to wish to have read ancient histories,
          written however in Spanish,
          to remember that the Persians and Scythians,
          Massagetae,
          Derbices,
          Tybareni,
          Hyrcanians,
          and even the Romans themselves,
          Angles and Cantabrians and other peoples of Spain far surpassed the Indians in vices and 
          savage customs,
          whom these men defame as cattle,
          as appears from Strabo,
          Mela,
          Solinus,
          Diodorus,
          Herodotus,
          and Jerome in book 2 against Jovinian. 
          Yet who ever read that they were rejected or despised on this account,
          so that they were held not as men but as beasts? 
          The gospel was announced to those peoples,
          but in a Christian manner,
          with evangelical modesty. 
          Egypt surpassed all regions in monstrous and abominable cults of demons,
          but nevertheless when the light of the gospel shone forth,
          the grace of God abounded there,
          so that the solitudes and monstrous deserts were inhabited by crowds of holy monks. 
          What does 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e531">Oviedo</name> 
          know whether the regions of the Indies would have had the same,
          unless they had been savagely devastated? 
          For what can the word of God and the grace of baptism not accomplish? 
          Nevertheless,
          if 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e542">Oviedo</name> 
          had applied as much diligence in questioning learned men so that he might know the effects 
          of marvelous
          <pb ed="#P" n="243-r"/>
          efficacy which the word of God produces and the habit of faith and the other supernatural 
          gifts which are most certainly infused into the soul in the sacrament of baptism;
          similarly if he had occupied himself in consideration of how sweet is the yoke of Christ and 
          the burden light,
          and the pious manner and modesty of the universal Church which it has always used in drawing 
          to its bosom those who have not yet entered its doors,
          just as he gave himself entirely in his life to profane matters that he might appear learned,
          who never learned Latin letters,
          surely he would have tempered the curses which he falsely heaped for the most part upon the 
          wretched innocent ones.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-d1e579">
          Moreover 
          <name>Oviedo</name> 
          wrote in book 5 chapter 3 that the inhabitants of the island of Hispaniola were sodomites 
          and subject to other abominable crimes,
          but truly he wrote this falsely. 
          For I am one of that number who sailed first or at least second to that island around the 
          year 1500,
          at the time when the Comendador Bobadilla,
          who sent Columbus to Spain in chains,
          was present there,
          where I remained for several years. 
          And having made a most diligent inquiry about this matter,
          I found the abominable vice of sodomy among them to be either none or most rare. 
          I understood only that if anyone was known to be defamed for that abominable crime,
          he scarcely escaped the hands of the angry women
          who rose up against them.
          <pb ed="#P" n="243-v"/>
          But at the time when 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e622">Oviedo</name> 
          entered that island,
          already the entire race of Indians had utterly perished from an immense multitude of mortals;
          and of the Spaniards who killed the Indians,
          except for two or three,
          no one remained,
          but all had died.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-d1e637">
          But 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e639">Oviedo</name> 
          wove his history or rather trifles from little fables which a certain sailor narrated to him,
          whose name was 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e647">Fernando Perez</name>,
          who guarding the ship never or rarely descended to land,
          and used to defame the Indians in sailor fashion so that by their labor and resources the 
          bandits rather than soldiers might be more lavishly fattened. 
          We believe this to be most certain,
          which God willing I will teach more fully in the history written by me about Indian affairs,
          that all the inhabitants of the island of Hispaniola and of the island of Saint John,
          of Cuba and Jamaica and of the others which are called the Lucayas,
          which once most cultivated,
          now by the savagery of these men are deserted,
          were entirely free from three vices. 
          For they neither sacrificed humans nor ate human flesh nor were sodomites. 
          They learned very many sins indeed from the Spaniards,
          believing that all things which were done by them were holy. 
          But what 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e803-Nd1e689">Oviedo</name> 
          asserts that the Indians are unteachable and incorrigible is false,
          more false,
          as will appear
          <pb ed="#P" n="244-r"/>
          manifestly from the second part of this Apologia.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>