<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 59 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 59 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</title>
          <date when="2026-01-07">January 07, 2026</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
        url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2026-01-07" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="244-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816">
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e97">
          Chapter 59
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e102">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Sepulveda finally contends that Pope Alexander VI advised the kings of Castile 
          that they should subdue the Indians by war and approved the war by which those peoples were brought 
          under our dominion.
          This is utterly false.
          The pontiff granted to the kings of Castile that they should be superior to those Indian princes 
          whom they had converted to the faith of Christ:
          and that they should hold them under their protection and authority as subjects.
          But the pontiff never ordered or permitted that they should subdue them by war.
          For why would he permit what conflicts with the precept and institution of Christ 
          and what generates hatred of the Christian name in the hearts of infidels?
          And what is altogether impious?
          For the will of a prince is always presumed to be in conformity with the law 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e142" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c25q1-d1e190">25. q. 1, c. Sunt quidam</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e147" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c25q1-d1e205">c. contra statuta</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e150" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c25q1-d1e205">c. si est qui preest. 11. q. 3.</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e155" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c1q7-d1e462">1. q. 7. c. Etsi illa.</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e160" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l2t13-d1e301">
            c. litteras. de restitutione spoliatorum
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e163" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t2-d1e210">c. quae in ecclesiarum. de constitutionibus.</ref>
          and there the doctors.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e170">Innocentius in c. Inquisitioni. de sententia excommunicationis.</ref>
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e175">c. quanto de rescriptis.</ref>
          And by the legists in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e183">L. quod principi placet ff. de constitutionibus principum</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e188">C. de legibus L. digna vox.</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e193">c. si contra Iu. Et vtilitatem publicam. L. finali</ref>
          etc.
          But it is contrary to law to compel the Indians by war to accept the faith:
          or by the misfortunes of war to cause them to hold in hatred the Christian religion,
          on account of whose preaching they see so many lamentable evils inflicted upon themselves.
          Therefore it is not to be believed that the vicar of Christ permitted war to be waged against them,
          since this would be contrary to all divine and human laws:
          especially since the care of spreading the faith pertains principally to him 
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e220" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c24q1-d1e309">c. officii nostri: 24, q. 1</ref>.
          Therefore it is to be believed that he wishes what is just and what is in accordance 
          with the precepts and example of Christ.
          For it is fitting that he should act thus as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e231" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t29-d1e271">c. sane de officio delegati</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e234" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t3-d1e407">c. super litteris. de rescriptis.</ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e239" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l3t12-d1e119">c. vt nostrum extra vt ecclesiastici beneficii.</ref>
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e244" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t39-d1e422">
            de sententia excommunicationis c. a nobis col. 2o
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Rd1e249" 
            target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c11q3-d1e1047">11. q. 3. c. tunc vera est.</ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e205">
          But Christ wished His gospel to be preached gently,
          sweetly and with all meekness and that pagans should be led to the truth 
          not by armed forces but by holy examples,
          Christian morals,
          and the word of God.
          So that in no way should occasion be provided whereby His adorable name might be blasphemed 
          and the true religion be held in hatred on account of the morals of the preachers.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e228">
          For this is nothing other than to render useless the coming and passion of Christ,
          when evangelical truth is held in hatred before it is either understood or heard:
          or when innumerable mortals are killed in war waged under the title of preaching the gospel 
          and spreading religion.
          Therefore it must be judged that the pontiff,
          with Christian meekness,
          wished the gospel to be preached.
          But that this was the mind of the pontiff is proven because in the bull granted by him 
          the petition of the Catholic kings is recounted,
          containing that the Indians are a gentle people having some knowledge of God:
          and finally such that if they were instructed in the faith there would be hope 
          that the religion of Christ could be propagated far and wide.
          Therefore it is not to be believed that the pope thought that a people 
          whom the petitioners narrate to be gentle should be subdued by war.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e272">
          And thus it is false what 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-Nd1e275">Sepulveda</name>
          asserts that Pope Alexander exhorted the kings to subdue those peoples by war.
          Now truly,
          so that the matter may be clearer,
          I will add the very words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e285">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Indeed we have learned that you who some time ago had proposed in your mind 
          to seek and find certain remote and unknown islands and mainlands not yet discovered by others,
          in order that you might lead the inhabitants and residents of those islands 
          to worship our Redeemer and to profess the Catholic faith etc.
          And below:
          who finally with divine aid,
          having made extreme diligence in navigating the Ocean sea,
          found certain remote and unknown islands (and also mainlands):
          in which very many peoples living peacefully and not eating flesh dwell:
          and as your aforesaid messengers can judge,
          these same peoples dwelling in the aforesaid islands and lands believe 
          that there is one God the creator in heaven:
          and they seem sufficiently apt to embrace the Catholic faith and to be imbued with good morals,
          and there is hope that if they were instructed the name of our savior the Lord Jesus Christ 
          could easily be introduced in the aforesaid lands and islands.
          Wherefore considering all things diligently and especially the exaltation and spreading 
          of the Catholic faith (as befits Catholic kings and princes),
          in the manner of your ancestors of illustrious memory the kings:
          you have proposed to subject to yourselves the aforesaid mainlands and islands 
          and their inhabitants and residents with divine clemency favoring,
          and to lead them to the Catholic faith.
          We therefore greatly commending in the Lord this your holy and praiseworthy intention 
          and desiring that it be brought to a proper end,
          and that the very name of our Savior be introduced in those parts,
          exhort you most earnestly in the Lord and through the reception of holy baptism 
          by which you are bound to apostolic commands,
          and by the bowels of our Lord Jesus Christ attentively require:
          that when you intend to pursue and undertake such an expedition altogether 
          with ready mind for the zeal of orthodox faith,
          you should wish and ought to induce the peoples dwelling in such islands and lands 
          to receive the Christian religion:
          nor should dangers or labors ever at any time deter you,
          with firm hope and trust conceived that almighty God will favorably prosper your endeavors.
          Thus there.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e396">
          In the words of this apostolic decree five parts can be noted.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e405">
          First:
          That the Catholic kings had proposed in their mind to seek through their messengers 
          and to find certain remote and unknown islands and lands not yet discovered by others:
          so that they might by their industry,
          aid and royal diligence induce the inhabitants of those places to worship God 
          and to profess the Catholic faith.
          Behold the end of this whole matter.
          Which the supreme pontiff himself declares he intends,
          as he ought,
          at the beginning of the aforesaid decree saying:
          Among other works pleasing to the divine majesty and desirable to our heart,
          that indeed especially exists:
          that the Catholic faith and Christian religion especially in our times be exalted 
          and everywhere be amplified and spread and the salvation of souls be procured etc.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e440">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> The second part contains that with divine aid having made extreme diligence 
          in the ocean sea they found certain islands and mainlands:
          in which very many peaceful peoples living dwell:
          and as their seafarers could judge they believed that there is one God the creator in heaven:
          and they seemed sufficiently apt to embrace the Catholic faith and to be imbued with good morals,
          and that if they were instructed there was hope that the name of the savior 
          could easily be introduced in the aforesaid lands.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e469">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> The third is added that the Catholic kings,
          imitating the examples of their ancestors,
          wish to subject that people—naked,
          simple,
          sincere and gentle—to their rule with the favor of Christ,
          the best and greatest.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e491">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Fourth,
          the pontiff praises in the Lord this pious plan of our princes:
          adding that he greatly desires that the name of Christ be implanted in their hearts 
          and that He be worshiped by them as true God in the Christian manner.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e816-d1e508">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Fifth,
          the pontiff exhorts the Catholic princes through the bowels of Christ 
          and through the vow made in baptism by which they were bound to observe apostolic precepts,
          that they should undertake the matter with every danger despised 
          and therefore with every particular temporal good of theirs,
          not doubting success with the favor of almighty Christ who will prosper their plans.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>