<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 28 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 28 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-28">Apr 28, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-28" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="125-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Hd1e97">Chapter 28 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e99">
          Chapter 28.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e104">
          <add place="margin-left" hand="E">Sixth case</add>
          There is another case and it is the sixth besides the five already related and known to all:
          and indeed a new one and hitherto unheard of,
          not to say contrived:
          by which the Church can actually exercise coercive jurisdiction over unbelievers,
          as if there were found those who oppressed unjustly certain innocent persons or if they killed them 
          for the sake of sacrificing them to their gods:
          or so that they might feed on their corpses.
          Which rumor indeed reports certain peoples of the Indian world do.
          And this is the third argument or third cause which 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e136">Sepúlveda</name> 
          introduces to justify those expeditions of his.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e141">
          Whose error in this matter must also be eliminated in what follows.
          Where it must be considered first:
          that the reason for this matter is not that sacrificing humans is against the law of nature,
          concerning which I shall submit below:
          nor that anyone is bound by natural law to free those who are oppressed and led to death 
          <del rend="strikethrough" hand="B">from which obligation also</del> 
          unjustly:
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e163">Proverbs 24</ref>. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e165">
            Deliver those who are led to death
          </quote>,
          from which obligation also the Church is not exempt:
          but because those innocent persons potentially belong to the Church;
          therefore they are under its protection:
          whence it pertains to the Church and to the Pope who is the head of the Church to take care:
          that they obtain eternal salvation.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e188">
          Moreover they would not obtain this,
          the innocent ones,
          if they were killed.
          Therefore it pertains to the Church and to the Pope to whom from Christ the pastoral care of 
          the whole world has been committed,
          to prevent such innocent ones from being killed lest the souls of those perish forever:
          whose salvation must especially be cared for.
          And so to the Church and to the Vicar of Christ as to the pastor and universal caretaker of 
          the whole world it pertains authoritatively and autonomously to exercise jurisdiction in this case:
          not indeed that it punish or subjugate unbelievers by reason of this crime:
          for nothing 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e220">
            to do with judging those who are outside:
            but the Lord will judge
          </quote>. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e225">1 Corinthians 5</ref>,
          as has been widely proven:
          but that it provide what will be necessary to prevent such innocent ones from being killed.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e237">
          Moreover all princes of the world for excusing this sin and similar ones are considered 
          private persons:
          nor can they declare law outside the boundaries of any one kingdom.
          For although any private person is bound by natural law to free such innocent persons:
          yet that is true when there is no one else who would free them.
          Wherefore if the Church committed to some Christian prince or to another 
          <add place="margin-left" hand="F">to free the innocent pertains to the Church</add>
          private person the liberty of these,
          no one else could take up arms or do anything else to free them,
          which is proven by a threefold reason.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e276">
          ¶ First because the obligation of freeing the innocent,
          like other works of piety or charity:
          does not oblige except in a case,
          namely when there is no one else suitable to free them.
          Just as the obligation of giving alms to a poor person:
          ceases if there is another who supplies it.
          A gloss uses a similitude of this kind on those words 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e295">Ecclesiasticus 4</ref>. 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e297">
            free him who suffers injury.
            Just as,
            it says,
            generosity to the poor is said to be alms:
            so it shows that freeing the unjustly oppressed is mercy
          </quote>.
          So it says.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e310">
          ¶ Second because when a superior to whom the care of some republic pertains provides or 
          designates someone who should do those things:
          it would be a temerity worthy of punishment for another to meddle in that business:
          especially if a superior had forbidden it.
          And things done against the prohibition of a superior are not valid by law.
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e327">
            c. veritatis in fi. de dolo et contuma. 32 dist. in § verum
          </ref> 
          to which it is read and noted in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e336">c. nihil de electione super glossa final.</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e339">
          Thus therefore the Church or its head,
          who is superior in the whole world to whom it is incumbent to provide the opportune remedy 
          for those innocently suffering such things:
          if it has committed or shall have committed such liberation of innocents to some Christian prince:
          the rest have nothing unless they act presumptuously to which for such matters they extend 
          their hands.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e359">
          ¶ Third,
          because the obligation of freeing innocents which nature teaches all men:
          and Christian charity the faithful:
          ceases where first those evils have been met.
          Whence since all other princes in this case are private persons:
          nothing else remains for them to do.
          But it is necessary for the Church to proceed further:
          because it must not only meet those evils but also care for the salvation of souls incessantly,
          all obstacles being removed:
          so that all the peoples of the world obtain salvation.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e390">
          <choice><sic>And</sic><corr>And</corr></choice> 
          although <del rend="strikethrough" hand="B">truly</del> 
          we confess that it pertains to the Church to prevent such things,
          namely the unjust death of innocents:
          nevertheless this ought to be done with this moderation lest thence some greater evil arise 
          over other peoples:
          which would be an impediment to their salvation:
          and thus the fruit and end of Christ's passion would be frustrated.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e416">
          For since the salvation of men is the end which Christ intends:
          vain would be every remedy by which the attainment of such an end would be prevented,
          as 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e425">the Philosopher</name> 
          says.
          And on account of this he also says that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e429">
            he who destroys the end destroys every good
          </quote>,
          as we said widely above.
          And that makes 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e434">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e435">Gregory's</name>
          </ref>
          point: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e437">
            what use is it when,
            even if they have been forbidden against long custom,
            nothing is gained for the conversion to the faith
          </quote>.
          So he says.
          And he speaks of unbelievers 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e447">45. dist. c. qui sincera</ref>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e453">
          ¶ And because to free such oppressed ones who are led to death for the sake of sacrificing them 
          or feeding on their flesh could not be done if there be pertinence to the oppressors except by 
          taking up arms:
          therefore we ought most vigilantly to consider:
          tumult / sedition / slaughter / fires / disasters / and the fury of Bellona:
          which must necessarily be present to prevent this evil,
          and prudence being brought into counsel:
          sometimes the Church will take up arms,
          sometimes it will dissimulate.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e481">
          For circumstances sometimes render unjust what is just in itself,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e487">c. sicut dignum. de homicidio</ref>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e491">c. cum causam de testibus</ref>.
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e494">l. aut facta ff. de penis</ref>.
          Which is sufficiently proven by that which we read 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e501">Genesis 4</ref> 
          according to the translation of the 
          <title><choice><sic>70</sic><reg>Seventy</reg></choice></title> 
          interpreters 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e510">
            if you offer rightly:
            but if you do not divide rightly you have sinned:
            be quiet
          </quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e518">
          Discoursing on which words 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e520">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e521">Augustine</name> 
            in 
            <title>City of God</title> 
            book 15. chapter 7
          </ref>
          says 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e530">
            sacrifice is offered rightly when it is offered to the true God to whom alone it must be 
            sacrificed in this way only.
            But it is not rightly divided when there are not rightly discerned either places or times:
            or the very things which are offered,
            or who offers or to whom it is offered:
            or those to whom what has been offered is distributed for eating:
            so that we understand here by division,
            discretion:
            whether when it is offered when it is not fitting:
            or when that which nowhere and never,
            or when a man keeps choicer things or things of the same kind than are those which he offers 
            to God
          </quote>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e564">
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e566">Augustine</name> 
          closes his speech with the words 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e571">1 John</ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e573">John 3</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e575">
            Not as Cain who was of the evil one and killed his brother,
            and for what reason did he kill him:
            because his works were evil:
            but his brother's were just.
            It is given to be understood that for this reason God did not look upon his gifts.
            Which all those do who following not God's will but their own,
            that is,
            living not with a right but with a perverse heart:
            offer to God only a gift by which they think him redeemed,
            that he not help in healing their depraved desires,
            but in fulfilling them
          </quote>.
          So says 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e606">Augustine</name>.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e609">
          To this pertains the saying of a certain wise man namely 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e613">
            God is not a rewarder of names:
            but of adverbs
          </quote>.
          That is to say God does not reward the good that is done:
          but what is done well.
          Whence God did not reward the Jews who crucified Christ:
          although the death of Christ was good: 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e638">15 q. 6. c. 1</ref>.
          To give alms to one in need is a pious work:
          if however I gave it so that the recipient might betray someone to me,
          so that I might kill him:
          it would be an impious work.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e651">
          Hence 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e653">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e654">Dionysius</name> 
            in 
            <title>Divine Names</title> 
            book 4
          </ref>
          says: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e662">
            good is from an integral cause:
            but evil from particular defects
          </quote>:
          that is:
          for a work to be perfect:
          it is required that no circumstance be lacking:
          otherwise a pious work will be rendered impious.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-d1e676">
          Thus 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e678">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e679">the Philosopher</name> 
            in 
            <title>Ethics</title> 
            2,
            after the description of virtue
          </ref>
          says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Qd1e688">
            To act well happens only in one way:
            but badly in many ways
          </quote>,
          that is,
          that for a work to be good it must be according to right reason which is only one:
          but for it to be evil,
          that it fall short of reason,
          which can happen in many ways.
          The cause of this matter 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e704">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Nd1e705">St. Thomas</name> 
            writes in 1a 2ae. q. 19, throughout
          </ref> 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e408-Rd1e712">q. 20</ref>.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>