<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 44 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 44 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-17">April 17, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" 
      url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-17" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="193-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Hd1e97">Chapter 44</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e99">
          Chapter 44
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e104">
          They bring forward that Constantine the Great waged wars against unbelievers so that, 
          once they were subjugated to his empire, 
          he might remove idolatry and the faith might be introduced more freely. 
          But where is it established that war was waged against them for this reason alone, 
          that they were pagans? 
          Or from what is read in the ecclesiastical history book 10 chapter 9, 
          namely: "Meanwhile Constantine, 
          inspired by piety, 
          subdued by arms in their own territory the Sarmatians, 
          Goths and other barbarian nations, 
          unless those which had offered peace either through friendship or through surrender. 
          <pb ed="#P" n="194-r"/>
          And the more religiously he subjected himself to God, 
          the more God subjected all things to him." 
          These words are there.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e139">
          From these words it is by no means clear that Constantine waged war against them 
          merely because they were pagans, 
          so that (namely) 
          he might overturn the worship of idols. 
          For indeed if he had turned arms against them for this reason alone, 
          certainly the aforementioned ecclesiastical history would not have kept silent about it, 
          since it would tend directly to the glory of God and to the exaltation of the Catholic faith. 
          Rather we will be able to persuade the contrary by probable arguments. 
          First, 
          because when the Goths, 
          against whom Constantine moved arms, 
          had very violently exercised the Roman people with arms and provoked them with daily incursions, 
          it is probable that Constantine, 
          gravely stirred by old and new injuries, 
          turned arms against them, 
          not however precisely for the purpose of removing idolatry. 
          For the Gothic people were fierce and terrible with savage cruelty and most hostile to the Roman name, 
          and troublesome to all peoples. 
          Wherefore Constantine most justly waged war against them, 
          since they had afflicted with many injuries inflicted the peoples of the Roman dominion, 
          whose injuries Constantine was bound to repel. 
          Whence it is said in the Tripartite History Book 1 chapter 9: 
          "since that people was prone in wars and always exercised in arms by their multitude 
          and greatness of bodies, 
          they prevailed indeed over other barbarians, 
          but they had only the Romans resisting them." 
          And a little before the said history says that those who were called Goths then most recently 
          <pb ed="#P" n="194-v"/>
          celebrated treaties with Constantine for the sake of favor. 
          Therefore from these things it cannot be gathered that Constantine declared wars against them 
          in order to remove idolatry and draw that people to the faith.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e216">
          Secondly, 
          the Goths, 
          Sarmatians, 
          and Gelones were Scythian peoples of Europe, 
          according to the authority of Pomponius Mela book 2, 
          Pliny book 4 chapter 12, 
          Strabo book 11. 
          But they differed only in that some inhabited the rough mountains and others the plains of the region; 
          nevertheless all were Scythians, 
          just as the Cantabrians, 
          the Gallograeci inhabiting the mountains and ridges of Spain, 
          are Spaniards, 
          as are also the Baeticans. 
          But the Archbishop of Florence in the second part of his history writes that the Scythians, 
          a fierce and savage people, 
          making devastation, 
          burst into the borders of the Roman dominion in the time of Constantine or a little before. 
          Therefore Constantine was repelling injury or inflicting similar disasters in vengeance for his people, 
          not indeed did he wish to lead them by war to knowledge of Christ.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e261">
          Thirdly, 
          the Goths very greatly and most frequently weakened the Roman empire by waging war, 
          and even triumphed over the very city of Rome, 
          conqueror of all peoples, 
          according to the authority of Orosius Book 7 chapters 37, 
          38, 
          39, 
          and Paul the Deacon book 12 of Roman history, 
          and Jerome in his letter to Heliodorus laments this sufficiently. 
          Augustine also in book 5 of the City of God chapter 23. 
          <pb ed="#P" n="195-r"/>
          Therefore Constantine had quite diverse causes for waging war against the Goths, 
          who were destructive to the Roman people both in his own age and in subsequent ones, 
          whose provinces they both harassed and claimed for their own empire. 
          Therefore it is not certain that Constantine made war against foreigners in order to draw them to the faith.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e305">
          Fourthly, 
          beyond the fact that they were idolaters, 
          the Goths were infected with the Arian heresy, 
          as is proved from the Tripartite History book 8 chapter 13, 
          and were favoring a most pestilential error. 
          Perhaps they were waging war against Catholics for the defense of that sect, 
          for which reason Constantine, 
          defending the Catholic people, 
          most justly turned his forces against them. 
          Therefore possibly, 
          with the verisimilitude and probability of these causes being presupposed, 
          those on the contrary side will by no means boast that they make evidence. 
          But what is said, 
          that Constantine penetrated into their provinces and subdued them by waging war, 
          was the mark of a prudent emperor. 
          For since he knew those peoples to be hostile and inimical to him, 
          and that they sought nothing other always than an occasion by which they might most harm him 
          and his people, 
          he prudently penetrated with armed force into their provinces, 
          which war was just by law. 
          For in this case, 
          it is lawful to wage war against enemies (namely) 
          preparing arms and watching for an occasion, 
          <pb ed="#P" n="195-v"/>
          for I ought not to wait for an enemy to wound me first before I defend myself and repel his force, 
          which both natural reason dictates and civil laws dispose.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e367">
          Fifth, 
          it is proved that the people of Hibernia, 
          wild, 
          barbarous and most devoted to the worship of idols, 
          according to the authority of Caesar book 5 and Strabo book 4, 
          received the faith of Christ in the time of Constantine the Great, 
          not indeed compelled by warlike terror from Constantine, 
          but by the faith and diligence of a certain Christian slave woman and finally by a divine miracle displayed. 
          The conversion of this people, 
          as is written in the ecclesiastical history book 10 chapter 11, 
          delighted Constantine more than if the Roman empire had received a great increase by new kingdoms and empires.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e398">
          Again, 
          in chapter 10 of that history it is narrated that farther India in the time of Constantine 
          received the word of God by the persuasion of two servants of a certain merchant or curious philosopher 
          who was eagerly traversing new provinces and kingdoms with a desire of seeing and learning.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e416">
          Sixthly, 
          because it is not likely and thus not probable that Saint Sylvester would induce Constantine to do 
          that in favor of the faith by which the faith would be rendered most hateful to unbelievers. 
          But if Constantine by war attacked nations of unbelieving idolaters who had never received the faith, 
          so that he might subject them to his dominion, 
          <pb ed="#P" n="196-r"/>
          in order to destroy idolatry among them unconquered, 
          and afterwards the preaching of faith would follow, 
          the faith itself would be rendered most hateful to them, 
          as we have made sufficiently lengthy evidence of this matter above.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e456">
          Therefore it is not likely and thus not probable that either the holy bishop would advise Constantine 
          to undertake such a war, 
          or that Constantine himself would assume a war of this kind. 
          Therefore neither Saint Sylvester the pontiff nor Constantine Caesar waged war against pagans 
          so that by warlike terror they might abstain from the worship of idols. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e475">
          From which it is clear that that passage from the ecclesiastical history confirms nothing 
          of the anti-Christian cause which Sepulveda undertook to defend. 
          For neither should Pope Sylvester, 
          who has been numbered among the saints, 
          have persuaded Constantine to something not only useless but even most harmful 
          for extending the Christian religion. 
          For pagans affected by warlike troubles, 
          which surpass every plague and calamity, 
          by Christians from whom they ought not to be compelled but taught, 
          will hold the Christian religion hateful, 
          seeing that there is such savage inhumanity in the worshippers of Christ, 
          raging against them with slaughters, 
          violence, 
          fires, 
          and plunders, 
          and they will never believe that the gospel (that is) 
          the joyful message is announced to them, 
          but that a hellish calamity is sent by demons. 
          Especially since for their own defense and that of their gods they would have a just war, 
          supposing a probable error against anyone, 
          indeed for avenging themselves for evils received 
          <pb ed="#P" n="196-v"/>
          it would be most just on their part. 
          Will they hear the names of shepherds and fathers who wish to lead them to the fold of Christ 
          by Christian charity? 
          Or will they see robbers and thieves gaping for plunder, 
          not for the salvation of souls? 
          Wherefore not undeservedly the peoples will abominate the faith, 
          thinking it is not what it is, 
          namely truth, 
          but falsehood.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e548">
          What has been decided above is confirmed, 
          because blessed Sylvester led idolaters to the faith by gifts and blandishments, 
          as is read in his history, 
          and the canonists write in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Rd1e561" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c1q2-d1e142">
          c. quam pio, 1, q. 2</ref>, 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Rd1e566" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t3-d1e240">
          6. cum in ecclesiis de Simonia</ref>. 
          So also Gregory offered Jews, 
          that they might be converted, 
          remission of the tribute which they owed from possessions of the church leased to them, 
          which is evident from his letter 6 of book 4. 
          How far these things are from war! 
          Very much indeed. 
          For to entice pagans by blandishments and charity befits the precept of Christ 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Rd1e584">Matthew 5</ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Qd1e589" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt5_16@1-19">
          "So let your light shine before men that they may see your good works and glorify your Father 
          who is in heaven."</quote> 
          But to wage war is an occasion that the adorable name of Christ be blasphemed, 
          according to the authority of Chrysostom in homily 10 on the imperfect work, 
          who expounding those words of Christ says: 
          "through those who teach and do, 
          God is magnified; 
          but through those who teach and do not do, 
          he is blasphemed. 
          For example, 
          if they teach well and live better, 
          the gentiles seeing say: 
          blessed be the God who has such servants. 
          Truly their God is the true God. 
          For unless he himself were just, 
          he would never hold his people thus in justice; 
          for the discipline of the master is demonstrated by the customs of the household. 
          Not like our philosophers who speak great things and do not even moderate things. 
          But if they teach well and live badly, 
          seeing them they say: 
          <pb ed="#P" n="197-r"/>
          What sort is the God of those who do such things? 
          Would he tolerate them doing such things unless he consented to their works? 
          Our fathers, 
          as they think, 
          worshipping idols, 
          preserved all justice; 
          but these speak glorious words and do ignominious works. 
          You see how God is blasphemed through bad Christians, 
          and the Lord cannot have a good reputation who has a bad household. 
          Whence it was said to the people of God: 
          for the name of God is blasphemed among the gentiles because of you," 
          Ezekiel 36 and Isaiah 5 and Romans 2. 
          These words of Chrysostom. 
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e661">
          Then in the perfect work 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Rd1e665">homily 15</ref>, 
          expounding the same words he says: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Qd1e668">
          "nothing else scandalizes the gentiles except that there is no love; 
          nothing so converts as virtue of soul, 
          nothing scandalizes as malice. 
          For when they see someone using avarice, 
          stealing while he commands the contrary, 
          and to those who are of the same tribes, 
          as it were using outside, 
          when he commands to love enemies, 
          he will call madness those things which are said. 
          When he sees someone loving principality and serving other passions, 
          he will remain firm in his own doctrines, 
          imagining nothing great. 
          For we are the cause of their remaining in error. 
          For indeed the doctrines which are among them 
          <pb ed="#P" n="197-v"/>
          they would have long ago despised, 
          and they would likewise have admired ours; 
          but they are prohibited by our life. 
          But when we rather more fiercely tear apart the substance of our neighbors, 
          they call us the ruin of the world,"</quote> 
          etc. These words of Chrysostom.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-d1e712">
          Again in the same 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Rd1e716">homily 15 on Matthew</ref> 
          he says: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e618-Qd1e721">
          "Christians win for themselves the benevolence of the gentiles if they are prepared not to do evil 
          but to suffer evil."</quote> 
          These words of that author.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>