<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 60 [Bnf 12926 English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 60 [Bnf 12926 English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2026-01-07">January 07, 2026</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2026-01-07" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="246-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829">
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-d1e97">
          CHAPTER 60
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-d1e102">
          From the first and fifth parts of the bull appears the mind of the pontiff and the spirit 
          which the kings of Castile displayed,
          and the precept imposed upon them that they should accomplish the matter.
          And this is what the pontiff praises in the fourth part of the kings,
          namely the spirit of expanding the Christian religion and seeking new regions unknown to 
          prior ages.
          From the second part of the bull where the pontiff reports the gentleness,
          sincerity,
          and simplicity of the Indians,
          and likewise their aptitude and docility for receiving the word of God,
          he manifestly indicates the judgment by which the third part should be endowed,
          namely that they should subject,
          that is,
          dispose them to the faith in that manner by which it is fitting to subject a most humane 
          people,
          most sincere,
          naked,
          docile,
          modest,
          peaceful,
          and most ready to obey—gently,
          namely,
          humanely,
          and finally in a Christian manner,
          so that,
          having first known the true God through evangelical faith,
          they might finally subject themselves voluntarily to the king of Castile from whom they 
          had received such a great benefit,
          as to their prince and supreme emperor,
          saving nevertheless the rights of natural lords.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-d1e163">
          That the word "subject" ought to be interpreted as "dispose" is proved in this way:
          because to subject those peoples is assumed as a certain means by which they might 
          willingly hear the preaching and voluntarily receive the faith.
          But the preaching of the faith according to the institution of Christ ought to be peaceful 
          and loving;
          but means proportionate to the end,
          according to the authority of the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e182" target="http://scta.info/resource/aristdp-d1e56">Philosopher in the second book of the Physics</ref>.
          Therefore to subject those peoples is nothing other than to dispose peacefully and humanely 
          those peoples to hearing the gospel and voluntarily receiving the faith.
          And thus it ought to be done according to the traditions of the Christian faith,
          because bringing them to the faith is the end and united purpose both of the pontiff and 
          also of the king,
          as has been said.
          And these things are confirmed from the rule of law:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Qd1e206" source="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l5t40-d1e195">The understanding of sayings is to be taken from the causes of speaking,
            because the matter is not subject to the speech but the speech to the matter</quote>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e217">de regulis Iuris c. intelligentia</ref>
          That is,
          speech ought to serve intention or understanding,
          because the gospel consists not in leaves but in the root of reason and in sense,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e225" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c1q1-d1e1098">1 q. 1 c. Marchion</ref>.
          And words are to be drawn to an external sense where the matter cannot otherwise be 
          preserved—the argument 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e237">C. de verborum significatione, L. cum quidam</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e241">C. de legibus, L. cum quaestio</ref>.
          See 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e244">the gloss on the second rule</ref>.
          Therefore those peoples are to be subdued by evangelical gentleness as Christ taught and as 
          their nakedness and simplicity require.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-d1e256">
          Thus,
          therefore,
          those words of the bull are to be understood:
          "you have proposed to subject them."
          For to subject that people to the dominion of our prince through the preaching of the word 
          of God was most easy without warlike tumult,
          which is most alien to evangelical business.
          For it would be to act perversely,
          making the means the end and the end the means,
          which the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e275" target="http://scta.info/resource/ArNeTH-d1e145-Dd1e109">Philosopher calls the worst error in the sixth book of the Ethics</ref>.
          And thus the war would be most impious.
          For it would impede the end,
          namely the expansion of the Christian name and the conversion of those peoples,
          as we have proved above.
          Wherefore it is most manifest that the vicar of Christ never dreamed,
          by that word "subject," that the Indians should be subdued by war.
          For war would manifestly overthrow the plan of God and of his vicar the pontiff,
          namely the expansion of the faith and the conversion of those peoples,
          contrary to the precept of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e303">the apostle in 1 Corinthians 10</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Qd1e305" source="http://scta.info/resource/Icor10_31">Whatsoever you do in word or work,
            do all to the glory of God</quote>,
          and to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e313">Colossians 3</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Qd1e316" source="http://scta.info/resource/col3_17@1-13">Whatsoever you do in word or work,
            do all in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ</quote>.
          Therefore 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Nd1e323">Sepúlveda</name>
          falsely asserts that the pontiff approves war against the Indians and exhorts the Catholic 
          kings to subject them by war.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-d1e335">
          The words of the bull are these:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Qd1e340">We exhort you most strongly in the Lord that you wish and ought to induce the peoples 
            dwelling in such islands and lands to receive the Christian religion through receiving the 
            sacred bath,
            etc.
            Note those words:
            induce to the faith</quote>.
          Is it inducing to the faith to attack the most gentle peoples,
          meek,
          peaceful,
          and deserving nothing of the sort?
          Is this inducing,
          or rather compelling that they receive the faith falsely and not truly from the heart,
          seeing the impiety of Christians?
          Indeed it is more certain to drive them further away.
          The kings are commanded as an end to induce the Indians to the faith.
          But it is granted that they be subject to their empire as a fitting means helping to obtain 
          the end;
          therefore that subjection ought to be proportioned and fitting to the end,
          which is namely the expansion of the divine name and glory,
          and the conversion of those peoples.
          But war is not an apt means for expanding the glory of Christ and evangelical truth,
          but rather that the Christian name be hateful and abominable to those suffering warlike 
          troubles.
          Therefore the war against the Indians which we commonly call conquests is impious and 
          antichristian in itself.
          For neither is that the reason by which we persecute them with war,
          nor have they ever in prior ages committed any fault worthy of war against us,
          since they were utterly unknown to our regions.
          Since,
          therefore,
          war ought not to be waged unless injury from him against whom arms are prepared precedes 
          for him who makes war,
          according to the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e416" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1479-d1e302">Saint Thomas 2a2ae q. 40, article 1</ref>,
          and it is reported from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e422" target="http://scta.info/resource/bnh77h-d1e77-d1e224"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Nd1e423">Augustine</name></ref>
          in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Rd1e425" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c23q2-d1e132">c. dominus noster, 23, q. 2</ref>,
          and the canonists teach this there,
          it follows that war against the Indians is illicit,
          which is also proved from many arguments related in the preceding.
          Nevertheless war against them could be just if they should commit anything from those 
          things which we have written above in six cases.
          Again,
          that war against the Indians is unjust is proved from the words of the bull which I shall 
          subjoin here:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-Qd1e451">And moreover we command you in virtue of holy obedience,
            as you also promise,
            and we do not doubt that you will do it for your greatest devotion and royal magnanimity,
            that you ought to send to the aforementioned mainland and islands good men fearing God,
            learned,
            skilled,
            and experienced to instruct the aforementioned inhabitants and dwellers in the Catholic 
            faith and to imbue them with good morals,
            employing all due diligence in the aforesaid</quote>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-d1e477">
          Note,
          reader,
          what was the mind of the pontiff,
          namely that those peoples should be led to the truth by holy and Catholic instruction.
          Then note what soldiers he orders to be sent into those provinces:
          good men fearing God,
          learned,
          skilled to instruct the inhabitants in the Catholic faith and good morals.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e829-d1e493">
          What do armed robbers and predators of immense savagery have to do with these soldiers,
          mixing all things with fire and sword?
          Therefore it is false that the pontiff advised the kings of Castile to make war on the 
          Indians.
          For it could not have fallen into the mind of the most holy pontiff that a means would be 
          assumed that necessarily impeded,
          or rather completely destroyed,
          the end which God intends and he himself as his vicar.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>