<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 36 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 36 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-12">May 12, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-12" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="160-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e526-Hd1e97">Chapter 36</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-d1e100">
          Chapter 36
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-d1e105">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> From these suppositions it is inferred that what we taught above 
          (namely) that remaining within the limits of natural light,
          that is,
          when human or divine positive law ceases,
          and if you add to these where grace and doctrine are lacking,
          men ought to immolate human victims to the true God or to a supposed one:
          if it is held to be the true God.
          That we deduce in this way,
          since men naturally know that God exists and judge that nothing is better or greater than Him
          <pb ed="#P" n="160-v"/>
          and that all things whatsoever we possess,
          are capable of,
          and are,
          are given to us by His immense goodness:
          so that even if we should offer all our things together with life:
          we would by no means render equal thanks to Him:
          Also,
          the principal manner of worshipping God is to offer sacrifice to Him:
          which is the one act by which we show that He to whom we offer sacrifice is God and that we are subject to Him and acknowledge ourselves grateful.
          Moreover,
          nature teaches that it is most just to offer to God,
          to whom we recognize ourselves debtors for so many reasons,
          those things which are more precious and excellent:
          on account of the admirable excellence of His majesty:
          but according to human judgment and truth,
          nothing in things is more precious or greater than the life of men and men themselves.
          Therefore,
          nature itself dictates and teaches those who lack faith,
          grace,
          or doctrine,
          with every positive law to the contrary ceasing,
          who exist within the limits of natural light:
          that they ought to immolate even human victims to the true or false god,
          if it is esteemed to be true:
          so that by offering the most precious thing for so many received benefits they may be found more grateful.
          For the law of nature teaches gratitude,
          and that we should not only benefit the one benefitting us:
          but truly also that we should repay most abundantly the benefit received:
          considering the benefit,
          and him who confers the benefit,
          and the disposition with which he confers the benefit upon us:
          according to the authority of Seneca and Saint Thomas 
          2a 2ae q. 107 articulo 5o et 6
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-d1e240">
          But the beneficence by which the Lord created us,
          <pb ed="#P" n="161-r"/>
          equipped us with so many gifts:
          enriched us with so many goods:
          proceeds from immense charity and infinite goodness:
          and produces for us innumerable goods and life itself:
          in short,
          whatever we are.
          Since,
          however,
          we cannot repay equal thanks for so many benefits:
          certainly we are bound to provide what seems to us greatest and most precious,
          namely the life of men,
          especially when the removal is done for the salvation of the republic.
          For pagans will think that through such immolations they avert evils from the republic and secure favor and prosperity for kingdoms.
          Therefore,
          whoever immolates men to God can be led to this by natural reason,
          most especially when faith and Christian instruction are lacking.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-d1e284">
          The aforesaid is corroborated by the fact that Dionysius of Halicarnassus,
          in book 1,
          writes that when the peoples of Italy,
          afflicted with many evils,
          had striven to propitiate the gods by offering the first fruits of things:
          a certain old man said that they were mistaken if they thought they were being accused unjustly by the gods.
          For indeed,
          he says,
          of other things they had rightly and justly paid the first fruits:
          but they still owed the first fruits of offspring,
          the thing most precious to the Gods.
          If therefore the Gods should receive the owed part of these,
          there would be an end,
          he responded.
          When they heard these things,
          some thought these things were rightly said:
          but to others the speech seemed composed from fraud.
          Finally,
          when someone proposed that the judgment of the god should be sought:
          whether it was pleasing to him to receive tithes of men:
          they send augurs a second time:
          and God responded that they should do so.
          <pb ed="#P" n="161-v"/>
          Thus he says.
          Hence perhaps the opinion of immolating men spread through all peoples.
          But someone will object that this ought not to be admitted:
          since men are immolated unwillingly and innocent.
          But to this I will respond,
          as I said above,
          that no man,
          however innocent,
          ought not to owe God more than life:
          and thus,
          although by elicited act they are not voluntary:
          nevertheless they are voluntary by owed act.
          For all men ought to pour out blood and life:
          wherever the honor of God requires this.
          Which we Christians are bound to do by divine law:
          and all who knew God in ancient times.
          But a case seemed to occur in which divine honor was involved:
          when,
          according to the law received in some kingdom,
          those to whom the lot fell were immolated.
          Therefore,
          although they were otherwise innocent,
          no injury,
          at least according to the estimation of those who lacked grace and doctrine,
          was inflicted upon them,
          and it is confirmed.
          For indeed every best citizen:
          is bound to pour out his life for the salvation of the republic 
          (which according to the erroneous opinion of the gentiles was thought to consist in the worship of the Gods):
          according to the Philosopher and is proven 
          23, q. 3, c. fortitudo. et q. 8, c. omni timore.
          And Saint Thomas,
          I, q. 60, articulo 5 et 1a 2ae, q. 109, articulo 3, in corpore.
          Et 3 sententiarum, distinctio 29 articulo 3.
          Those,
          therefore,
          who lack faith have a probable error in immolating men to God.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-d1e390">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Nor does it oppose if someone objects that thing is judged to be possible for a man which he can do conveniently without his own destruction,
          <pb ed="#P" n="162-r"/>
          according to the authority of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-Rd1e403">Saint Thomas in 4o Sententiarum distinctio 15a q. 2, articulo 2o ad 3um</ref>
          where he teaches that although man ought to owe his whole power to God:
          nevertheless it is not required of him of necessity that he do all that he can,
          because this is impossible according to the state of present life:
          that he expend all his power on any one thing:
          since it is necessary that he be solicitous about many things:
          but there is a certain measure applied to man which is required of him,
          that is,
          the fulfillment of God's commandments:
          and beyond this he can bestow something to make satisfaction.
          Thus he says.
          Again,
          q. 3, articulo 2o q. 4 in corpore,
          he says:
          the legislator by his precept does not require from man all that he can:
          since he does not intend to order the state of man with respect to one day or a short time:
          but to the whole life from which he would fail,
          if once man should do all that he could,
          etc.,
          thus Saint Thomas.
          To the first,
          therefore,
          I respond:
          that although it is true that God,
          out of His immense mercy,
          does not require from men as much as they can:
          nevertheless,
          not all men understand this.
          For nature does not teach this:
          so that it is perceived by the light of intellect alone,
          such that no man could deny it.
          Just as those things which are known through themselves,
          which,
          once the terms are known,
          all concede without any discourse through the light of the agent intellect,
          like that principle about any thing,
          affirmation and negation,
          and of nothing both of these.
          Nor is it perceived by imperceptible discourse,
          <pb ed="#P" n="162-v"/>
          like this:
          if from equals you take away equals,
          what remains is equal,
          and other principles which are not proven but supposed.
          Concerning which sufficiently through the Philosopher in the books of the Posterior Analytics.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-d1e482">
          Therefore,
          what Saint Thomas teaches,
          since men do not perceive it by natural light alone:
          they require grace and doctrine,
          but infidels lack this.
          But that all things whatsoever we owe in this life are owed to God,
          even barbarians perceive by natural light alone,
          and it is for them a common conception of the mind even without God's special grace or doctrine:
          supposing,
          however,
          always the universal influence of divine providence.
          Wherefore it is not to be wondered at if infidels who lack grace and instruction,
          considering how much men owe to God:
          devise a most difficult retribution 
          (namely) to immolate certain men to Him in honor of God.
          Which indeed,
          speaking absolutely,
          is possible for them.
          It can also be responded to what Saint Thomas teaches:
          that when the honor of God comes into danger,
          then man is bound by divine precept to expend all his power absolutely,
          and thus to expose his life lest the glory and honor of God be diminished.
          For God wills every man then to die for the defense of His glory.
          Which also the law of nature itself teaches,
          even if we did not have God's positive precept.
          For naturally all animals,
          both rational
          <pb ed="#P" n="163-r"/>
          and also irrational,
          love God more than themselves.
          Since all creatures naturally love more Him from whom they proceed and through whom they exist:
          than themselves.
          This is clear by example.
          For indeed if the body is endangered,
          and the hand is a part of the body,
          it opposes itself lest the body be wounded.
          Since the hand is a part and member of the body.
          But this natural appetite has this reason,
          that the happiness of the part depends on the happiness of the whole,
          and the happiness of the whole is more useful to the part or member than the happiness of itself.
          For the part would not be well:
          if the whole,
          from which the part has whatever it is,
          were badly off.
          For what would the hand be if the body were corrupted?
          Therefore,
          since all creatures are from God:
          for God is the good of the whole universe:
          it follows that every creature,
          by love naturally implanted,
          loves God more than itself,
          and consequently ought to expose its life to death for the defense of the glory of God,
          from whom it has whatever happiness it has.
          On this matter Saint Thomas discusses 
          1 parte, q. 60, articulo 5o et 1a 2ae q. 109 articulo 3 in corpore.
          Hence it happens that all Christians are bound to expose our life to death:
          wherever the honor of God is endangered:
          or it is very likely that a neighbor will fall into some mortal offense.
          According to the authority of Saint Thomas 
          2a 2ae q. 3 articulo 2o per totum
          <pb ed="#P" n="163-v"/>
          et 3o Sententiarum distinctio 29 articulo 8 q. 2 ad 3m.
          We have an example of this in the exterior confession of faith,
          to which we are bound of necessity for salvation,
          even exposing our life to the dangers of death.
          Then 
          (namely) when through the omission of this confession of faith the honor due to God would be withdrawn:
          and also the utility to be expended on neighbors.
          And for this reason the saying of Saint Thomas in our case does not proceed.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-d1e636">
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> To the other thing,
          however,
          which Saint Thomas said:
          that the legislator does not oblige man to do all that he can,
          etc.,
          we say that the reason is different concerning God,
          who is Lord of all absolutely:
          and concerning the laws promulgated by Him:
          and concerning men and the laws established by them.
          For any legislator,
          since he has authority to establish law not from himself but from the people or community:
          cannot oblige his subjects through his law to do or suffer:
          except what is expedient for the salvation and happiness of the whole republic or community:
          according to the requirement of the necessity of the republic.
          Having regard that the state of each citizen be ordered and preserved through a long time insofar as can be done.
          But if the necessity of the republic requires that man do or suffer all that he can 
          (that is) that he expose his life to the dangers of death for the salvation of the republic.
          Without doubt the legislator can justly,
          <pb ed="#P" n="164-r"/>
          by his precept,
          oblige any suitable citizen to this:
          and the citizen himself is bound by natural law to obey the command.
          This is proven:
          from what was proven a little above concerning the whole and the part.
          For since a citizen is part of the whole republic,
          and his happiness or good depends on the good and happiness of the republic,
          therefore he is bound to love the common good and happiness more than his own particular good,
          and consequently,
          for preserving it,
          he is bound to do or suffer all that he can,
          even ending his life quickly,
          by natural law.
          <pc type="pilcrow"/> Since,
          therefore,
          the gentiles believe that the universal good and happiness of the whole republic consists in such sacrifices and immolations or human victims,
          as we have proven elsewhere from Augustine,
          Chrysostom,
          and Valerius:
          it is not surprising if,
          afflicted by necessities,
          they immolated to God the thing most precious and most pleasing by their judgment 
          (namely) men,
          as is clear from the examples related above:
          and from what Titus Livy writes in book 2 of the 3rd decade:
          that the Romans,
          when the city was in the greatest danger,
          placated Mars by immolating a rooster and a hen:
          a Greek man and a Greek woman.
          And then,
          given the probability of the error of the gentiles,
          the legislator can and ought to constrain certain ones of the people by his precept,
          in the great necessity of the whole republic:
          that a sacrifice be offered from them slain,
          <pb ed="#P" n="164-v"/>
          and that they themselves,
          by elicited act,
          are bound to will this,
          as appears extensively from what has already been deduced.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e513-d1e765">
          Therefore,
          you see,
          reader,
          that there is some probable natural reason by which men can be induced to immolate men to God:
          and consequently not easily:
          nor suddenly,
          nor by a few words can the Indians be persuaded:
          that they abstain from the received custom of immolating men.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>