<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 25 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 25 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-20">Apr 20, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-20" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="113-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Hd1e97">Chapter 25 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e99">
          Chapter 25.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e104">
          <note type="marginal-note" place="margin-left" hand="E">Case 4</note>
          ¶ The fourth case in which the Church can punish pagans by war or otherwise:
          is when they impede the propagation of the faith essentially and not accidentally,
          by word or deed raging against those who wish to embrace it:
          or who have already embraced it,
          or certainly try to accomplish this by entreaties or gifts.
          For such injuries obstructing the expansion of the faith,
          and inflicted upon members of the Church:
          the Church can coerce by natural law and suppress by military force through Christian princes.
          Nor can such evil be remedied in any other way,
          as is evident from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e140">many passages at 23. q. 8</ref>.
          Nor does it accord with law and equity that the Church should suffer men initiated in Christian mysteries,
          to withdraw from Christian profession by gifts,
          blandishments,
          or threats.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e155">
          This is also proven because all princes or governors of republics:
          are bound to protect their subjects from all injury:
          and to take up arms against their oppressors,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e165">ff. de dolo. l. cum quis</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e171">de ordi. cognitio. c. 2</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e173">de restitu. spolia. c. 1</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e178">de appella. c. dilectis</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e184">23. q. 2. c. dominus noster</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e187">q. 8. c. scire vos oportet</ref>.
          So note 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e190">Innocent and Hostiensis in d. c. dilectis</ref>.
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e195">Hostiensis de tregua et pace, c. 1</ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e202">
          Therefore,
          the pope,
          since he is prince and head of the Catholic Church,
          is bound to protect all Christians living everywhere and to defend them from all injury,
          under whatever prince they live:
          so that they not fall away under any oppression.
          Which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e217">Pope Leo signifies in c. scire vos oportet</ref>,
          that 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e222">
            we never permit our men to be oppressed by anyone,
            but (if any necessity occurs) we personally avenge them.
            Because we ought to be avengers of our flock in all things,
            and their chief helpers
          </quote>.
          These words are there.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e237">
          Again:
          when Christians through the work of unbelievers renounce the worship of Christ:
          they diminish what was already inserted into the body of Christ and the Christian Church,
          and by such renunciation the name of Christ to be adored is blasphemed:
          the pope and any Christian prince is bound to avenge such injury,
          indeed any particular person is at least bound to impede it.
          For what is committed against divine religion is inflicted as an injury upon all,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e263">l. manichaeos, C. de hereticis</ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e266">
          ¶ Moreover,
          when pagans impede those who wish to receive the Christian faith from receiving it:
          they inflict great injury upon the Catholic Church,
          which is evident thus,
          first.
          For the will to receive the Christian faith,
          just as in other works of virtue,
          is just:
          generating no prejudice against anyone:
          for pagan princes if they receive the word of God do not lose their kingdoms or dominion:
          on the contrary,
          their possession is rendered more secure and more legitimately confirmed:
          and cities instructed in the knowledge of truth and good morals:
          will be rendered most flourishing,
          by the strength of the holy sacraments which are exercised there.
          Therefore,
          those punishing or prohibiting the execution of this will inflict injury upon the Christian Church and upon those who wish it,
          against natural justice.
          Therefore the Church can punish them.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e312">
          Secondly it is proven because the care of the whole world,
          which both faithful and infidels inhabit,
          has been divinely committed to the pope:
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e318">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Nd1e319">Chrysostom</name>
            teaches this in his homily 87 on John
          </ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e325">
            For when Christ had communicated great things to Peter,
            he committed to him the care of the terrestrial orb
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e333">
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e335">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Nd1e336">Saint Bernard</name>
            in book 2 of On Consideration to Pope Eugene
          </ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e341">
            Therefore your privilege stands unshaken for you:
            both in the keys given and in the sheep entrusted.
            Accept something which nonetheless confirms your prerogative:
            the disciples were sailing and the Lord appeared on the shore.
            Peter knowing that it was the Lord cast himself into the sea and thus came to him,
            the others coming by boat John last.
            What is this?
            Surely a sign of singular power and Peter's pontificate:
            by which he received for governing not one boat as the others each their own,
            but the very world itself
          </quote>.
          These words of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Nd1e370">Bernard</name>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e373">
          And Saint 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e377">
            Pope Leo in sermon 
            <choice>
              <sic>3</sic>
              <corr>
                4
                <note>Modern numbering from PL 54:149–50.</note>
              </corr>
            </choice>
          </ref>
          of his ordination,
          exalting the excellences of Peter,
          says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e388">
            One Peter is chosen who is placed before both the calling of all nations and all the apostles and all parts of the Church
          </quote>.
          These are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e398">
          Therefore,
          since the nations of the whole world have been committed to Peter and his successors,
          and are subject to the Church:
          some indeed actually,
          others habitually and potentially,
          and the care of drawing nations to the knowledge of truth pertains to the Roman Pontiff:
          it is manifest that the war is just by which the Church coerces infidels impeding the propagation of the faith and prohibiting anyone from receiving the Christian religion.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e421">
          Hence it happens that any pagan prince can be compelled by war to have the Gospel preached in his dominion.
          Not indeed from the sin which they commit by prohibiting the preaching of the Gospel,
          which canonists assert:
          for the Church does not punish their sins,
          as is already plain above:
          but because they maliciously,
          without legitimate cause,
          as we said essentially,
          impede the expansion of Evangelical truth which Christ commanded to be announced to all nations.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e445">
          They also impede the benefit of souls who,
          having heard the word of God,
          will receive it.
          Wherefore the Church,
          to which pertains the care of the nations of the whole world regarding the announcement of truth,
          justly wages war against those prohibiting the Gospel from being preached in their dominion.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e461">
          And thus what the doctors write about this matter should be understood,
          especially 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e467">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Nd1e468">Cajetan</name>
            2 2. q. 10. ar. 8
          </ref>,
          where he asserts the Church can justly wage war against infidels killing preachers:
          for those forbidding the preaching of the Gospel also oppose the expansion and propagation of the faith.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e483">
          ¶ But it is necessary to remember that this is true when pagans,
          knowing what is preached to them,
          kill 
          <add place="above-line" hand="B">preachers</add>
          maliciously and because of the hatred which they always bear toward the faith itself:
          such pagans are Turks and Moors who are not ignorant of Christian dogmas.
          If however they did not kill them knowingly and maliciously and essentially as preachers of the Gospel,
          but from hatred of the Christian people,
          from whom perhaps they had received great injuries with savage and fierce violence:
          just as the Indians killed some innocent preachers,
          not indeed because they were preachers,
          but because from the Spanish people they and theirs and all Indian nations 
          <add place="above-line" hand="B">received damages</add>
          <del rend="strikethrough" hand="B">
            the most savage of all peoples and judged by the best right to be barbarous and savage with truculent cruelty,
            since from them so many savage and 
          </del>
          <add place="above line" hand="B">and from the ages</add>
          unheard-of evils,
          <del rend="strikethrough" hand="B">they received</del>:
          not only cities having been devastated,
          but also kingdoms and the greatest regions.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e554">
          An innumerable and unthinkable multitude of mortals having been slaughtered,
          kings and princes having been despoiled of great principalities,
          dominions,
          and royal honors:
          peoples having been led into servitude.
          Therefore such people,
          by not receiving preachers or even cruelly killing them,
          do not impede the preaching of the Gospel essentially,
          but accidentally and beyond their intention,
          and the cause per accidens is outside the rules.
          And judgment about things should not be given according to what is per accidens,
          but per se,
          from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e582">
            Book 2 of the Physics
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e587">Book 4 of the Metaphysics 9</ref>.
          But what is beyond intention does not deserve corporal or severe 
          <choice>
            <sic>ponam</sic>
            <corr>punishment</corr>
          </choice>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e598">
          Therefore,
          when the Indians,
          afflicted by so many horrendous evils,
          see that preachers are men of the same nation and language,
          with white color and 
          <del rend="strikethrough" hand="B">bearded</del>,
          mixed with their enemies the Spanish and treating with them most familiarly:
          they will necessarily be ignorant:
          who might be servants of God?
          And again,
          who might be ministers and instruments of Satan?
          They will also be ignorant where the preachers are heading,
          but truly where the other Spanish,
          with whom they most justly wage war?
          What do we want to do to the Indians?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e631">
          Should they,
          as soon as they hear preachers admonishing them to acknowledge the true God,
          testifying that they are not of that crowd which harms them,
          immediately give credence to those who,
          having been summoned a thousand times by faithless men to Spanish camps after giving their word,
          were slaughtered and paid the penalties of their levity?
          Does an Indian anywhere receive a benefit from a Spanish man?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e651">
          Therefore it surpasses all astonishment and savors of miserable ignorance to affirm that the Indians can be attacked by war,
          even if they kill two hundred thousand preachers,
          and even if they killed 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Nd1e661">the Apostle Paul</name>
          himself and the other disciples of Christ evangelizing.
          For such a war would savor of savage barbarism and more than Scythian savagery:
          and should be called a war of the devil rather than Christian.
          And the Indians waging war against the Spanish conducting affairs thus would deserve to be adorned with the most exquisite praises by any wise philosophers.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e686">
          <add place="margin-left" hand="F">note</add>
          Indeed,
          I would dare to affirm that war cannot be justly but rather unjustly waged against Indian princes,
          if,
          fearing for their possessions,
          they are unwilling to receive preachers accompanied by fierce and barbarous men,
          even in lands or provinces where the savage 
          <seg type="correction" hand="B">
            tyranny
            <subst>
              <del rend="strikethrough">de</del>
              <add place="above-line">s</add>
            </subst>
          </seg>
          of Christians is not yet known.
          For he will not fear rashly for the safety of his kingdom if he receives a foreign people,
          even merely formidable in appearance.
          For any prince is bound to provide for the safety of his kingdom,
          as I have taught more fully elsewhere.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e729">
          Therefore cease,
          Christians,
          to flatter yourselves with these pretenses:
          do not associate your insatiable greed with diabolic spirit by the spilled blood of a most innocent people.
          Let those be silent who,
          swollen with foolish erudition,
          give courage to tyrants to persecute most innocent sheep,
          objecting that they kill preachers of the faith,
          because it is not formally true,
          but rather those who give the cause kill them.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e754">
          For they do not know what the Gospel is,
          what a preacher is:
          they kill those not as preachers,
          but as Spanish men mixed with the rest of that savage people,
          their enemies.
          Most religious men will certainly be crowned by Christ:
          but the Spanish themselves will be said to have killed them by their crimes,
          defaming the Gospel and impeding the propagation of the faith.
          But the Indians,
          in my judgment,
          are in no way guilty before the Supreme Judge,
          because,
          being ignorant and harassed by so many evils,
          they descend to that crime.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e788">
          ¶ It should also be noted that war for this cause is perhaps just against infidels when princes or kings alone maliciously impede the propagation or preaching of the Gospel:
          but if both princes and the whole people,
          precisely from love and devotion to their religion,
          are unwilling to hear or admit Christian preachers,
          then they cannot in any way be compelled by war to admit them.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e819">
          For they oppose divine words.
          For Christ said:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e823">
            Going,
            teach all nations
          </quote>,
          namely those willing to hear:
          do not inflict violence on those unwilling to hear.
          You will find no saying either in sacred scriptures or uttered by holy doctors,
          you will adduce no argument by which,
          being supported,
          we may without reproach compel infidels unwilling to hear the doctrine of Christ to do so.
          Whence,
          acting thus,
          we would offend Christ,
          whose precious death would be rendered fruitless.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e848">
          For when infidels,
          especially those who have always lacked the teaching of truth,
          are led by certain probable reasons to the cultivation and love,
          indeed defense,
          of their gods and rite of ancient religion,
          moreover,
          so that they may consult for the peace,
          liberty,
          and safety of the whole state of their present and future republic,
          they are unwilling to admit foreign and unknown peoples in their kingdoms or lands,
          and thus neither to receive preachers of the faith nor to hear their doctrine,
          even from zeal for their religion:
          if on this occasion alone they should be attacked by war,
          which indeed is an ocean of all evils,
          by which,
          they having been subdued and after so many slaughters,
          so many irreparable evils,
          pains,
          groans,
          
          <choice>
            <sic>weepings</sic>
            <corr>tears</corr>
          </choice>,
          and bitterness having been inflicted.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e895">
          Granted that,
          thus compelled,
          they now hear the Gospel:
          with what mind,
          I ask,
          will they listen to evangelical truth?
          In what way will they understand it?
          With what will they love it?
          How will they give credence to the proofs of Christian mildness and truth?
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e911">
          <add place="margin-right" hand="F">
            it should be noted that in no way is it fitting that preachers should go to evangelize together with armed soldiers
          </add>
          ¶ Indeed,
          I speak boldly and am not ashamed to bring forth these things,
          that if preachers,
          accompanied by the clash of arms,
          should announce the Gospel to any people,
          by that very fact they are unworthy that credence be given to their words.
          For what has the Gospel to do with cannons?
          What has the announcer of the Gospel to do with armed robbers?
          Indeed,
          those believing such preachers would be most vain and most foolish rather than prudent:
          and those spurning their words could be somewhat excused before God.
          For they would not be bound to give credence to the apostles or to Christ our Redeemer himself evangelizing in this manner.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e948">
          Miracles established credence in the words of Christ:
          and unless Christ had performed visible or invisible miracles,
          men would not have been guilty of the crime that they had not believed him.
          For no one is bound to what is beyond his powers,
          unless in the manner by which it is made possible for him.
          But to believe is beyond the natural power of man.
          Whence it proceeds from the gift of God,
          according to that of 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e969">the Apostle to the Ephesians 2</ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e971">
            By grace you have been saved through faith,
            and this not from yourselves.
            For it is the gift of God
          </quote>.
          From 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e979">Philippians 1</ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e981">
            To you it has been given not only to believe in him,
            but also to suffer for him
          </quote>.
          Therefore man is bound to believe according as he is aided by God to believe.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e993">
          Someone is aided by God to believe in three ways:
          either by secret inspiration,
          or by teaching,
          or by miracles,
          which three we interpret as miracles of God.
          If these had been lacking,
          the whole world would be excused if it had not believed.
          So the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e1006">Savior teaches in John 15</ref>.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e1011">
            If I had not come and spoken to them,
            they would not have sin
          </quote>,
          namely of infidelity,
          according to Augustine.
          Likewise 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e1020">in the same place</ref>:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Qd1e1022">
            If I had not done among them the works which no one else did,
            they would not have sin
          </quote>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e1031">
          
          <choice>
            <sic>If</sic>
            <corr>Thus</corr>
          </choice>
          the Lord God had commanded the Jews not to believe anyone affirming himself sent by God,
          unless either he performed signs or predicted future things in the name of the Lord.
          Thus we read in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e1043">Deuteronomy 8</ref>.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e1049">Saint Thomas writes about this in Quodlibet 2, article 6</ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-Rd1e1054">Abulensis on Matthew chapter 10</ref>,
          question 21.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e1061">
          ¶ Therefore,
          since an army of armed men,
          especially unexpected,
          is at first sight formidable to all men by its very nature,
          even if the soldiers do not extend their hands to the acts of war which they are accustomed to perpetrate,
          namely:
          slaughtering,
          despoiling,
          plundering,
          and exercising other savage acts,
          and as much as it abhors natural reason,
          peace,
          tranquility,
          humility,
          Christian mildness,
          meekness,
          the teaching and miracles of Christ:
          it follows that if the apostles,
          accompanied by an army of armed men,
          had gone so that they might compel nations by terror to hear the Gospel,
          especially if they exercised acts of war,
          indeed if Christ himself had been thus accompanied for preaching,
          unless he had aided the hearers by miracles or internal inspiration,
          without doubt their words would lack credence,
          nor would infidels be bound to believe their doctrine,
          but rather they would rightly have waged most just war as against public enemies.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e368-d1e1109">
          All these things are manifest from the teaching of Christ and from natural reason itself:
          they appear no less from very many truths demonstrated above.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>