<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 17 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 17 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-12-05">Dec 05, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-12-05" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="82-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Hd1e97">Chapter 17 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e99">
          Chapter 17.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e104">
          As to the other matter which 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e108">
            Innocent in the said chapter which is on vows
          </ref>
          adds,
          namely that it pertains to the pope alone to punish a gentile who has only the natural law if he worships idols 
          (because he says 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Qd1e120">
            it is natural to worship one and only God the creator and not creatures
          </quote>
          , 
          these are his words).
          We say,
          with due respect to so great a teacher,
          that his opinion,
          if understood without distinctions,
          suffers many contrary arguments.
          For the clarification of this matter it must be presupposed:
          that here we intend to speak of infidels whom sacred scripture calls nations or gentiles,
          that is those who were or are without law,
          and have not yet heard anything of the catholic faith nor believed.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e148">
          They are called gentiles because they are as they were born (that is) 
          as they descended in the flesh under sin (that is) 
          serving idols and not yet regenerated:
          therefore they were first called gentiles.
          According to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e158">
            Isidore book 8. c. 10. of the Etymologies
          </ref>
          .
          For the world was full of these when Christ came:
          and the apostles began to preach.
          And by our doctors they are called infidels privatively or negatively:
          because they are naturally capable of having faith and do not have it.
          Of this kind are all whom we call western and southern Indians.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e180">
          I said if understood without distinctions:
          because in some infidels (namely) 
          dwelling in the lands of the church or its members:
          and in certain cases it would pertain to the pope to punish those worshipping idols,
          as you can fully gather from what has been said and will be said below.
          With these things thus presupposed we respond with the following conclusion.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e201">
          Conclusion.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e206">
          Infidels (of whom our present discourse concerns) 
          would be punished illicitly,
          at least by human judgment,
          merely because they worship idols.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e219">
          The conclusion is proved thus.
          No one can be licitly punished,
          at least by human judgment,
          who is invincibly or probably ignorant that the act which he does is prohibited:
          or that what he omits is commanded,
          even concerning faith.
          But the infidels of whom we speak,
          worshipping idols,
          are invincibly or probably ignorant.
          Therefore they would be punished illicitly,
          at least by human judgment,
          merely because they worship idols.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e246">
          The consequence is clear with the major premise,
          because whoever invincibly or probably performs some act prohibited to him or omits what is commanded to him is excused from fault.
          The reason for this is 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e259">
            according to Saint Thomas:
            because such ignorance is the cause of the act or omission and therefore causes involuntariness.
            But fault or sin is not unless it be voluntary.
            Whence it always excuses unless the ignorance itself be a sin.
            Ignorance is a sin when someone is ignorant of those things which he is bound to know,
            and can know.
            As appears in the constitution or mandate of the pope which all are bound to know in their own way:
          </ref>
          
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e285">
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e287">
            if anyone is ignorant through negligence:
            he is not excused from fault if he acts against it.
            But if anyone has a sufficient impediment on account of which he could not know:
            for instance if he was in prison or in foreign lands,
            to which the constitution did not reach:
            or on account of something similar:
            such ignorance excuses so that he does not sin.
            For no one sins in that which he could not avoid.
          </ref>
          These are 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e310" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1137-d1e895@5-27 http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1137-d1e907@5-31">
            Saint Thomas's words 1a 2ae. q. 90. ar. 4. ad 2 and 3
          </ref>
          .
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e315">
            de veritate q. 17. a. 3. c.
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e320">
            Quodlibetal 1. ar. 19
          </ref>
          .
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e323">
          According to the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e325" target="http://scta.info/resource/cice-l1t2-d1e134">
            canonists c. cognoscentes
          </ref>
          with its material 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e334">
            de constitutionibus
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e336" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e1823">
            ff. de iuris et facti ignorantia
          </ref>
          with what is noted there by the legists.
          But without fault no one can licitly be punished by human judgment:
          at least with the punishment of scourging so that he be killed or mutilated,
          as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e347" target="http://scta.info/resource/TAca84-d1e1830-d1e1150@55-71">
            Saint Thomas teaches 2a 2ae q. 108. final article
          </ref>
          .
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e354">
          And according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e356" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p1d56-d1e220">
            the laws as 56th distinction c. satis peruersum
          </ref>
          .
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e3s4" target="http://scta.info/resource/gd-p2c16q7-d1e691">
            16, q. 7. c. inventum
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e365">
            de restitutione spoliatorum, c. conquerente
          </ref>
          .
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e370" target="http://scta.info/resource/bgy6gt-d1e965-d1e718">
            ff. ad legem aquiliam, l. si putator
          </ref>
          .
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e372" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e6135-Dd1e326">
            Cod. de poenis. l. sancimus
          </ref>
          .
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e377" target="http://scta.info/resource/azsw2e-d1e115-Dd1e115">
            Cod. ne sacrum baptisma reiteretur, l. 2
          </ref>
          ,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e382" target="http://scta.info/resource/wef6td-d1e1612-d1e265">
            the rule sine culpa. sixth book
          </ref>
          .
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e388">
          The minor premise is proved first thus:
          he is invincibly ignorant and thus excused from fault:
          who cannot overcome that ignorance either by himself or by questioning others.
          But such infidels cannot by themselves divine those things which are of faith since they are above every faculty of nature:
          nor do they have anyone whom they might question or by whom they might be taught,
          according to the common course of nature.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e419">
          Therefore those worshipping idols are invincibly ignorant.
          The minor premise of this argument is clear:
          because the first principle or first truth which must be had concerning the true God:
          is that God is one and alone.
          But that God exists is not self-evident,
          and much less that he is unique or alone:
          because it is not implanted in the nature of things so that,
          the terms being known,
          one would immediately without any reasoning assent to that proposition:
          God exists and is alone:
          just as when we see a whole and a part we immediately recognize that every whole is greater than its part.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e456">
          Whence this proposition:
          God exists and is unique:
          is not self-evident:
          although it is true and necessary:
          but we hold it from faith.
          Likewise 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e464">
            that which is denied by many conceiving the terms:
            is not self-evident
          </ref>
          .
          But that God exists:
          is of this kind as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e472">
            Psalm 13
          </ref>
          .
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Qd1e474">
            The fool said in his heart:
            there is no God
          </quote>
          .
          Therefore that God exists is not self-evident.
          Furthermore:
          that which is proved by someone:
          is not self-evident.
          But the saints have attempted to prove that God exists.
          Therefore it is not self-evident.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e488">
          Moreover 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e492">
            blessed Anselm by that definition
          </ref>
          God is that than which nothing greater can be thought.
          And other saints and even philosophers attempt to prove and demonstrate that God exists:
          but nothing demonstrable is self-evident.
          Therefore that God exists is not self-evident.
          If therefore that God exists is not self-evident,
          but is held only from faith:
          the aforementioned infidels negatively cannot divine that God exists,
          and much less that he is one and the other supernatural matters of faith.
          Therefore by themselves they cannot overcome their ignorance.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e524">
          Similarly they do not have anyone whom they might question,
          by whom or by whom they might be taught (as we suppose) 
          since all are lacking faith and all worship idols.
          Indeed they have their priests:
          and their theologians:
          their prophets or diviners who long before things come announce the future to them:
          whom they hold in the greatest reverence and devotion.
          Who nevertheless,
          laboring under the same ignorance,
          teach things contrary to the faith.
          Finally they have their kings,
          lords and magistrates who by their laws foolishly command that that religion and the worship of idols and ceremonies be observed:
          thus relying on public authority.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e571">
          For the error of the people confirmed by the prince's authority makes law,
          and excuses as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e577">
            l. Barbarius .ff. de officio presidis
          </ref>
          .
          And they without doubt render their errors probable.
          For the probable is according to 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e587">
            the Philosopher in the first book of the Topics
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e592">
            first book of the Rhetoric
          </ref>
          
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Qd1e594">
            That which seems so to all or to the majority,
            or to the wise.
            And to these either all or most,
            or the most famous and approved
          </quote>
          .
          These are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e604">
          And what is thus probable is called morally certain.
          For they are not bound to wander through the world that they might seek the wise men of other nations,
          by whose counsel or authority the opinion which they happen to follow might be rendered probable.
          But it suffices to consult their wise men and elders:
          or to follow their examples or teachings.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-d1e624">
          Since therefore infidels negatively worshipping idols can neither teach themselves nor have others from whom those things which are of faith might be taught:
          but rather all the wise men,
          kings,
          satraps,
          magistrates and all the peoples and all individual commoners:
          hold,
          profess and follow that religion of the most ancient custom supported by habit,
          and thus have sufficient impediments:
          it is manifest that such error or ignorance is invincible and probable and thus the cause of the act and which causes involuntariness:
          and consequently lacks fault.
          For he is not judged to err or be deceived who follows public law.
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Rd1e663">
            l. nihil consensui ff. de regulis iuris
          </ref>
          .
          Therefore infidels negatively would be punished illicitly merely because they worship idols,
          at least by human judgment.
          And thus without doubt 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e263-Nd1e675">
            Innocent
          </name>
          is mistaken.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>