<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 22 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 22 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-04-12">Apr 12, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a 
          <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
          Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
          </ref>
          </p>

        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 
        guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>

      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-04-12" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>

        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="102-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Hd1e97">Chapter 22 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e99">
          Chapter 22.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e104">
          Again 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e108">
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Nd1e109">Augustine of Ancona</name>
          </ref>
           argues that pagans sinning against nature can be punished by the pope:
           because anyone can justly be punished for transgression of the law which he receives,
           and which he professes to observe. 
          But pagans,
           and all barbarous nations receive the law of nature and can be convicted by it:
           moreover the pope is the guardian or ought to be the guardian of the law of nature. 
          Therefore the pope can and ought to punish all pagans and barbarous nations acting 
          against the law of nature.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e134">
          To this argument we respond in three ways:
            <add place="margin-right" hand="F">
          Solution to the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e140">
          argument of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Nd1e142">Augustine of Ancona</name>
          </ref>
          </add>
           first it is true that anyone ought to be punished by the law which he receives,
           and professes,
           thus by natural law:
           yet with this distinction (namely) either by divine judgment or human judgment 
          according to the reason of each of these judgments.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e160">
          Indeed to the reason of human judgment it pertains to punish sins,
           which are committed against the natural law in sinners who are subject to human 
          judgment. 
          But to divine judgment it pertains to punish the sins of those who for some reason 
          are not subject to human judgment. 
          Whence such punishment is known to be reserved to divine judgment.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e179">
          This can be made clear thus. 
          For many nefarious crimes could be committed against the natural law and divine 
          positive law,
           of which the pope is the first defender:
           and every competent judge:
           upon whom it falls to punish these in their subjects;
           nevertheless in many cases:
           neither the pope
            <add place="margin-right" hand="F">
          Cases in which the pope cannot punish his subjects
          </add>
           nor any other judge has the power to punish such things in their own subjects:
           because they pertain precisely to divine judgment.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e206">
          And this can be exemplified in many cases. 
          One is if someone committed some crime and indeed a most grave one against natural 
          law and divine law before the pope or king alone,
           with no other witnesses present. 
          So that the pope or king alone had seen it with his own eyes.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e222">
          Certainly the pope or king could not punish it. 
          The reason for which is:
           because judgment must be made according to what is alleged and proved:
           and not according to what the judge personally saw,
           and therefore he is reserved to divine judgment,
           for in that case such a delinquent is not subject to human judgment,
           that is to the pope or to another judge's judgment,
           and the pope punishing this person would rightly hear:
           
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Qd1e241">
          who are you that judges another's servant?
           To his own master he stands or falls
          </quote>
           
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e248">
          Romans, 14
          </ref>. 
          Which in the case set forth above 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e253">
          Pope Evaristius adduces in c. nullum cl. 2. 30r. q. 5
          </ref>
           there:
           
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Qd1e259">
          we ought not to judge or condemn anyone before true and just proof:
           as the apostle testifies who says:
           who are you,
           that judges another's servant? 
          To his own master he stands or falls
          </quote>
           etc.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e271">
          Where the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e273">
          Gloss
          </ref>
           says 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Qd1e275">
          another's servant,
           that is to be judged by another,
           namely,
           by God
          </quote>. 
          The same 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e280">
          Evaristius in c. deus omnipotens .2. q. 1
          </ref>. adduces the example of the sin which the Sodomites committed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e288">
          ¶ Of this kind is the infidelity of the Saracens and Jews living in the lands of 
          Christians,
           which is opposed to the divine law which they received from God,
           and of which the pope is the principal guardian,
           as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e298">
          c. sunt quidam 25. q. 1
          </ref>. 
          Also the impiety of the Saracens is opposed to the law of nature. 
          For they worship a false prophet,
           impious,
           stained with the filth of all vices:
           they also observe certain obscene ceremonies opposed to the law of nature. 
          Nevertheless they are not punished by the pope or by another prince,
           because the punishment of those sins is reserved to divine judgment,
           nor does punishment pertain to the pope:
           or to another human judge. 
          because in those sins they are not subject to any men.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e326">
          And therefore the 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e330">
          doctors in c. quod super his de voto.
          </ref>
           and in other places say that being a Jew is a sin before God:
           who will punish the crime:
           but not before men. 
          For among men that crime is not punished,
           but is reserved to divine judgment. 
          To be a Jew (they say) is in itself an offense,
           namely,
           with respect to God and to eternal punishment:
           but not to the judge and contentious forum,
           and thus it is not punishable by men.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e356">
          Thus teaches 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e359">
          Bartholus in l. ppud iulianum, § 1
          </ref>. 
          And there 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e363">
          Iasso § constat, 5th column
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e365">
          Ludovicus Romanus in l. multum ff. de verborum obligationibus
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e372">
          Ioanes de Anania in c. presenti: in principio
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e378">
          extrauagantium de Iudaeis
          </ref>. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e380">
          Felinus in c. multorum, 2nd column, same title
          </ref>. 
          And other doctors also hold the same. 
          The same of the Saracens,
           Arabs and other pagans. 
          For neither is their superstition punished by human Christian judges:
           but is reserved to God,
           as is clear from the above.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e396">
          ¶ Similarly judgment must be made concerning crimes committed by drunkards or the 
          insane. 
          For although they kill,
           blaspheme or commit other atrocities,
           they are not to be punished while the insanity or drunkenness lasts as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e409">
          <expan><abbr>clemen</abbr><choice><ex cert="high">tina</ex></choice></expan>
           si furiosus. de homicidis
          </ref>. 
          For an insane person can suffer injury but not cause it .l. illud ff. de iniuriis. 
          For their offenses are judged no differently than if they had been committed by 
          fortuitous accident.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e426">
          If however a man is intoxicated or falls into insanity through his own fault by 
          engaging in an illicit thing:
           then they are guilty of crimes:
           therefore they will render an account to God. 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e434">
          Saint Thomas 2a 2ae q. 64, article 2, q
          </ref>. 
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e441">
          4º. sententiarum distinctio 17, q. 2, article 2. q. 24, 2m
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e447">
          Because when someone becomes intoxicated through his own fault:
           the fault committed by him is in some way voluntary:
           just as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e455">
          if someone bent a 
          <subst hand="AB">
          <del rend="strikethrough">javelin</del>
          <add place="above-line">bow</add>
          </subst>
          </ref>
          :
           not looking first whether there was anyone who could be 
          <subst hand="AB">
          <del rend="strikethrough">struck</del>
          <add place="above-line">wounded</add>
          </subst>
          ,
           just as 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e476">
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Nd1e477">Lamech</name>
           did,
           who by such accident killed 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Nd1e479">Cain</name>
          </ref>. 
          By the same reasoning one who lusts after another's wife is guilty before God:
           nevertheless he is not punished by human judgment;
           a similar example is assigned in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e492">
          c. si quis insaniens. 15. q. 1
          </ref>. 
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e497">
          c. inebriauerunt
          </ref>. 
          And in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e501">
          c. sane
          </ref>. 
          Similar to these are those who wish to become rich from others' property,
           and those who possess others' property are liable to restitution.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e514">
          Also those who possess in bad faith. 
          For although they are not punished by human judges,
           nevertheless before God,
           they are guilty of crime.
          <add place="margin-left" hand="F">
          Hadrian
          </add>
           About these matters 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e524">
          Adrian the Florentine Roman pontiff wrote a quodlibet (namely) quodlibet 1. article 2.
          </ref>
           where he writes four propositions quite suitable to this treatise. 
          Of this number are also carnal offenses of children,
           who are not capable of deceit:
           they are not punished by law as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e540">
          c. 1. de delictis Puerorum
          </ref>. 
          Whence a minor under twelve years cannot be accused of adultery. 
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e549">
          l. minor. ff. ad legem luliam de adulteriis
          </ref>.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e552">
          Nevertheless they sin mortally before God if they are capable of deceit. 
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e558">
          c. firmissime 15. q. 1
          </ref>.
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e563">
          c. 1. de delictis puerorum
          </ref>.
          Where it is also proved that if children steal,
           lie,
           or swear falsely,
           which crimes are against the law of nature:
           they are guilty of crime before God,
           if they are capable of deceit. 
          Which happens in some in the seventh year of age.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-d1e580">
          But by human judgment they are not punished unless they are close to puberty. 
          As is noted in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e588">
          said c. 1
          </ref>. 
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e590">
          in § pupillus. institutionum: de inutilibus stipulationibus
          </ref>, 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e329-Rd1e596">
          gloss in §. in suma de obligationibus quae ex delicto nascuntur
          </ref>.
        </p>

	    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>