<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 1 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolome de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 1 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-07-09">July 9, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0
          guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-09" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="11-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Hd1e97">Chapter 1 [Bnf 12926 Translation]</head>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-d1e99">
          Apology against the persecutors and slanderers of the peoples of the new world
          discovered in the ocean:
          of the most reverend lord Sir Brother Bartholomew de las Casas,
          former bishop of Chiapas,
          of the sacred order of preachers.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-d1e115">
          Chapter One
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-d1e120">
          Whoever teaches either by voice or in writings that the inhabitants of the new world,
          whom we commonly call Indians,
          ought to be subdued and conquered by war before the gospel is announced and preached to them:
          so that after they have been thoroughly conquered they may be instructed
          and hear the word of God:
          they err grievously concerning two things.
          <pb ed="#P" n="11-v"/>
          First concerning divine and human law,
          misusing divine words:
          doing violence to the scriptures,
          and to the decrees of the pontiff:
          and to the traditions of the holy fathers:
          and again they err when they adduce histories,
          which are nothing other than mere fables:
          and most shameless trifles:
          by which the most hostile enemies of the miserable Indian people,
          most falsely slander them.
          Moreover they err concerning the meaning of the decree or bull of Pope Alexander VI,
          whose words they corrupt and distort,
          in support of their opinion,
          as will be clear through what follows.
          Again their error and ignorance is proven most clearly:
          because they make judgments about things pertaining to an infinite multitude of mortals
          and the vast expanses of the widest provinces:
          all of which since they do not fully know:
          it is the height of shamelessness and rashness to pronounce most serious defects about them:
          both natural:
          and concerning morals:
          condemning in general so many myriads of men:
          when in reality the great majority of them are free from such things.
          All of which things drag countless souls to destruction
          and impede the benefit of spreading the Christian religion:
          blocking the eyes of those who,
          raging with blind ambition,
          concentrate all the strength of body and mind on this one thing:
          that they may obtain wealth:
          empire:
          honors and dignities:
          and for this purpose they kill
          and tear apart with monstrous savagery
          <pb ed="#P" n="12-r"/>
          the most innocent,
          most gentle,
          harmless,
          modest peoples,
          most prepared and most ready to receive and embrace the word of God.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-d1e209">
          Who,
          I will not now say more learned in theology,
          but who is of sound mind:
          who would dare to put forth a 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e218">judgment and opinion</ref>
          so poorly Christian:
          from which so many savage wars:
          so many slaughters:
          so many bereavements:
          so many pitiable evils are produced?
          Do we not have the word of Christ:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e227" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt18_10@1-7">
            See that you do not despise one of these little ones!
          </quote>
          And
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e232" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt18_7@12-17">
            woe to him through whom scandal comes?
          </quote>
          And
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e237" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt12_30@1-13">
            he who is not with me is against me
          </quote>:
          and
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e242" source="http://scta.info/resource/lc11_23@9-13">
            he who does not gather with me scatters.
          </quote>
          And elsewhere:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e248" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt6_34@14-17">
            Sufficient for the day is its own evil
          </quote>.
          Who is so impious as to wish to incite savage,
          ambitious,
          proud,
          greedy,
          unbridled and always idle men to plunder their brothers:
          and to destroy their souls together with their goods:
          when lawful war is never permitted:
          except when waged by unavoidable necessity?
          Who therefore of sound mind will approve war against innocent,
          ignorant,
          gentle,
          modest,
          unarmed men,
          destitute of all human protection:
          when from such war arises the most certain destruction of the souls of that people,
          which
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e274">
            perishes without knowledge of God,
            without the strength of the sacraments
          </quote>,
          and the Christian religion is rendered hateful and abominable to those who survive:
          whence the end which God intends and for the attainment of which he suffered so many 
          and so great things is frustrated:
          by the impieties and atrocity which our people exercise against them with monstrous savagery?
          What opinion will that people conceive of Christ,
          the true God of Christians,
          <pb ed="#P" n="12-v"/>
          when they see Christians rage against them without any just cause at least known to them:
          nor indeed imaginable:
          and without any fault committed by them against the Christians:
          with so many slaughters,
          with so much bloodshed?
          What good can arise from these military expeditions:
          which before God who measures all things with ineffable charity
          is equal to so many evils,
          so many injuries,
          so many unprecedented calamities?
          Again,
          how will that people love,
          how will they contract friendship with our people?
          (Which is necessary,
          that they may receive our faith).
          When sons see themselves deprived of parents,
          wives of husbands,
          fathers of children and friends?
          Also when they see those whom they love wounded,
          captured,
          despoiled and reduced from an innumerable multitude to a few?
          When they see princes despoiled of their dominion,
          oppressed,
          and afflicted with miserable servitude?
          All of which things necessarily follow from war.
          Who is there who would wish the Gospel to be preached to himself in this way?
          Does not that negative precept apply generally to all men:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e344">
            what you do not wish done to you by another
          </quote>,
          see that you do not do it to another?
          And again that affirmative precept
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e354" source="http://scta.info/resource/mt7_12@1-12">
            all things whatsoever you wish that men should do to you,
            do you also to them.
          </quote>
          This any man knows,
          perceives,
          understands by the natural light impressed on our minds.
          From which it clearly appears that those who teach that those most gentle sheep
          must first be tamed by savage war by rapacious wolves before being fed by the word of God:
          err concerning things most manifest and oppose the natural law.
          <pb ed="#P" n="13-r"/>
          They also err impiously when they say these wars are just if they are waged as they ought
          to be waged;
          they think,
          I suppose,
          if they are waged moderately,
          killing only those whom it is necessary to kill so that the rest may be subdued.
          As if they held all the peoples of the new world enclosed in cages or prisons
          and wanted to slaughter them:
          as many heads of men as are usually sold in markets each day for the food and sustenance 
          of the people (to make this comparison).
          But if they would consider war and the slaughter of a frightened people:
          not for one or a hundred days:
          but lasting for ten or twenty years:
          with incredible loss of the inhabitants:
          while they wander and are hidden through groves and forests,
          scattered,
          unarmed,
          naked,
          and destitute of all human protection,
          they are slaughtered by the Spaniards,
          stripped of their fortunes,
          miserable,
          exiles,
          astonished:
          and terrified with incredible fear:
          with which the tyrants have frightened them by committing monstrous crimes.
          If those who speak such things would consider the breasts of the miserable people struck 
          with such great fear:
          that they would wish to throw themselves headlong into the deepest caverns of the earth;
          to escape the hands of these robbers:
          I do not doubt that they would speak more soberly and more wisely.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-d1e430">
          Coming therefore to the matter,
          this apology will contain two most principal things.
          First I will teach that the Reverend Doctor Sepulveda with his followers errs in law 
          in all things which he brings forth against the Indians:
          <pb ed="#P" n="13-v"/>
          and at the same time I will subjoin a response to all his arguments and to the authorities
          which he violently distorts.
          Second,
          I will teach how greatly they err in fact,
          with loss of their own souls.
          For the creator of every creature has not so despised these peoples of the new world;
          that he wished them to lack reason and made them like brute animals:
          so that they ought to be called barbarians,
          savage,
          wild and brutish:
          as these men think or pretend,
          but rather they are of such gentleness and modesty:
          that above all other peoples of the whole world they are most fit and most ready to abandon 
          the worship of idols and to receive province by province and people by people the word of God
          and the announcement of truth.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-d1e478">
          <add place="lm" hand="E">
            Response to the first argument or cause of Doctor Sepulveda
          </add>
          As to the first point,
          concerning which elsewhere we have discoursed more extensively and generally against all 
          who are infected with errors of this kind concerning the matter of unbelievers:
          but for the present,
          for some slight refutation of Sepulveda's first justification of his war:
          it should be known that according to
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e496">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e497">the Philosopher</name>
            in the 1st and 3rd books of the <title>Politics</title>
          </ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e503">the 7th of the <title>Ethics</title>
          </ref>
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e507">according to <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e509">Saint Thomas</name>
          </ref>
          and other doctors in various places:
          there are four species of barbarians.
          <add place="lm" hand="F">
            First species of barbarians when they are inhuman and savage and horrible
          </add>
          First,
          a barbarian,
          the word being taken improperly and broadly:
          signifies any savage,
          inhuman,
          wild,
          fierce man,
          abhorrent to human reason either by anger or by nature:
          so that,
          having cast aside human modesty,
          gentleness and moderation:
          <pb ed="#P" n="14-r"/>
          he becomes hard,
          rough,
          quarrelsome,
          intolerable,
          savage,
          and gives himself headlong to crimes:
          which only wild beasts dwelling in the forests would perpetrate.
          Speaking of this kind of barbarians,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e542">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e543">the philosopher</name>
            in book 1, chapter 2 of the <title>Politics</title>
          </ref>
          says:
          that just as man following right reason and the best institutions excels all animals:
          so if he deviates from right reason of judgment and from laws,
          he is the most impious,
          worst and most inhuman of all animals:
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e560">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e561">Boethius</name>
            also speaks of these in book 1, prose 4 of the <title>Consolation</title> where
          </ref>
          he calls the courtiers of the tyrant king Theodoric barbarians because of their savage
          and insatiable greed.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e571">
            How often (he says) I protected with interposed danger of my authority the wretches whom
            the unpunished greed of the barbarians vexed with infinite false accusations
          </quote>.
          Again also in
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e581">the second book of Maccabees, chapter 15</ref>
          mention is made of barbarians of this kind:
          for when
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e585">Nicanor</name>
          the savage and fierce tyrant wished to join battle with
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e592">Judas Maccabeus</name>
          at Jamaria on the Sabbath day:
          certain Jews who were with him said to him:
          do not do this so fiercely and barbarously,
          that is savagely and inhumanly,
          and in this sense both Greeks and Latins and whoever can be called most civilized in their
          way of life are called barbarians:
          if they approach the Scythians in savagery of morals:
          whose province was particularly called barbarous,
          according to
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e610">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e611">Isidore</name>
            <title>Etymologies</title> Book 14, chapter 4
          </ref>.
          because of the savage and inhuman morals of the people,
          and from the number of these our Spaniards are truly not foreign:
          indeed from the most monstrous works which they have exercised against those nations:
          they have surpassed all barbarians.
          To this kind of barbarians belongs he who,
          stirred up by anger or hatred or some other vehement passion,
          defends something seditiously:
          <pb ed="#P" n="14-v"/>
          forgetful of reason and decorum.
          Of these speaks
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e636">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e637">Gregory</name>
            <title>Epistles</title> Book 2, chapter 69
          </ref>.
          and
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e642">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e643">Gratian</name> c. Quanto apostolice. dist. 63
          </ref>.
          where speaking of a sedition that arose among the Milanese concerning the election of a 
          certain bishop he says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e654">
            many of the Milanese,
            forced by barbaric ferocity,
            persist
          </quote>,
          etc.
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Rd1e661">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Nd1e662">The Philosopher</name>
            in the 7th book of the <title>Ethics</title>, chapter 1
          </ref>
          calls barbarians of this kind beasts with these words:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e52-Qd1e669">
            but bestiality is especially among the barbarians and because of illness and bereavements:
            thus we defame them above others (that is) saying or asserting that they are bestial 
            and barbarous
          </quote>.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>