<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 30 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 30 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2025-05-03">May 03, 2025</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>
            Published under a 
            <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
              Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)
            </ref>
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition. 
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2025-05-03" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>
            Created file for the first time.
          </p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="135-v"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Hd1e97">
          Chapter 30 [Bnf 12926 Transcription - English Translation]
        </head>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e99">
          Chapter 30.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e104">
          ¶ To the argument (namely) that when a city is condemned by just war,
          all its inhabitants are presumed to be enemies,
          this is false. 
          For a presumption of law ought not to operate in matters that are impossible. 
          For who would presume that infants,
          weak in strength and counsel and lacking all malice,
          are guilty? 
          Who would suspect that trembling women gave cause for war,
          unless it is established that they aided the war with resources,
          which very rarely happens?
          Therefore it is a natural demonstration that these are innocent. 
          Therefore the contrary presumption in this case operates nothing. 
          As in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e136">
            c. Veritate 8. distin.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e142">
          Moreover,
          that women and children are innocent and thus do not deserve punishment is proven by 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e148">
            divine law, Deut. 20
          </ref>. 
          Where the Lord commands the Hebrews that when they would attack any city for a just cause,
          such as an injury inflicted upon them,
          they should spare the women and infants,
          but use military force against the men;
          which God would not have commanded unless it were manifest,
          at least for the greater part,
          that such a class of persons are not enemies but innocent. 
          Therefore these are innocent by divine testimony.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e174">
          Secondly,
          it is proven from 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e178">
            Innocent in d. c. Dilectus
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e182">
            d. c. Graue
          </ref>
          and from the doctors in both places,
          who suppose as manifest that in any people there are very many innocents. 
          Then if perhaps war is waged among Christians,
          in any city there are priests,
          monks and nuns,
          and many others dedicated to divine worship. 
          There are farmers,
          workers,
          foreign merchants,
          pilgrims,
          whom the law judges to be innocent,
          so much so that they are immune from all military force by decree of the church,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e208">
            c. ennouamus. de tregua et pace
          </ref>,
          so much so that if they are despoiled by soldiers,
          the soldiers are bound to restitution and sin mortally.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e220">
          Since therefore in any city there are very many innocents,
          it is false that when a city is condemned,
          all who are within are presumed to be enemies,
          and consequently soldiers ought to abstain from inflicting violence on persons who present themselves as innocent,
          which the greater leaders of armies ought to admonish exactly and severely,
          lest they wish to become participants in the same sin and harm.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e242">
          Nevertheless,
          it is necessary to remember that confused opinion of the doctors,
          that when a city is condemned to be plundered in war,
          namely just war,
          soldiers are not bound to examine who are the guilty and who truly are innocent,
          because as they say,
          then accidentally (that is) beyond intention,
          it is to kill innocents,
          which is true when,
          if some circumstance or act were omitted,
          victory in that just war could not be had or the enemies would not be subdued. 
          And nevertheless it happens in that act or circumstance that innocents are found.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e268">
          But if such an act or circumstance is not necessary but can be excused,
          without doubt they are guilty of the death and other harms of such innocents. 
          Let there be an example of this circumstance:
          imagine an army making a just war,
          rushing upon a condemned city by decree of the prince to be plundered;
          the soldiers run through the forums and regions of the city,
          killing all who meet them.
          Certainly then if they kill a merchant or pilgrim,
          they do not sin.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e323">
          For they are not bound at that time to examine whether the one who meets them is an inhabitant of the city or a stranger,
          lest while doing this,
          victory comes into danger,
          and the victors,
          with fortune changed,
          remain defeated. 
          And therefore accidentally innocents are killed then,
          not per se.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e348">
          This however must be understood unless those who meet them are manifestly among those who,
          as innocents,
          must be spared,
          such as if it be a boy,
          woman or old man,
          or an unarmed man,
          or one venerable in priestly or monastic garb. 
          For if soldiers kill these,
          they sin mortally. 
          For now they inflict violence on them not accidentally but per se and from principal intent.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e371">
          And that they are bound to presume through such probable signs that such persons are innocent,
          and thus to abstain from inflicting evils upon them,
          is evident,
          because the harms that are inflicted in war are not of such small moment that in doubt or easily and indiscriminately,
          without fear of offending God and neighbor,
          they can be inflicted. 
          Therefore Christian warriors are bound to presume those whom they see appear innocent by such signs rather than harmful,
          even in battle.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e400">
          ¶ Let there be another example:
          women,
          children,
          old men,
          and other innocents have taken refuge in some citadel. 
          Certainly if it is not highly necessary for the favorable outcome of the whole war that that citadel be attacked,
          it would be a most grave sin to destroy the citadel either by flames or by tunnels,
          with great slaughter of the innocent as is necessary. 
          For this would be to kill innocents per se. 
          If however it is necessary,
          they would be killed accidentally and beyond intention.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e424">
          Which is proven because war is never licit except when it is necessary,
          so that it can in no way be excused. 
          For it is a plague and an atrocious calamity of the human race,
          as in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e435">
            c. s. quos. 23. q. 4
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e438">
            c. ad apostolice de re judi. libro 6
          </ref>
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e443">
            c. Pisanis. de restitu. spolia.
          </ref>
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e449">
          For war is a work impious in itself and of the third kind of acts,
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e453">
            ch. 28b above
          </ref>,
          unless it is rendered just by circumstance,
          namely necessity,
          as author 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e467">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e468">
              Augustine
            </name>
          </ref>
          says in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e473">
            c. noli. 23. q. 1
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Qd1e475">
            War must be of necessity,
            so that God may free from necessity and preserve in peace
          </quote>—
          these are his words.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e483">
          Moreover 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e486">
            Pope Nicholas
          </name>
          in c. si nulla 23. q. 8 says: 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e490">
            if no necessity prevails,
            not only in Lenten time but also at all times one must abstain from battles. 
            But if unavoidable urgency presses,
            even in Lenten time,
            for the defense both of oneself and of the fatherland or of paternal laws,
            preparations for wars must without doubt be undertaken
          </ref>—
          and so forth. These are his words. 
          The divine words agree with these: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Qd1e511">
            if it be possible,
            as much as depends on you,
            living peaceably with all men
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e519">
            ad Roma. 12
          </ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e522">
          Likewise 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e524">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e525">
              Cicero
            </name>, 
            <title>
              On Duties
            </title>
            book 1
          </ref>
          never approves war unless unavoidable necessity presses,
          so that it can in no way be avoided. 
          Therefore if a citadel filled with innocent people can not be destroyed without great danger to the victory of the whole war,
          certainly a prince attacking it and destroying it with bloody assault is guilty before the Supreme Judge of killing innocents per se. 
          For the circumstance is lacking by which war is rendered just,
          namely necessity. 
          Therefore he and the soldiers will give account to God for all the evils that happen there and will be bound to restitution.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e559">
          This truth is confirmed from the words of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e563">
            St. Thomas
          </name>,
          who,
          expounding those words of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e567">
            the Apostle
          </name>,
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Qd1e569">
            we can do nothing against the truth
          </quote>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e575">
            2 Cor. 13
          </ref>,
          says that if the apostle were to punish the innocent,
          he would act against truth and justice. 
          But to act against justice is mortal sin,
          as author 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e586">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e587">
              St. Thomas
            </name>
            says, 
            2a 2ae. q. 59. ar. 4
          </ref>,
          and those seizing anything in such acts sin mortally and are bound to restitution.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e599">
          Therefore the innocent are not to be killed,
          whether few,
          and much less many,
          so that a few guilty may be punished. 
          For evil things are not to be done that good may come thereof, 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e609">
            Romans 3
          </ref>. 
          Nor indeed does God wish these evils to be compensated by such gain, 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e617">
            according to 
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e619">
              Augustine
            </name>
            on 
            <title>
              Psalm
            </title>
            146
          </ref>,
          and it is read in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e625">
            33. q. 5. c. 1
          </ref>: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Qd1e630">
            For (he says) God does not wish such harm to be compensated by such gain;
            surely this compensation is most dangerously admitted
          </quote>,
          and in 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e637">
            alia parte 14. dist. c. quod ait
          </ref>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e640">
          And there is a 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e644">
            notable gloss
          </ref>,
          and it agrees with 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e646">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e647">
              St. Thomas
            </name>
            2a 2ae. q. 26. ar. 4 in corpore
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e652">
            2m.
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e655">
            q. 43. ar. 7, ad 5um
          </ref>,
          where he says that it is licit to no one to sin venially that another may not sin mortally. 
          Which also 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e667">
            <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e668">
              Augustine
            </name>
            asserts in c. faciat homo 22. q. 2
          </ref>
          in these words: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Qd1e674">
            let a man do even for the temporal safety of men what he can;
            but when it has come to this,
            that he cannot provide for such safety except by sinning,
            now he does not have what to do
          </quote>.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e686">
          And 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e688">
            c. sequenti
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e693">
            c. nequis arbitretur
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e695">
            c. Primum
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e700">
            extra de vsuris. c. super eo
          </ref>
          and 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e703">
            extra ne cleri. vel monachi. c. magnopere
          </ref>. 
          Indeed,
          says 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e708">
            St. Thomas
          </name>,
          a man ought rather to choose death and atrocious torment than to sin even venially,
          thus 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e714">
            2a 2ae: q. 110. ar. 3. ad 3um
          </ref>
          and in other places.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e720">
          Hence arises the rule that when evil and good are so conjoined that from the good which I wish to do,
          evil must necessarily arise,
          or almost always evil arises,
          if the evil is greater than the good which I wish to do,
          the good must always be omitted lest evil arise from it. 
          The reason is that if anyone endowed with the greatest virtues is guilty of the least mortal sin,
          he will be damned eternally.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e749">
          But 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e753">
            St. Thomas
          </name>
          and 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e755">
            Augustine
          </name>
          understand this rule even when venial sin arises from it. 
          Likewise this rule must be understood not only in ourselves,
          but also when we wish to do a benefit to someone,
          taking care lest evil come to him;
          for we ought to examine whether from that good which we wish to do for him there arises a greater evil than that which we wish to avoid.
        </p>
        
        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-d1e775">
          Thus 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e777">
            St. Thomas quodlib. 3. ar. 11. ad. 5m
          </ref>,
          where he says thus: 
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Qd1e784">
            then only should some good be omitted on account of consequent evil when the consequent evil would be much greater than the good and would happen more frequently
          </quote>—
          these are the words of 
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Nd1e794">
            St. Thomas
          </name>
          formally. 
          And see 
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e434-Rd1e796">
            Abulensis on Matthew ch. 23. q. 19
          </ref>.
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>