<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chapter 14 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] [English Translation]</title>
        <author ref="#per-bdlcbd">Bartolomé de las Casas</author>
        <respStmt>
          <name ref="#jeffreycwitt">Jeffrey C. Witt</name>
          <resp>Transcription Editor</resp>
          <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Chapter 14 [Bnf 12926 Transcription] [English Translation]</title>
          <date when="2024-10-23">Oct 23, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="P" n="cod-dlc9qq">Bnf Latin 12926</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/diplomatic.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines
          for a diplomatic edition. This file is an English translation of the original Latin.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-10-23" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#P" n="72-r"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223">
        <head xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Hd1e97">Chapter 14 [Bnf 12926 Transcription]</head>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e99">
          Chapter 14.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e104">
          ¶ Furthermore, <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Nd1e106">Sepúlveda</name>,
          in support of his opinion,
          twists the words of the blessed <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e110">Cyprian,
          written in the book To Fortunatus, on Exhortation to Martyrdom.</ref>
          There <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Nd1e117">Cyprian</name>, citing <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e119">Deuteronomy 13,</ref>
          reports that the Lord commanded that a city
          universally worshipping idols be destroyed.
          Cyprian argues thus:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Qd1e128">if in the time of the old law,
          before the coming of Christ,
          a city worshipping false gods was punished in this way,
          how much more will the same be done today,
          and the same commandment of the Lord be observed?
          Since the Lord himself,
          having become man in word and deed,
          has taught us the truth and the worship of the true God?</quote>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e142">
          By this authority,
          <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Nd1e148">Sepúlveda</name> — with open display, as they say —
          incites the Spanish people to the destruction of the Indians,
          teaching that those who shed the blood of that people
          consecrate their hands to God:
          on the analogy of that earlier time,
          in which a city that had apostatized through idolatry
          from the true faith in God which it had previously received
          was to be destroyed by divine command,
          as is found in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e172">Deut. 13.</ref>
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e175">
          And indeed a sentence worthy of eternal fire.
          For if,
          in order to ward off so many slaughters and losses of human life —
          indeed so many destructions and devastations of peoples and multitudes,
          and innumerable evils henceforth irreparable,
          perpetrated by tyrants in that world up to now —
          the very many laws, rules, precepts, prohibitions,
          threats, and penalties issued by the kings of Spain profited nothing;
          the gentle entreaties of preachers of the Word of God,
          offered both in season and out of season,
          together with the most vehement reproaches
          and solemn warnings of the terrible day of final judgment
          and of infernal punishments, profited nothing;
          the denial of the sacraments by confessors profited nothing;
          the censures and excommunications of prelates profited nothing —
          none of these things, I say, profited to make
          so many evils cease,
          but rather they grew worse and far more harmful day by day —
          what will befall the wretched,
          peaceful, gentle, <gap reason="blank" extent="6" unit="characters"/> and unarmed people
          at the hands of such enemies,
          who thirst for their blood in order to increase their own gold,
          once the plunderers should perceive that there are those who say
          that in committing those crimes
          they consecrate their sacrilegious and blood-stained hands to the true God —
          just as was said in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e237">Exodus 32,</ref>
          concerning those who by the command of Moses
          carried out vengeance upon those who worshipped the golden calf?
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e245">
          O the profound darkness of a man
          who seeks to catch popular favor,
          or strives most dangerously to flatter royal ears!
          ¶ And although this error has been answered
          by what we adduced in the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e258">preceding chapter</ref>
          regarding the statement of <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e264">Nicholas of Lyra,</ref>
          nevertheless it has seemed good to answer it more fully
          by explaining the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e270">opinion of blessed Cyprian</ref>
          in what follows.
          For the clarification of this,
          it must be observed that the entire intention
          of <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e280"><name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Nd1e281">blessed Cyprian</name> in that work</ref>
          concerns the exhortation of Catholics
          to persevere in the faith of Christ once received,
          and to prefer to endure every torment and thus martyrdom
          rather than to depart from the faith.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e293">
          Hence, first in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e295">chapter 6,</ref>
          he teaches Christians that,
          with death and every torment despised,
          they ought to profess Christ the true God.
          Adducing that passage of <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e303">Matthew 10:</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Qd1e306">he who loves father or mother more than me
          is not worthy of me.
          For having been redeemed and brought to life by the blood of Christ,
          we ought to place nothing before Christ.
          For in the Gospel the Lord says:
          he who loves father or mother more than me is not worthy of me</quote>
          and so forth.
          And in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e321">chapter 7</ref>
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Qd1e323">he says: those snatched from the jaws of the devil
          and freed from the snares of the world
          ought not to return to the world again.</quote>
          And he adduces that passage of <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e330">Exodus 14</ref>
          concerning the children of Israel wishing to return to Egypt.
          And in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e337">chapter 8 of that same work, Cyprian</ref> says
          that one must persist and persevere in faith and virtue
          and the completion of heavenly and spiritual grace.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e346">
          And because in his time many Christians
          who had embraced Christian truth
          were returning to the worship of idols,
          he begins in <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e356">chapter 10</ref>
          to teach that an idol is not God,
          and that neither man nor idol ought to be worshipped
          besides God.
          In the <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e363">second chapter</ref>
          he proves that the worship of latria is owed to God alone,
          and that every sacrifice is worthy of him alone.
          In the third chapter he teaches what threats
          the Lord announced against those
          from the Jewish people who would worship idols
          — for which he adduces several authorities —
          and moreover in the fourth chapter
          he strives to prove that the Lord very rarely grants pardon
          for sins committed through idolatry
          once a man has recognized him through faith.
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Qd1e390">Moses (says Cyprian) intercedes in Exodus for the people
          and does not obtain it:
          I pray, he says, O Lord,
          this people has sinned,
          they have committed a great sin,
          they have made for themselves gods of gold</quote>
          and so forth.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e402">
          ¶ Likewise, <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e404">in the fifth chapter,</ref>
          he reports that the Lord was so angered against
          those who had apostatized from the faith through idolatry
          that he commanded that all of them be killed outright,
          even if a son or brother were the one urging others
          to return to idolatry — <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e421">Deuteronomy 13.</ref>
          For so Scripture says:
          that if your brother should entreat you,
          or your son, or your daughter,
          or your wife who lies in your bosom,
          or your friend who is equal to your own soul,
          secretly saying: let us go and serve other gods,
          the gods of the nations —
          do not consent to him, and do not listen to him,
          and let your eye not spare him,
          and your hand shall be upon him,
          and so forth.
          Then, he says, the Lord commands there
          that if all the Jews of some Hebrew city
          were to worship idols,
          they should be utterly destroyed.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e445">
          For he is not speaking of cities
          that were outside the promised land,
          but of those inhabited by the Jews,
          as appears there.
          For the Lord says:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Qd1e467">if you hear in one of your cities,
          which the Lord your God will give you to dwell in,
          that certain sons of Belial have gone out from among you
          and have turned away the inhabitants of their city,
          and said: let us go and serve other gods —
          inquire diligently, and when the truth of the matter is established,
          if you find it to be certain,
          you shall immediately strike the inhabitants of that city
          with the edge of the sword,
          and destroy it</quote>
          and so forth. Deuteronomy 13.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e492">
          And he speaks of the Hebrews themselves
          dwelling in the same city.
          As is clear from the phrase there:
          "in one of your cities,"
          and there: "and they have turned away" —
          that is, from the faith to the worship of idols —
          "the inhabitants of your city."
          Likewise it is clear that he is not speaking
          of Canaanite idolaters,
          since at the entry of the Israelites into the promised land
          all the native and natural inhabitants were to be killed
          by divine command.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e515">
          Therefore <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e517">Cyprian, citing</ref>
          <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e520">chapter 13 of Deuteronomy,</ref>
          has in mind those who,
          having heard and received the evangelical truth,
          were returning to the worship of idols.
          For he teaches that these are to be punished,
          and that to punish them is greatly pious and holy;
          and thus the prince is bound to punish them,
          even if they bring his rule into danger.
          Hence Cyprian argues holily and with great learning,
          from the lesser to the greater, saying:
          <quote xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Qd1e539">if before the coming of Christ
          these precepts concerning the worship of God
          and the spurning of idols were observed,
          how much more must they be observed
          after the coming of Christ,
          since he, in coming,
          not only urged us by words alone,
          but also by deeds</quote>
          and so forth — this is what Cyprian teaches,
          and we gladly affirm and profess it.
          But what, I ask, does this have to do with the people of the Indians,
          who have not even heard the evangelical truth by report,
          much less received it,
          and who moreover are innocent in warfare
          and most inclined to receive the truth —
          a people to be nurtured with Christian charity
          rather than to be persecuted with arms
          in a diabolical and more than pagan fashion?
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e578">
          ¶ <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e580">Gratian, moreover, began that chapter
          from the words "if you hear":
          Si audieris, 23. q. 5.</ref>
          from which the adversaries draw their fragile argument against the Indians.
          Gratian adduces that chapter together with the preceding ones
          in order to prove that even after the coming of Christ
          evildoers are to be punished with death
          by those holding legitimate power in the commonwealth,
          without violation of <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e608">that precept,
          "you shall not kill."</ref>
          And this is <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Nd1e613">Gratian's</name> final intention.
        </p>

        <p xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-d1e619">
          ¶ It appears therefore manifestly
          how <name xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Nd1e623">the Reverend Doctor Sepúlveda</name>
          has corrupted <ref xml:id="lca8s8-d1e223-Rd1e628">the opinion of blessed Cyprian,</ref>
          as well as the testimonies of other saints,
          dragging it to a meaning contrary to it.
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>